<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>DIYnamics</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://diynamics.github.io/</id><updated>2018-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>El Marino Language School Science Fair</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/el-marino-science-fair.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-04-27:/el-marino-science-fair.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team taught basics of rotating fluids using our beloved tables, frozen cans of tomato paste, inflatable globes, and LEGO Batmen at a really cool science fair.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-sean.jpg" width="600" title="Sean leading a demo" alt="Sean leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean leads a demonstration of "baroclinic instability" (a.k.a. the
combination of a strong temperature contrast and rotation that
generates storms on Earth) to El Marino students and parents.  They're
so focused!  We're now using a LEGO Power Functions remote control to
reduce the rotation rate for this demonstration, which makes these
eddies larger and therefore more engaging.  Even with the bigger
eddies, we were also able to shrink the tank compared to previous
attempts, which allows for a little more breathing room.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 27, 2018, Ashna, Sean, and Spencer of the DIYnamics team
performed hands-on demonstrations for dozens of kids at the 23rd
annual science fair of the &lt;a href="https://elmarino.ccusd.org/"&gt;El Marino Language
School&lt;/a&gt;, a foreign language-focused
elementary school in the Culver City Unified School District, in
Culver City, CA.  In a cool twist on the traditional elementary
school-level science fair, El Marino's fair featured science posters
and demonstrations both from their own students and from multiple
science groups at UCLA.  So the students got to show off their awesome
science and simultaneously learn about the just-as-awesome science
conducted at the university level.  And they even fed us dinner!
Naturally, this was an event that DIYnamics wasn't going to miss!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-ashna.jpg" width="600" title="Ashna leading a demo" alt="Ashna leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our newest DIYnamicist, Ashna, with two excited young El Marino
students eager to drop dye into our tanks.  But before they do so,
Ashna makes sure that they make a hypothesis about what they will see
in each tank.  Then, once the dye has been injected, she asks them to
describe what they are seeing, to decide if their hypothesis was
right, and then ultimately link the results back to the underlying
science we're trying to teach.  This gets participants engaged in
active learning throughout the demonstration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We came equipped with a handful of our DIYnamics rotating table
platforms, our handy globe, and some LEGO Batman figurines to teach
the students and parents who came by about how Earth's rotation and
temperature contrasts combine to generate the weather patterns that we
know and (sometimes) love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-spencer-sean.jpg" width="600" title="Spencer and Sean leading a demo" alt="Spencer and Sean leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spencer using an inflatable globe with a LEGO figurine (LEGO Batman,
to be specific) taped onto the north pole to make the connection with
students between the real world and the tanks on the table.  The
DIYnamics table farthest back in this image has another LEGO Batman
taped at its center, sitting on top of a polar stereographic map
(a.k.a. a map centered on the North Pole).  Spencer spins the globe
showing that Batman spins with it, and at the same time Sean spins the
table showing that Batman spins the exact same way there!  We've found
this really helps students make the otherwise difficult connection
between tanks of water and the real world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parents were a great bunch too!  One father told us that he is a
pilot, and that our explanation of weather systems using the DIYnamics
was the best one he's ever heard!  Pilots really need to know the
weather to fy safely, so that's no small compliment (if we may say
so).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-bci-closeup.jpg" width="600" title="El Marino students getting a closeup look at baroclinic instability" alt="El Marino students getting a closeup look at baroclinic instability"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;El Marino students eagerly awaiting the onset of "storms" driven by
the frozen can of tomato paste in the center of the table.  Initially,
all of the blue dye was injected next to the can and all of the red
dye outside of it.  But you can see that the blue dye has moved
outward in places, while the red dye has moved in toward the can.
(Don't be alarmed by the red patch on the hand pointing down at the
tank...one downside of using red dye is that when it gets on hand it
looks like blood!  No DIYnamicists (or students or parents) were
harmed in the making of this demonstration.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Erika M. von Euw of UCLA and the El Marino Language
School PTA for organizing, the many student and parent volunteers at
the event, and most of all the great kids and parents who came to our
table.  We're crossing our fingers that we get a repeat invitation for
next year's fair!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics tables used in an undergraduate+graduate level course</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/ucla-epss-class.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-04-26:/ucla-epss-class.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics has now officially been implemented into undergraduate and graduate teaching, as part of a "lab day" in a UCLA course.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/jmitch-course-tables2018.jpg" width="600" title="DIYnamics tables after the demo, with students and Prof. Mitchell at the next station" alt="DIYnamics tables after the demo, with students and Prof. Mitchell at the next station"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students in the background at one of Prof. Mitchell's demonstration
stations.  They had just finished at the DIYnamics station, where we
used our simple tables to teach some of the basic properties of
rotating fluids.  Spencer can't multi-task well enough to have gotten
a picture of the students while they were at our station, but they
really were just there, we swear!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 26, 2018, DIYnamics marked a major milestone by being
incorporated into undergraduate and graduate-level curricula.
Prof. Jonathan Mitchell of the UCLA Department of Earth, Planetary,
and Space Sciences and Department of Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences
(that's a mouthful!) invited us to use the DIYnamics materials as part
of a "lab demos" day in his course to teach some basic principles of
rotating fluids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With only one of us (Spencer) there, it was difficult to get pictures
of the students at the DIYnamics station in the moment.  So the
picture above showing the aftermath --- with dye in both the rotating
and non-rotating tables, and the students moved on to the next station
--- will have to suffice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shows that the DIYnamics materials can be effective teaching
tools from the elementary school to graduate levels!  Of course, the
level of complexity of the accompanying explanations has to be
tailored to the audience: for early elementary school students, we're
content with the students recognizing that things are different when
you rotate or not, whereas at the university level we're connecting
the demonstations to concepts like the Coriolis parameter, solid body
rotation, spinup times, the Rossby number, and baroclinic instability.
But the physical demonstrations we perform are essentially identical
across these levels!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to Prof. Mitchell for allowing us to take part in his
class, Alex Gonzalez of UCLA and the Jet Propulsion Laboratory for his
assistance with the DIYnamics station, Henry Gonzalez, Emily Hawkins,
and Helen Parish of the EPSS department for their work on the awesome
stably stratified convection station, and to all of the students for
indulging us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More DIYnamics at the university level&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prof. Mitchell's class was a great way to inaugurate DIYnamics' use at
the college teaching level, and we're excited for him to (hopefully!)
have us back later in the quarter to help him teach "baroclinic
instability"...they haven't gotten that far in the lectures yet.  But
our expansion into the university level isn't stopping there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/angel-video-bci-snapshot.png" width="600" title="Snapshot of a video taken by Angel Adames using his DIYnamics table" alt="Snapshot of a video taken by Angel Adames using his DIYnamics table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snapshot from the video that Prof. Adames posted to his Facebook page
using the DIYnamics table to (kind of) demonstrate baroclinic
instability.  Thanks for trying us out, Prof. Adames!  We'll help you
work out the kinks of getting that demonstration working properly.
Looks awesome!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dept.atmos.ucla.edu/stewart"&gt;Prof. Andrew Stewart&lt;/a&gt; of the
UCLA AOS Department and &lt;a href="http://clasp.engin.umich.edu/people/afadames"&gt;Prof. Ángel
Adames&lt;/a&gt; of the
University of Michigan Department of Climate and Space Science have
both purchased and successfully built their own DIYnamics tables and
intend to use them in courses they teach, also at the university
level.  Thanks both for giving us a try!  We're eager to see how their
DIYnamics-based teaching pans out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as we DIYnamics team members love putting on demonstrations
ourselves, there are only so many of us, compared to millions of
students around the world that could learn from these materials.
That's why we always try to leave behind a complete DIYnamics rotating
table kit behind at the schools we visit.  And that's why efforts like
these by other teachers and professors to use our materials themselves
are the most important thing moving forward!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="colleges"></category><category term="undergraduate"></category><category term="graduate"></category><category term="curriculum"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics featured on UCLA Physical Sciences website</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/ucla-website-story.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-03-25:/ucla-website-story.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The UCLA Division of Physical Sciences has a new article on DIYnamics on their main website and has added DIYnamics to its Outreach page.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ucla-physci-pic1" src="{filename}../images/ucla-phy-sci-site-snippet.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snippet from the UCLA Physical Sciences website with the link to the
story they commissioned about DIYnamics.  How cool is that?!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This isn't exactly an event, but it's exciting enough that we felt it
deserved a post anyways!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of March 2018, the DIYnamics project is now featured in multiple
places on the official website of the UCLA Physical Sciences Division
(link to main site &lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;;
permalink to the DIYnamics story
&lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/spinlab/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  Not only
that, they have also listed us as one of the "Year-Round Programs"
available for community and K-12 outreach on their &lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/outreach/"&gt;outreach
page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Physical Sciences Division, one of five divisions of the UCLA
College of Letters and Sciences, oversees the Atmospheric and Oceanic
Sciences Chemistry &amp;amp; Biochemistry, Earth, Planetary, and Space
Sciences, Mathematics, Physics &amp;amp; Astronomy, and Statistics
Departments, collectively home to thousands of students and hundreds
of faculty and staff.  With all of the amazing research and outreach
acivities that goes on across the division, it's a real honor for us
to be featured on their page so prominently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to Lisa Garibay of the UCLA Physical Sciences Divison for
initially taking an interest in us, writing the article, and getting
us featured on both pages.  They say any publicity is good publicity,
in which case this is absolutely fantastic publicity!  We're looking
forward to getting our materials into the hands of even more educators
thanks to these links.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="press"></category><category term="colleges"></category></entry><entry><title>UCLA Exploring Your Universe (EYU) 2017</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/eyu-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-11-05:/eyu-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team ran a booth at UCLA's massive public science fair "Exploring Your Universe," featuring demonstrations and kids building their own DIYnamics tables.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_sean.jpg" width="600" title="Sean leading a demo" alt="Sean leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean leading a demonstration using DIYnamics tables.  The farther
table has a special acryllic sidewall that enables us to fill the
whole table with water.  The nearer one uses a plastic planter tray
that costs a few dollars to achieve nearly the same thing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 5, 2017, the DIYnamics team performed hands-on
demonstrations for hundreds of kids at the annual &lt;a href="https://www.exploringyouruniverse.org/"&gt;Exploring Your
Universe&lt;/a&gt; (EYU) event at UCLA.
EYU is basically a massive science fair, with groups from nearly every
science department at UCLA, from astronomers to biochemists,
performing demonstrations to teach kids (and their parents!) about
their science.  Of course, DIYnamics had a booth where we had kids
build our tables, use them to learn about rotating fluids, and also
give more in-depth demonstrations using our larger, custom square
tank.  We had a blast showing off our equipment and teaching science
to hundreds of people in total over the course of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_norris.jpg" width="600" title="Norris helping kids build their own tables" alt="Norris helping kids build their own tables"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris helping out as several kids (and an adult!) build their own
motors for the DIYnamics table.  His table was swamped all day; kids
really loved building these!  Who doesn't love building with LEGOs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One highlight of the day was our newest activity, wherein kids got to
create the DIYnamics rotating tank kit themselves!  We provided all of
the needed LEGO parts, along with printouts of our official
instructions of how to assemble the motor.  Dozens of kids went
step-by-step through the instructions, creating the finished product
in just a few minutes every time.  We provided a little guidance here
and there, but mostly they were able to do it all on their own!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever somebody finished building their motor, we would then use it
to drive a table in a science demonstration.  The kids loved to hear
us announce their name and to see their creation used to perform a
real-world science experiment.  Overall, this affirmed our belief that
our kit really is easy to build and use, and that the DIY aspect of
the apparatus adds to the connection students make with the science --
if we can learn about something using LEGOs and food coloring, how
hard can it really be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_juan.jpg" width="600" title="Juan leading a demonstration at EYU" alt="Juan leading a demonstration at EYU"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan demonstrating baroclinic instability using our large square
tank, along with a GoPro in the rotating frame that streams footage to
his iPad.  Look at all those excited faces!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight was demonstrating baroclinic instability in our
larger square tank.  By putting a bucket of ice in the center, we
created baroclinic eddies and added some "Hollywood magic" via a GoPro
mounted in the rotating frame.  The rotating frame footage was
streamed directly to an iPad, rather than to an iPhone + projector as
we had in the past.  As usual, this was a crowd favorite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_baroclinic.jpg" width="600" title="Baroclinic instability on the DIYnamics table generated at EYU" alt="Baroclinic instability on the DIYnamics table generated at EYU"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Baroclinic instability generated on the DIYnamics table using a
frozen can of tomato paste as the cold source at the center.  We were
happily shocked when this worked first try, all while we were getting
setup for the rest of the event!  Huge thanks to Henry Gonzalez for
making the acryllic sidewall that enabled the fluid to span the
table's full width.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in addition to the baroclinic instability demonstration on
the big tank, we managed to get it working for the first time on the
smaller DIYnamics table!  These eddies need a sufficiently large tank
in order to grow (specifically, the tank radius must be appreciably
larger than the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rossby_radius_of_deformation"&gt;"Rossby radius of
deformation"&lt;/a&gt;,
which determines the size of the eddies), and that extra space was
enabled by an acryllic sidewall that Jon installed on one of the
tables with the help of Henry Gonzalez of the UCLA Dept. of Earth,
Planetary, and Space Sciences.  Instead of a paint bucket filled with
ice, we used a frozen can of tomato paste, which also allowed for more
room for the eddies to grow.  We're really excited to try this one
again and ultimately create a lesson plan and videos for it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to returning volunteer Chloe Wicker, first time
volunteer Tersi Arias-Young, the EYU organizers, and most of all the
great kids and parents who came to our booth.  We're already looking
forward to EYU 2018!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="outreach"></category><category term="public"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics + a record player at the Sierra Nevada Aquatic Research Laboratory</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/snarl-event.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-06-13:/snarl-event.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamicist Jon Aurnou led demonstrations using the DIYnamics table and a record player...and even got written up in the local newspaper!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On June 13, DIYnamics' own Prof. Jon Aurnou led an outreach event
featuring our Lego-based rotating tanks at the Sierra Nevada Aquatic
Research Laboratory
(&lt;a href="http://www.ucnrs.org/reserves/sierra-nevada-aquatic-research-laboratory.html"&gt;SNARL&lt;/a&gt;).
Jon gave a public lecture on his research on Jupiter's jets and
performed demonstrations for before and after the lecture.  The event
was even written up in a full-page article in the community's local
newspaper, &lt;em&gt;The Sheet&lt;/em&gt;.  Checkout a PDF
&lt;a href="{filename}../pdfs/aurnou_event_article_2017-06.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;; DIYnamics
is featured at the top of page 1 and all of page 23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon utilized a feature of the DIYnamics table that we hadn't in our
prior events: pouring water directly into the OXO lazy susan, rather
than into a container sitting on the OXO.  This utilizes the full 16"
diameter surface, although because the rim is only around 1/2" tall,
only a shallow layer can be attained.  But this is more like Earth's
atmosphere or ocean anyways!  In fact, the true aspect ratio (i.e. the
ratio of how wide they are to how tall they are) of either of these is
even larger -- not far from that of a single piece of paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/snarl/jon-oxo.jpg" width="600" title="Jon using the DIYnamics table" alt="Jon using the DIYnamics table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jon using the DIYnamics Table to teach kids and adults about rotating
fluids.  Photo credit: Abagael Giles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon complemented the demonstrations performed on the DIYnamics table
with others using a turntable (i.e. what you use to play vinyl records
or be a legit DJ).  Turntables are another great tool for these
demonstrations.  Like the DIYnamics table, they are portable and
inexpensive compared to custom built tanks primarily used at
universities.  And unlike the DIYnamics table (at least for now), many
have a lever that enables varying the rotation rate by up to +/-10%,
which is needed for e.g. demonstrating &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor_column"&gt;Taylor
columns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(One snag with using record players is the center nub that keeps vinyl
records centered as they spin.  A notch has to be machined out of the
bottom of your tank, or the tank has to be sitting on something like a
platform with legs.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole event was a major success in Jon's eyes, as the crowd seemed
really interested in the hands-on demonstrations.  "Kids loved getting
to operate the table themselves. They kept playing with it until it
got dark outside," Jon said.  "And they made a complete mess and asked
a lot of questions -– a great sign that they had fun and learned
something."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/snarl/jon-record-player.jpg" width="600" title="Jon using a record player" alt="Jon using a record player"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prof. Aurnou using a turntable (a.k.a. a record player) at the same
event.  Turntables are another great way to demonstrate the behavior
of rotating fluids.  Photo credit: Abagael Giles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="outreach"></category><category term="public"></category><category term="record player"></category><category term="press"></category></entry><entry><title>Ralph Bunche Middle School Event</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/ralph-bunche-event.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-22T16:16:01-06:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T16:16:01-06:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-05-22:/ralph-bunche-event.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team brought their rotating tables to the 7th grade science class at Ralph J. Bunche Middle School in Compton, CA.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On May 22nd, 2017, we visited Ralph Bunche Middle School in Compton,
California. Similarly to our La Tijera K-8 School events, we first
introduced students to the field of geophysical fluid dynamics
(GFD). We sought to teach students about the importance of models in
studying science and, to this end, we showed how our assortment of
rotating tanks can be used to illustrate aspects of GFD. Both the
group experiments and individual DIY Rotating Tank experiments went
great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lecture" src="{filename}../images/ralph-bunche/sean-slide-show.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean provides a lecture on GFD and the use of models in studying
science. Lecture slides can be found
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ClYEmFAEATzG2iHZ8uqD2pzgEYSqbrYZD0xDRfuADzk/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="LEGO Table" src="{filename}../images/ralph-bunche/katie-students.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Rotating Column" src="{filename}../images/ralph-bunche/small-table-solid-body.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Katie and other members of the DIY Rotating Tank team demonstrate how
rotating tanks are a simple yet effective tool for studying GFD. Among
other experiments, students created a vertical column and learned how
it mirrors the interior of rotating planets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="White Whale 1" src="{filename}../images/ralph-bunche/white_whale_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="White Whale 2" src="{filename}../images/ralph-bunche/white_whale_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan provides a demonstration of the mechanical creation of
vortices, a.k.a. the swirling patterns in the dye. When students dip
their hands into the large rotating tank, the physical disturbance
results in turbluence. Other sources of turbluence like the movement
of heat can also generate vortices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Square Table" src="{filename}../images/ralph-bunche/square-tank.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan shows how an uneven temperature distribution can influence
GFD. An ice bucket at the center of the tank and rotation result in
the formation of vortices. This behavior reflects the weather patterns
of the Earth's middle latitudes. A video of this demonstration is
available &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G26klqKKCmM"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category></entry><entry><title>La Tijera K-8 School Event</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/la-tijera-events.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-05-19:/la-tijera-events.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team brought rotating tables large and small to La Tijera K-8 Charter School in Inglewood, CA, to teach basics Earth's atmospheric and oceanic motions.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On May 12th and May 19th, 2017, we visited La Tijera K-8 School in
Inglewood, California. We introduced seventh and eighth grade students
to the study of geophysical fluid dynamics (GFD) and how this pertains
to our everyday lives. Like many other areas of science, studying GFD
involves the extensive use of scientific models and, to this end, we
brought a range of rotating tables to showcase key concepts. Everyone
had a lot of fun during group demonstrations and individual
experiments involving the DIY Rotating Tank. At the end, we talked
with students about how they can pursue careers in science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Model" src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/globe-table.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Gyroscope" src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/gyroscope.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean and Spencer discuss how GFD can be studied using smaller scale
models. Lecture slides can be found
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ClYEmFAEATzG2iHZ8uqD2pzgEYSqbrYZD0xDRfuADzk/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="White Whale 1" src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/white_whale_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="White Whale 2" src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/white_whale_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan demonstrates the creation of vortices using our large rotating
tank nicknamed the "White Whale." When students placed their hands in
the water, vortices were mechanically generated (seen as swirling
patterns of the colored dyes). Other forms of turbulence can also
create vortices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/square-tank.png" width="450" title="The square tank" alt="The square tank"&gt;
&lt;img src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/square-projector.png" width="450" title="The projector" alt="The projector"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan provides a demonstration on the effects of temperature
distributions on rotating fluids. At the center of the square tank is
an ice bucket, which cools the nearby water. The resulting temperature
contrasts in the water induce vortices analogous to the weather
patterns of the Earth's mid-latitudes. We used a camera and projector
to show the results from the rotating point of view. A video of this
demonstration can be found
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G26klqKKCmM"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego 1" src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/lego_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Lego 2" src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/lego_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alex and other members of the DIYnamics team guided students in using
the DIY Rotating Tank to model GFD concepts. The students were able to
compare the movement of dye in rotating versus non-rotating bodies of
fluid. Rotating columns are analogous to the movement of molten iron
in the Earth's outer core.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group Photo 1" src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/group_photo_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Group Photo 2" src="{filename}../images/la-tijera/group_photo_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Group photos of DIYnamics team members and our host Mr. Stephenson
taken during the May 12th (left) and May 19th (right) trips. It was a
pleasure to work with Mr. Stephenson, and he played a large part in
making the events run as smoothly as possible. This included visiting
UCLA beforehand to learn about GFD and how it relates to his
curriculum.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry></feed>