<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>DIYnamics</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://diynamics.github.io/</id><updated>2021-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>Affordable materials for geoscience teaching demonstrations</subtitle><entry><title>Field Report: Teaching with DIYnamics at the Colegio La Esperanza, Tijuana, Mexico</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/tijuana-2021.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Nick Lutsko</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2021-04-12:/blog/tijuana-2021.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nick Lutsko, an assistant professor at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UC&lt;/span&gt; San Diego, describes his collaboration with the Colegio La Esperanza elementary school in Tijuana, Mexico, using DIYnamics to teach (remotely and in Spanish!) their students some fundamentals of rotating&amp;nbsp;fluids.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country &amp;#8212;- and in this case, the world(!) &amp;#8212;- share how they&amp;#8217;ve
used the DIYnamics kit and materials in local communities.&amp;nbsp;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How can I describe hurricane dynamics in rudimentary Spanish?”  This
was one of the questions I asked myself a few weeks ago while giving a
virtual demonstration of some DIYnamics experiments in (limited)
Spanish to the fifth and sixth graders at the Colegio La
Esperanza. The Colegio is a kindergarten and primary school in the La
Esperanza Colonia of Tijuana, Baja California, Mexico. Sited at the
top of a hill about nine miles south of the San Diego border, the
school was founded in 1989 by the non-profit Americas Foundation with
the goal of creating a social institution in an unorganized and
unincorporated yet highly populated area. The school’s curriculum has
a strong focus on the arts, and the Foundation works with volunteers
and other nonprofit organizations and schools in both San Diego and
Tijuana to stage cultural events and educational programs across the
border&amp;nbsp;region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/tijuana-2021/tijuana01.png" width="600" title="Tijuana 1" alt="Tijuana 1"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adding the food dye at the start of the Taylor-Proudman&amp;nbsp;experiment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met the director of the Americas Foundation, Christine Brady, at a
virtual reunion event for Princeton alumni last year &amp;#8212;- Christine
graduated from Princeton with a physics degree, and I did my
Ph.D. there. We stayed in touch over the past year, during which the
Colegio transitioned to remote learning in response to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19
epidemic.  It’s been a very difficult time for the Colegio, as many
students live in households without running water or
electricity.  Christine has led several funding drives to get
wireless-enabled cell phones for all the students who needed one to
follow along in Zoom&amp;nbsp;classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/tijuana-2021/tijuana02.png" width="600" title="Tijuana 2" alt="Tijuana 2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Answering questions after the demonstrations with Profesora&amp;nbsp;Lorena.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics experiments seemed like a fun way to teach the students
a little bit about how the atmosphere and the ocean work, so I reached
out to the DIYnamics team, who very kindly donated two of their
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-based tables to the&amp;nbsp;Colegio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the day of the demonstration, the Colegio moved the filming
equipment they use for virtual demonstrations to the ecology
classroom, where I was frantically building Legos (class with the
fifth graders started an hour earlier than I expected).  With
Profesora Lorena helping to explain the experiments and Profesor
José-Luis manning the cameras, we showed the kids Taylor-Proudman
columns and then how fronts develop. Using two cell phones, we had a
top-down view and a cross-section, so we could see the dye trapped in
columns or watch the swirling eddies from&amp;nbsp;above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/tijuana-2021/tijuana03.png" width="600" title="Tijuana 3" alt="Tijuana 3"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;José-Luis playing with the rotating tank before&amp;nbsp;class&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s always hard to get feedback over Zoom, but the kids seemed to
really enjoy the demonstrations. The sixth-graders in particular asked
lots of questions &amp;#8212; about weather and the oceans, about how
hurricanes and storms work, and about what it’s like to be a
scientist. There were also questions that were harder for me to answer
about the kinds of animals which live at the sea-floor and how long
sharks live. The teachers were also thrilled when they learned that
the kits are staying at the school. My only regret was that I didn’t
spend more time beforehand looking up meteorology terms in&amp;nbsp;Spanish.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="Field report"></category><category term="lego"></category><category term="K-12"></category></entry><entry><title>Portable Platforms - The DJ Table and the HT3</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/dj-ht3-tables-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-22T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Taylor Lonner</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-12-22:/blog/dj-ht3-tables-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In addition to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; revamp in the form of the Technic Table, DIYnamics has recently developed two brand new systems emphasizing portability, ease of assembly, and broad-range rotational capability: the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/dj-ht3-tables-2020/dj_table_annotated.png" width="600" title="DJ Table complete setup" alt="DJ Table complete setup"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introducing the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table! As the first DIYnamics table that
incorporates portability in the design, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table is the perfect
kit for schools and universities who want to showcase advanced fluid
dynamics phenomena in their classrooms and lecture&amp;nbsp;halls.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table is a three part system consisting of modified cart, a
high-torque record player, and a tank.  The modified cart has standard
utility shelf posts such that the height can be adjusted by one inch
increments and the only tool needed for assembly is a mallet.  The
cart is also the only part of the system that requires assembly and is
easily a one-person job.  We offer a variety of options for both new
and used record players, but highly suggest scouring the internet (and
local garage sales) for second-hand record players.  Record players
that lack a tone arm or functioning audio ports may seem like junk to
music enthusiasts, but are perfect for fluid dynamics experiments!
Finally, we provide a few different options for tanks.  While we
recommend our custom-designed tanks with centered holes for mounting
to record players, if you have your own tank, we also provide options
for elevation blocks such that you don&amp;#8217;t have to worry about the
record pin being in the way.  Overall, the pricing for the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table
ranges from $600-$1500 depending on your choice of record player and
tank.  This averages to about 1/5 the price of our more advanced
system, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table is well suited for schools looking to share a kit between
classrooms or lecture halls.  The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table&amp;#8217;s modified cart has locking
wheels and the system maintains a minimal footprint for easy storage.
Situated on the cart, the star of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table is the high-torque
record player which can generate rotation rates from 17 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; to 117 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt;
(depending on the specific model).  This rotation range makes the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt;
Table perfect for rapidly rotating experiments such&amp;nbsp;as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taylor&amp;nbsp;columns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Column collapse and&amp;nbsp;frontogenesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ekman&amp;nbsp;pumping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Centrifugal&amp;nbsp;forcing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corner vortices (in a square&amp;nbsp;tank)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spin up&amp;nbsp;demonstrations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Columnar (vertical)&amp;nbsp;convection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of columnar convection can be seen below.  The
visualization is accomplished with green food dye distributed using a
spray&amp;nbsp;bottle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/dj-ht3-tables-2020/vertical_convection.gif" width="600" title="Columnar Convection" alt="Columnar Convection"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/dj-ht3-tables-2020/ht3_annotated.jpg" width="600" title="HT3 complete setup" alt="HT3 complete setup"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introducing the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;!  The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; is our most ambitious kit to date.
Boasting a powerful turntable, meter-scale tank, and built in
visualization deck, this system can be used for demonstrating
geophysical fluid dynamics everywhere from a classroom or lecture hall
to a museum or a outreach science&amp;nbsp;festival.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; is a multi-part system optimized for portability,
accessibility, and ease of assembly.  The custom acrylic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; tank has
a maximized diameter while still fitting through a standard doorframe
and comes pre-drilled with mounting holes on a 2.5-inch lip for the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; visualization deck.  The visualization deck consists of a
polycarbonate plate held above the tank with three legs and it allows
users to place sensors in the rotating frame of the tank, including
phones and cameras to record and stream video.  The tank sits on a
powerful turntable, capable of maintaining a consistent low rotation
rate with over 25 gallons of water in the tank.  Finally, we encourage
those who want to invest in an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; to purchase the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt; (Taylor-Henry
Cart) - a multi-purpose cart designed by our team to make the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; a
broadly useful and accessible teaching device.  Low to the ground to
enable children to look over the tank, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt; sits on 5-inch locking
casters which turns the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; into an all-terrain vehicle.  With the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt;, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; system can easily be carted from classroom to classroom,
or across campus from lecture hall to lecture hall.  The lower deck on
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt; is ideal for storing your power, as well as dyes and other
visualization tools.  Additionally, the cart&amp;#8217;s handlebar can be bent
to provide a platform for controls, or completely stowed under the
lower deck to make 360 degrees of viewing available.  Most
importantly, the entire system (both the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt;) can be
assembled without any power tools!  The cost of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; kit with the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt; is&amp;nbsp;$4,800.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; system is a flexible device that was designed with large-scale
outreach in mind, but with careful set-up and leveling, it has the
potential for being a research device.  The visualization deck can
also be used to house measurement instrumentation including motion
tracking and thermometry systems.  The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; turntable is capable of
rotating from 0.16 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; to 13.3 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; which makes this system ideal for
experiments such&amp;nbsp;as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thermal wind&amp;nbsp;flows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ocean Garbage Patches and Ekman&amp;nbsp;Pumping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baroclinic&amp;nbsp;instability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Columnar&amp;nbsp;convection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanical turbulence (i.e., Great Red Spot&amp;nbsp;experiments)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-rotating evaporative convection (solar-style&amp;nbsp;convection)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rossby&amp;nbsp;waves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video shows a baroclinic instability demonstration on
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/HTm3U8mfE1Y'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit the DIYnamics Kits page &lt;a href="/pages/kits.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn more
about the original Do-It-Yourself rotating tank platform &amp;#8212; the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;
Table &amp;#8212; and its newly-released successor: the Technics Table. If you
are interested in sharing your experiences with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table or the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;, feel free to contact us on Twitter at
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/diynamicsteam"&gt;@DIYnamicsTeam&lt;/a&gt; or email at
&lt;a href="mailto:diynamicsteam@gmail.com"&gt;diynamicsteam@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="dj"></category><category term="ht3"></category><category term="thc"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics at Exploring Your Universe 2020</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/eyu-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-12-21:/blog/eyu-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team presented a diverse range of fluid dynamics experiments you can perform at home as part of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s Exploring Your Universe public science fair &amp;#8212; held virtually for&amp;nbsp;2020.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/eyu-logo.png" width="400" title="Exploring Your Universe" alt="Exploring Your Universe"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 1st, 2020, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Division of Physical Sciences presented its 12th annual &lt;a href="https://www.exploringyouruniverse.org/"&gt;Exploring Your Universe&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;) public outreach event. Every year, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; features dozens of booths for attendees to learn about a diverse range of topics. Amidst the ongoing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19 pandemic, this year&amp;#8217;s public outreach event was held entirely virtually on &lt;a href="https://hopin.com/events/eyu"&gt;hopin.to&lt;/a&gt;. The DIYnamics Team adapted and utilized the opportunity to share the following experiments for learning at&amp;nbsp;home!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why is Antarctica&amp;nbsp;Melting?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dS1W00XW2LM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jordyn created a video, &lt;strong&gt;How do glaciers melt?&lt;/strong&gt;, providing an overview of the fluid dynamics behind the titular process. She described the experimental setup in detail and analyzed experimental results for background into the range of structures observed. Watch to see the interface between density layers and baroclinic&amp;nbsp;eddies!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordyn Moscoso and Ken Zhao presented a talk on how do glaciers melt. Glaciers are massive bodies of frozen fresh water. In locales such as Antarctica, sheets of ice are surrounded by ocean or warm (in a relative sense &amp;#8212; absolute temperatures can dip to 34&amp;deg;F/1&amp;deg;C!) salty water. The temperature difference causes glaciers to melt from the bottom releasing cold fresh water. This loss of mass renders ice sheets unstable and susceptible to calfing or large chunks falling off. Meanwhile, the cold fresh meltwater is less dense than the warm salty ocean water due to differences in salinity. Convection occurs as the cold fresh water rises above the warm salty water and the ocean equilibriates into layers by&amp;nbsp;density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antarctica is a continent the size of the United States and Mexico combined. The fluid dynamics of this vast system can be modeled with a rotating tank platform capturing its key characteristics. Jordyn and Ken performed an experiment featuring a tank of warm salty water (the &amp;#8220;ocean&amp;#8221;) with a cylindrical block of ice (the &amp;#8220;glacier&amp;#8221;) at its center. The tank is spun to account for the fundamental impacts of Earth&amp;#8217;s rotation. In the experiment, we can observe the model&amp;#8217;s glacier melting from its bottom and ocean stratifying per density differences. Food coloring is added to help visualize fluid motions &amp;#8212; the interface between layers is distinct! Eddies or swirling structures form as the system&amp;#8217;s rotation interacts with the fluid body&amp;#8217;s density&amp;nbsp;differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Home Kitchen&amp;nbsp;Experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-1.png" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 1" alt="Air vortex cannon step 1"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-2.png" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 2" alt="Air vortex cannon step 2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-3.png" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 3" alt="Air vortex cannon step 3"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-4.png" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 4" alt="Air vortex cannon step 4"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-5.gif" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 5" alt="Air vortex cannon step 5"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-6.gif" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 6" alt="Air vortex cannon step 6"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to create your own air vortex cannon&lt;br&gt;
Step 1: Gather required materials &amp;#8212; plastic cup, balloon and source of smoke.&lt;br&gt;
Step 2: Cut a circular hole in the bottom of the cup. &lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: Be careful when using a scissor or knife.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Step 3: Cut the neck of the balloon to leave the head remaining.&lt;br&gt;
Step 4: Wrap the head of the balloon over the top of the cup.&lt;br&gt;
Step 5: Fill the inside of the air vortex cannon with smoke. &lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: Be careful when around open flames.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Step 6: Fire the air vortex cannon by pulling back then releasing the balloon.&lt;br&gt;
The goal is to eject a jet of air that pushes through stationary air &amp;#8212; do not release too much air at once else the jet will immediately break apart. The smoke in the air vortex cannon will allow you to visualize structures (including vortex rings) in the air! For best results, fire the air vortex cannon against a dark background for&amp;nbsp;contrast.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yufan Xu and Akash Gupta guided the virtual audience through easy to perform home experiments providing a glimpse into the fluid dynamics all around us! A vortex ring is a torus or donut shaped structure that forms when a jet of fast moving fluid collides with stationary fluid. As the jet pushes through, its edges are slowed by friction and wrap around themselves leading to the formation of a circular ring of circulating fluid. Yufan and Akash demonstrated how to build your own air vortex cannon before firing vortex rings of&amp;nbsp;smoke!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Convection refers to the transfer of heat by motion within a fluid. The transfer of heat occurs wherever fluid bodies feature a temperature gradient &amp;#8212; from a cooling cup of coffee to a sun generating energy by fusion. Convection can be visualized with particles suspended in fluid &amp;#8212; an ideal solution is Barbasoloscope with a recipe by Yufan &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/f9K3FEJkBrs"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Yufan and Akash highlighted convection by warming up miso soup on a stovetop &amp;#8212; the fermented soybean mixture tracked cells of fluid motion as the solution circulated between the pot&amp;#8217;s fire heated bottom and air cooled&amp;nbsp;top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pendulum O&amp;nbsp;Pendulum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/jon-demonstration.png" width="600" title="Jon's demonstration" alt="Jon's demonstration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jon added creamer (dyed pink) to water to demonstrate how waves in different layers oscillate back and forth through the fluid&amp;nbsp;body!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon Aurnou described how pendulums behave both individually and together. Pendulums refer to masses suspended by an arm from a pivot &amp;#8212; the masses swing back and forth about the pivot. Jon created a homemade pendulum by hanging a length of wood from a nail. He demonstrated that if a pendulum is released from a given height, it will swing across its equilibrium point until eventually coming to rest. Per the conservation of energy, with each cycle, the pendulum reaches a height near to but slightly less than its previous iteration. Meanwhile, the period or time required for a pendulum to complete a cycle depends on the length of the arm separating the mass and pivot. Jon compared short and long homemade pendulums to illustrate how given equivalent starting heights, the short pendulums will oscillate much faster. Having established that the behavior of each pendulum is tied to its properties, he tried swinging two different pendulums back and forth about the same pivot. The two pendulums do not behave independently but rather are impacted by each other &amp;#8212; the signals amplify when the pendulums travel together and are muted when the pendulums&amp;nbsp;collide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon shared how pendulum-like conditions also exist in fluid bodies! He created a &amp;#8220;pendulum&amp;#8221; by filling a tank with water &amp;#8212; after allowing the water to rest, to induce swinging, he added a mass of dense creamer with food coloring to one side. A wave of creamer oscillates back and forth through the tank! Different layers of the ocean (see &lt;strong&gt;Why is Antarctica Melting?&lt;/strong&gt;!) can oscillate at different frequencies leading to combined signals that have been amplified and muted. Finding the original frequency of a &amp;#8220;pendulum&amp;#8221; is an important yet challenging task &amp;#8212; a puzzle to&amp;nbsp;solve!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dancing Milk and the Importance of Surface&amp;nbsp;Tension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/grace-demonstration.png" width="600" title="Grace's demonstration" alt="Grace's demonstration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grace dipped a soap covered Q-tip into milk to spread the liquid apart creating vibrant displays of food&amp;nbsp;coloring!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grace Li performed a series of experiments (helping the virtual audience follow along at home!) demonstrating surface tension in action. Surface tension is a property of liquids referring to its surface&amp;#8217;s integrity against dissipation and attributed to forces of attraction between its molecules. Grace illustrated how different liquids have different degrees of surface tension by using a Q-tip to drag liquid droplets across wax paper. Water molecules are strongly cohesive whilst isopropyl alcohol molecules are weakly cohesive &amp;#8212; thus, only water droplets could be successfully dragged. The strong cohesion of water molecules is essential to the natural world &amp;#8212; from water striders walking on water to redwoods bringing water from their roots to&amp;nbsp;branches!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surface tension is disrupted by surfactants such as soap that reduce the forces of attraction between liquid molecules &amp;#8212; surfactants allow a liquid&amp;#8217;s molecules to spread apart. To demonstrate, Grace filled a tank with milk and rested droplets of food coloring on its surface. She dipped a soap covered Q-tip into the milk &amp;#8212; the surfactant caused the food coloring to dissipate leading to stunning patterns of green and&amp;nbsp;blue!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fluid Dynamics +&amp;nbsp;LEGOs!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/norris-demonstration.png" width="600" title="Norris' demonstration" alt="Norris' demonstration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris compared fluid motions in non-rotating versus rotating systems. In non-rotating systems, as pictured above, the food coloring is free to diffuse with no discernable structure. Rotation will impart constraints on the fluid motions of rotating&amp;nbsp;systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norris Khoo utilized the &lt;a href="/pages/lego.html"&gt;Technics Table&lt;/a&gt; to highlight the impact of rotation on a fluid body&amp;#8217;s behavior. The fluid dynamics of Earth&amp;#8217;s atmosphere (air), oceans (water) and interiors (molten iron) are all fundamentally impacted by the planet&amp;#8217;s rotation. To help the virtual audience reason with its effects, Norris presented a comparison of fluid motions in non-rotating and rotating systems &amp;#8212; food coloring is added to visualize fluid motions. The non-rotating system consists of a tank of water. After allowing the system to rest (no fluid motions within within the tank), we observed that the marked water is free to diffuse with no discernable structure. Meanwhile, the rotating system consists of a rotating tank of water &amp;#8212; the Technics Table. After allowing the system to spin up (no fluid motions within the tank as it rotates), we observed that the marked water organizes itself into vertical columns. This occurs because rotation constrains fluid motions to align them with its axis &amp;#8212; this counteracts diffusion. The impact of rotation, the Coriolis force, is a parameter influencing our (and other) planet&amp;#8217;s weather, ocean currents, magnetic field and&amp;nbsp;more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making Your Own Polar&amp;nbsp;Vortex&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/taylor-demonstration.png" width="600" title="Taylor's demonstration" alt="Taylor's demonstration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taylor established a thermal gradient in the rotating system using a frozen can. Due to rotation, the cold water in the center interacts with the warm water to the periphery to create baroclinic eddies. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; Table&amp;#8217;s diameter enables the formation of large&amp;nbsp;structures!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor Lonner utilized the &lt;a href="/pages/ht3.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; Table&lt;/a&gt; to highlight how rotation and turbulence interact in fluid bodies. Turbulence refers to a disruption to the system &amp;#8212; conditions include a thermal gradient or mechanical movement. Taylor performed a series of experiments feature different types of turbulence in a rotating system &amp;#8212; the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; Table. The rotating tank platform&amp;#8217;s meter diameter provided ample room for large and complex structures to form. Meanwhile, thanks to &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; and steps described &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/pdfs/technics/Zoom_Livestreaming_Guide.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, she provided real-time footage for the virtual audience to digest. This kickstarted a rich Q&amp;amp;A as the virtual audience worked with Taylor, Jon and Norris to analyze the stunning display inside the&amp;nbsp;tank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor established a thermal gradient in the rotating system using methods similar to &lt;strong&gt;Why is Antarctica Melting?&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8212; she fixed a frozen can in the middle of the rotating tank of water. The center is cold whilst the periphery is warm &amp;#8212; as the system rotates, dense cold water is pushed outwards whilst light warm water flows inwards to take its place. This leads to the formation of stunning eddies about the frozen can! On Earth, weather in the mid-lattitudes are defined by similar behavior as cold polar air mixed with warm equatorial air. To induce mechanical movement, Taylor rapidly removed the frozen can from the rotating tank of water. Although this can be interpreted as plucking the &amp;#8220;glacier&amp;#8221; out of the &amp;#8220;ocean&amp;#8221;, in general, the removal of the mass creates a vacuum causing water to flow and fill the gap. Constrained by rotation, the turbulence is reorganized into eddies of different shapes and sizes &amp;#8212; fluid motions remain aligned with the axis of rotation. The interaction between rotation and turbulence is responsible for massive storm systems as seen on&amp;nbsp;Jupiter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; was to demonstrate that you can perform your own experiments at home! Experiments are key to learning because models, whilst abstractions of real world systems, provide intuition into the fundamental forces that govern our universe. The process of setting up, performing and analyzing and experiment is an exciting challenge in problem solving and a first hand account proves invaluable. Most of these demonstrations can be performed using household materials to reduce barriers and expand inclusivity in the sciences. Ultimately, understanding the world around us can help audience members (whether in-person or virtual) make informed decisions in their daily lives &amp;#8212; &lt;strong&gt;Why is Antarctica melting?&lt;/strong&gt; highlights the detrimental impact that ocean warming of mere degrees will have on Antarctica. Learn more on our Teaching &lt;a href="/pages/teaching.html"&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; and YouTube &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnUHxOSVY4G4OFbF8XL1qUg"&gt;channel&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; organizers and volunteers, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Division of Physical Sciences and all of the attendees! It was a blast working together to learn from experiments and ponder interesting questions! Thank you to the following individuals &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/dS1W00XW2LM?t=490"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; who supported the &lt;strong&gt;How do glaciers melt&lt;/strong&gt; video. We look forward to next year&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="DIY"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="virtual"></category></entry><entry><title>The Technics Table - A Robust and Consistent $80 DIY Rotating Tank Platform</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/technics-table-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-11-19:/blog/technics-table-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Technics Table is the upgraded successor to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table. Available for $80, the Technics Table features a more robust design to provide a more consistent user&amp;nbsp;experience.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/technics-table-complete-setup.png" width="600" title="Technics Table complete setup" alt="Technics Table complete setup"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introducing the Technics Table! As with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table, the rotating tank platform consists of a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly, lazy susan and tank. Hands-on demonstrations provide insight into the forces responsible for our (or other) planet&amp;#8217;s weather, ocean currents, magnetic field and&amp;nbsp;more!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is an affordable yet effective way to build your own rotating tank platform? One of our answers is combining LEGOs and a lazy susan! From outreach events to classrooms, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table provides opportunities for audiences of all ages to perform experiments start to finish themselves. The Do-It-Yourself approach encourages analytical thinking as teachers and students reason together in establishing a model and relating observations with the world around us. After its use in facilitating a diverse range of experiments, we have received feedback that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table is an effective rotating tank platform but features several opportunities for improvement. Meanwhile, the DIYnamics community has been pushing the envelope on the capabilities of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table necessitating a robust design to&amp;nbsp;match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/lego-table-lego-assembly.png" width="400" title="LEGO Table LEGO assembly" alt="LEGO Table LEGO assembly"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/technics-table-lego-assembly.png" width="400" title="Technics Table LEGO assembly" alt="Technics Table LEGO assembly"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table (L) versus the Technics Table (R) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assemblies. The modules serve as a mount for the motor, battery and drive wheel rotating the lazy susan. Between (L) and (R), the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly has been upgraded to a beefier design for much improved&amp;nbsp;consistency.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we introduce the Technics Table! The Technics Table draws its name from Technics pieces &amp;#8212; a variant of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; pieces featuring interlocking beams and pins. Rather than reinventing the wheel, the Technics Table retains the core layout of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table consisting of a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly, lazy susan and tank. The second generation builds upon its predecessor by improving the sturdiness and stability of the system with changes to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly. The revamped &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly is constructed with Technics pieces and is built atop a broad baseplate. The Technics Table can be purchased in its entirety for $80 &amp;#8212; only $25 more than the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;Table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/design.png" width="400" title="Technics Table Technics pieces" alt="Technics Table Technics pieces"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/cad.png" width="400" title="Technics Table CAD design" alt="Technics Table CAD design"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(L) The Technics Table &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly with arm detached. The new design utilizes Technics pieces and features a broad baseplate. Compared to traditional &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; bricks, Technics beams and pins provide stronger connections difficult to pull apart. Instead of holding the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly in place with a rubber slip pad, there is now ample room to place down weights (e.g. water bottles) to keep the module stationary and in contact with the lazy&amp;nbsp;susan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(R) The Technics Table was created and documented with the help of the &lt;a href="https://www.ldraw.org/"&gt;LDraw&lt;/a&gt; family of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; software. Bricksmith (pictured above) enables developing designs in a digital domain and LPub facilitates publishing designs to&amp;nbsp;instructions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Technics Table has demonstrated itself to be a consistent rotating tank platform for driving experiments! Prior inconveniences with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table, such as the arm falling off or the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly shifting, have abated to non-issues. Although the Technics Table features a higher upfront cost  compared to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table, the new design enables users to depend on a consistent experience for each&amp;nbsp;experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="600" height="340" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/b4ARJls03YA" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, home to Earth Sciences research at Columbia University, held an open house &lt;a href="https://openhouse.ldeo.columbia.edu/"&gt;event&lt;/a&gt; in October 2020. We utilized the Technics Table to perform a variety of experiments illustrating the impact of planetary rotation on the fluid motions of our atmosphere, oceans and planetary&amp;nbsp;interior.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/mechanically-generated-vortices.jpg" width="600" title="Mechanically generated vortices" alt="Mechanically generated vortices"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(U) Technics Table experimental results and (D) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt; Juno &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/image-feature/jpl/churning-texture-in-jupiter-s-atmosphere"&gt;satellite image&lt;/a&gt; of Jupiter&amp;#8217;s atmosphere. Turbulence and rotation interact to form circular structures known as eddies &amp;#8212; fluid motions in the tank are analogous to storm systems such as Jupiter&amp;#8217;s Great Red&amp;nbsp;Spot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/juno-jupiter.jpg" width="600" title="Storms systems on Jupiter. Image credit: NASA Juno" alt="Storms systems on Jupiter. Image credit: NASA Juno"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the Technics Table, new developments include DIYnamics community driven add-ons that expand the utility of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based Tables! Visit the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based Tables page &lt;a href="/pages/lego.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and our YouTube channel &lt;a href="https://tinyurl.com/diynamicsvideos"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; and video guides on how to purchase, build and operate the Technics Table and&amp;nbsp;add-ons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/rotating-frame-camera-mount.png" width="400" title="Rotating frame camera mount" alt="Rotating frame camera mount"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/external-power-supply.png" width="400" title="External power supply" alt="External power supply"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(L) The rotating frame camera mount provides the ability to mount a camera in the rotating frame &amp;#8212; the perspective of an observer rotating in sync with the system. Capturing rotating frame footage is beneficial because it enables viewing fluid motions sans the visual effects of rotation. The rotating frame camera mount can be coupled with solutions like Zoom to livestream footage for real-time analysis. The design was developed by Marianna&amp;nbsp;Linz.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(R) The external power supply provides the ability to power the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based Tables with wall power instead of battery power. The adjustable voltage power adapter enables fine control over rotating rate &amp;#8212; perfect for experiments like Taylor columns! The design was developed by Alex&amp;nbsp;Gonzalez.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/sidewall-tank.png" width="400" title="Sidewall tank" alt="Sidewall tank"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sidewall tank provides an option for a tank of increased diameter and height. Using a larger tank expands the breadth and quality of experiments possible with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based&amp;nbsp;Tables.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit the DIYnamics Kits page &lt;a href="/pages/kits.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about our other larger Do-It-Yourself rotating tank platforms &amp;#8212; the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; Table. If you are interested in sharing your experiences with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based Tables, feel free to contact us on Twitter at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/diynamicsteam"&gt;@DIYnamicsTeam&lt;/a&gt; or email at &lt;a href="mailto:diynamicsteam@gmail.com"&gt;diynamicsteam@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="lego"></category><category term="technics"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>Exciting new chapter for DIYnamics with three new Kits and new guides</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/kits-launch-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-10-28:/blog/kits-launch-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics has launched a major overhaul with three new kits and accompanying guides that range from a beefed-up Lego table to a nearly research-grade 3-foot diameter&amp;nbsp;device.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/kits-launch-2020/technics_table.gif" width="600" title="New Technics table" alt="New Technics table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The new Technics Table in&amp;nbsp;action!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics &lt;a href="/pages/lego.html"&gt;Lego Table&lt;/a&gt; has proven to be a really valuable tool in
teaching fundamentals of atmospheric circulations, ocean currents,
planetary interior flows, and other core geoscience concepts.  Its low
cost, ease of ordering, assembly, and operation, and the simple fact
that it is mostly made out of toy Lego pieces help make the underlying
science seem approachable and fun to learn all the way down to the
elementary school level.  And at the other end of the educational
spectrum, its use in undergraduate and graduate courses continues to
expand across the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; and beyond: this semester with many
institutions teaching remotely due to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19, at least two courses
(at Harvard and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;) have provided Lego Tables for each of their
students to use remotely from their own homes &amp;#8212;- including multiple
students in China.  (More to come about these endeavors in future&amp;nbsp;posts.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, through our own uses and events and from reports
back from users in the wild, we&amp;#8217;ve come to find some limitations of
the original design.  For one, on repeated or extended use, sometimes
the motor arm will detach from the main assembly entirely&amp;#8230;not great
in the middle of a demonstration!  Another is that some &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OXO&lt;/span&gt; tables can
develop a tilt or slow spot, leading to tank-wide sloshing and/or the
rotation rate not staying constant.  Finally, for rotating tanks at
least there&amp;#8217;s no denying that bigger is better, and so the 6&amp;#8221; diameter
tanks that are most commonly used with the Lego Table can only
generate so much of a &amp;#8220;wow&amp;#8221; factor compared to much bigger&amp;nbsp;tanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/kits-launch-2020/dj_table.gif" width="600" title="New DJ Table" alt="New DJ Table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table in&amp;nbsp;action!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spurred by these limitations, over the past couple years the DIYnamics
team &amp;#8212;- most of all Norris, Taylor, Henry, and Jon &amp;#8212;- have been
developing upgraded rotating tank platforms.  The result of their hard
work is three new &amp;#8220;kits&amp;#8221;, as we&amp;#8217;re now calling them, ranging from a
beefed-up Lego table to a nearly research-grade, 3-foot diameter tank
(but that&amp;#8217;s 100% portable).  We&amp;#8217;re happy to introduce these new kits
&amp;#8212;- the &lt;a href="/pages/lego.html"&gt;Technics Table&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="/pages/dj.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt;
Table&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href="/pages/ht3.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  A series of
posts will follow this introductory one, each describing one of the
new kits in more&amp;nbsp;detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/kits-launch-2020/ht3_table.gif" width="600" title="New HT3 table" alt="New HT3 table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; table in&amp;nbsp;action!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devices are only so helpful without instructions on how to build
and operate them, and so the team has also created &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; and video
guides for each device.  Along the way, we (mostly Norris) also
created guides for commonly needed &amp;#8220;peripherals&amp;#8221; like how to
livestream rotating frame footage &amp;#8212;- these were inspired by ingenious
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; solutions created by team members Alex and Marianna.  These too
are now all available via our &lt;a href="/pages/kits.html"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnUHxOSVY4G4OFbF8XL1qUg"&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;channel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We encourage you to check out the new materials now, and to look out
for our followup posts describing each kit in more detail, all coming&amp;nbsp;soon!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="organization"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: A high schooler teaching fluid dynamics to middle schoolers using DIYnamics</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/isu-middle-school-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Natalie Kongable</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-05-25:/blog/isu-middle-school-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Natalie Kongable, a high school student working with DIYnamics team member Alex Gonzalez at Iowa State University, describes how she taught middle schoolers about extratropical cyclones using the DIYnamics &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;table.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country &amp;#8212;- share how they&amp;#8217;ve used the DIYnamics kit and materials
in their local communities.  Also, for this post we do not include any
photos of the actual event, because minors appear and we did not
attain release forms from parents permitting their photos to be used
in this way.  Keep that in mind for your own futurue K-12-facing&amp;nbsp;events!]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Natalie Kongable, and I am a senior in high school.  I was
able to purchase and build the DIYnamics rotating table setup.  I used
it with when I was doing research for my Iowa Academy of Science
project.  My project involved collaborating with Professor Alex
Gonzalez from Iowa State University (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt;) along with two graduate
students.  We selected one experiment (The demonstration of
extratropical cyclones) and I presented it to groups of middle school
aged students (6th through 8th&amp;nbsp;grade).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/isu-middle-school-2020/isu-middle-school-2020_01.png" width="600"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/isu-middle-school-2020/isu-middle-school-2020_02.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side views of the extratropical cyclones experiment taken just after
the blue dye and then red dye was injected.  [Note from Spencer: for
those familiar with thermal wind, notice how this baroclinic eddies
simulation actually looks a lot like thermal wind in these shots.
That&amp;#8217;s because these are taken during the initial spin-up phase before
the baroclinic eddies have kicked in.  Timescale&amp;nbsp;matters!]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiments proved to be successful in students understanding of
how cyclones were formed and maintained.  The students I worked with
were from two different schools, including a homeschool, and they
enjoyed the hands-on experiment.  I would love to have more
opportunities to present to students and continue doing outreach to
engage younger students and excite them about the science aspect of
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt;.  Another thing I would like to try would be to do it with more
groups than middle schoolers; I would like to try it with elementary
students, probably about 2nd or 3rd grade, and continue it with a
variety of ages all the way up to high&amp;nbsp;school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although for the most part this was a successful experiment, there was
one improvement I would have made.  I would have tried to find a
better dish that had a flat bottom.  Most of the issues I had were
largely in part due to the slight curve of the bottom. Some of those
problems included the frozen can sliding so it was not in the center
of the dish throughout the entire experiment, and the dye would settle
into the little crevice right around the edge of the dish so no
pattern would be formed.  I believe that these are issues I would be
able to solve if I continued using the apparatus for experiments in
the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was lots of fun to be able to interact with and teach the students,
and I truly look forward to continuing with this&amp;nbsp;project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-report"></category><category term="guest-post"></category><category term="middle-school"></category><category term="high-school"></category><category term="LEGO"></category></entry><entry><title>New DIYnamics core team members</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/people-updates-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-04-21:/blog/people-updates-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics happily welcomes new members to our core team and updates the whereabouts of existing members and&amp;nbsp;alumni.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics has taken off far beyond what any of us expected when Jon,
Juan, Norris, and I got it off the ground in early 2017.  Now, over
three years later, we&amp;#8217;re happy to introduce some new members to the
core DIYnamics team and provide updates on those of us still around
and some alumni who have moved on to other exciting pursuits.  All of
this can be found on our freshly updated
&lt;a href="/pages/people.html"&gt;People&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These additions are long overdue &amp;#8212;- Alex, Jordyn, and Henry each have
been doing fantastic work for the DIYnamics efforts for a long time
already.  But better late than&amp;nbsp;never!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Alex&amp;nbsp;Gonzalez&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/people/alex-gonzalez.jpg" width="300" title="Alex Gonzalez" alt="Alex Gonzalez"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex joined the DIYnamics project in September 2019. He loves using
rotating tanks in the fluid dynamics classes he teaches at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt;. His
goal is to transition to placing more focus on applications rather
than theory in his classes. He is excited about using the DIYnamics’
rotating tanks in outreach activities to inspire a new generation of
scientists, especially those from underrepresented &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; groups. &lt;a href="https://tad.ge-at.iastate.edu/"&gt;Link
to Alex’s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt; Research Group&amp;nbsp;webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Jordyn&amp;nbsp;Moscoso&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/people/jordyn-moscoso.jpg" width="600" title="Jordyn Moscoso" alt="Jordyn Moscoso"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordyn is a graduate student in the Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences
department studying oceanography and ocean dynamics. She is excited to
be a part of the DIYnamics team and is working to bring DIYnamics into
the curriculum in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt; department. She is also a member of the
Society of Women Geoscientsts and uses DIYnamics to give hands on
experiences to women, girls, and people of other classically
underrepresented genders in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Henry&amp;nbsp;Gonzalez&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/people/henry-gonzalez.jpg" width="500" title="Henry Gonzalez" alt="Henry Gonzalez"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry Gonzalez is currently serving as the SPINLab Project Manager and
Space Magnetism Lab Manager, developing/coordinating everything from
spacecraft instruments to geophysical fluid dynamics experiments.  His
extensive knowledge in prototyping has paved the way to new modeling
systems for understanding the interiors and atmospheres of
planets.  Furthermore, he is working on the Henry &lt;span class="caps"&gt;III&lt;/span&gt; (H3) Model which
will be a portable geoshysical system that will be used for classroom
teaching of advanced concepts as well as outreach at public events and
interactive K-12 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="organization"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: DIYnamics tables in undergraduate teaching at Kiel University in Germany</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/mirjam-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Mirjam Glessmer</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-03-04:/blog/mirjam-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mirjam Glessmer describes how she and colleagues at Kiel University in Germany are using the DIYnamics tables in innovative ways in their&amp;nbsp;classrooms.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country &amp;#8212;- and in this case, the world(!) &amp;#8212;- share how they&amp;#8217;ve
used the DIYnamics kit and materials in their local&amp;nbsp;communities.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/mirjam-2020/mirjam-2020_01.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our group of students coming together at one tank to discuss
observations. Note that in the background a square tank is sitting on
a different rotating table, being spun up for the Rossby wave
experiment described&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we came across the &lt;a href="https://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/10.1175/BAMS-D-17-0215.1"&gt;DIYnamics
article&lt;/a&gt;
right after its publication,
&lt;a href="https://www.geomar.de/en/staff/fb1/od/tomartin/"&gt;Torge&lt;/a&gt; and I
(&lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/"&gt;Mirjam&lt;/a&gt;) were very excited about the
endless possibilities we saw opening up with an affordable tool like
the DIYnamics rotating table. We applied for, and were granted, money
for an “innovative teaching” project by &lt;a href="https://www.uni-kiel.de/en/"&gt;Kiel
University&lt;/a&gt;’s
&lt;a href="https://www.perle.uni-kiel.de/en"&gt;PerLe&lt;/a&gt; and built four DIYnamics
rotating tables (five if you count the one I built for personal use
;-)), which we’ve been working with for about a year now. Since we are
using them in a slightly different context than we’ve seen described
before, and also have modified and added some of the experiments, I
thought I’d report on it here. If you have any comments or suggestions
for us, please do get in&amp;nbsp;touch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;DIYnamics tables in undergraduate&amp;nbsp;education&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to using the DIYnamics rotating tables mainly for outreach
purposes which is the most common application I am aware of, we are
using them as part of a regular Bachelor-level class on &amp;#8220;ocean and
atmosphere dynamics&amp;#8221; at Geomar, Germany. I have gained a lot of
experience using a rotating table in undergraduate education at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFI&lt;/span&gt;,
Norway, but there we only had one – much bigger – table available. Now
we have four that can be used simultaneously! This is great for so
many&amp;nbsp;reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Time efficiency for the&amp;nbsp;instructor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With only one rotating table available, the typical setup I have used
was to have small groups of students come in at different times over
the course of a week or so, to do that week’s experiment with me. But
that meant that I would spend a lot of time in the lab, and a large
part of that time would be spent on waiting for the water on the
rotating table to have spun up into solid body rotation, as well as
prep time or cleaning, drying, putting away&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, wait times can easily be used for discussions of the
upcoming experiment, of the concept of a “spun up” body of water, of
how to judge whether or not a body of water is spun up or not, and
many other things. But those are things that don’t necessarily have to
be discussed in a setting of one instructor per each small student
group, they could just as well be discussed in student groups and then
in a larger&amp;nbsp;plenum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exchange between student&amp;nbsp;groups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the setup with one table and student groups coming in one after the
other, students would then write lab reports, submit them, and come
back for the next experiment. While I am sure there was some exchange
between student groups happening (which we could sometimes see from
eerily similar ways of expressing things between groups, or errors
propagating through several groups’ reports), that wasn’t an
instructional design&amp;nbsp;choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, however, when we have student groups working on the same
experiment at the same time in the same room, it is very easy to have
discussions both within individual groups and then across
groups. There are many instructional methods to choose from that
facilitate that kind of exchange, for example “think, pair, share”,
where students first think about a question individually, then pair up
with a partner (or the group at their tank) to discuss, and then
results are shared with and discussed in the whole&amp;nbsp;class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Seeing many implementations of the same&amp;nbsp;experiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason why these discussions are especially fruitful if done in
connection with simultaneously run tank experiments is that, even if
all student groups get the exact same instructions, two
implementations of the same experiment do not ever look the
same. There is always something that’s different. Maybe one tank is
spun up less than the others, or a bit wobbly, because someone bumped
into the table mid-spinup. Or the dye that is used as flow tracer has
a different density for one group (less diluted? Different
temperature?) and thus behaves differently. Or dye is put in a
different spot in the tank and thus shows different features of the
flow field. There are so many tiny things that can and will be
different from experiment to experiment, and it’s a great learning
experience to see an ensemble of different implementations and discuss
what change in boundary conditions made results look different rather
than just seeing one implementation and wrongly assuming that this is
the one and only way this experiment always turns&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Seeing many different experiments at the same&amp;nbsp;time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, there is of course the opportunity to have different student
groups work on different experiments simultaneously, which cuts down
on total prep and spin-up time and enables students to see a larger
variety of experiments. It also opens up the possibility that students
pick what experiment they want to work on – either new ones or
repeating older ones that they would like to take better pictures of
or modify something in the boundary conditions. This seems to be very&amp;nbsp;motivating!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Why we are using higher-walled&amp;nbsp;tanks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/mirjam-2020/mirjam-2020_02.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students working with an experiment on the Ekman bottom boundary
layer – one of the experiments that really benefit from a larger water
depth because this allows for observations of the development of the
boundary layer over&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the tanks we’ve seen used on the DIYnamics rotating
tables before, we chose to invest in some high-walled&amp;nbsp;tanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting feature of rotating fluid dynamics is that the flow
becomes 2D, so technically having a shallow layer of water is
completely sufficient to give a good representation of those
flows. And if we look at the aspect ratios of the oceans, they are in
fact extremely shallow compared to their horizontal extent. But it’s
easy to see a 2D flow in a shallow tank and assume that it’s 2D
because of the shape of the tank, not because of the flow itself. So
having an exaggerated third (depth) dimension that can be easily
observed by looking into the tank from the side actually helps drive
home the point that there is “nothing to see” on that dimension
because the flow really is as 2D as theory told us it would&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then there are of course the cases where the flow isn’t 2D, and
then a higher-walled tank is really convenient. For some experiments
where there are exciting things to discover by looking into the tank
from the side, check out &lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/2020/01/31/giving-it-a-side-eye-why-we-use-high-walled-tanks-on-our-rotating-table-flumefriday/"&gt;this blog
post&lt;/a&gt;
over on my&amp;nbsp;blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Experiment on planetary Rossby&amp;nbsp;waves&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first experiments we tried on our DIYnamics rotating table
was a “planetary Rossby wave” experiment. We hadn’t bought our
cylindrical tanks yet (read more about those below), so using a clear
plastic storage box was very convenient. Btw, this is one of the
experiments where looking into the tank from the side gives a lot of
interesting&amp;nbsp;insights!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/mirjam-2020/mirjam-2020_03.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Planetary Rossby waves in a square tank with a sloping&amp;nbsp;bottom.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the planetary Rossby wave experiment, we need a sloping bottom
(easiest done in a rectangular tank, but we’ve also run the same
experiment on a cone-shaped insert in a cylindrical tank) and a dyed
ice cube. When the tank is in solid body rotation, a dyed ice cube is
inserted in the shallow “eastern” corner of the tank (make sure it is
sitting far enough from the edge of the tank so it can turn around its
own axis unobstructed). For more details see &lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/2019/09/13/planetary-rossby-waves-on-beta-plane-a-super-easy-tank-experiment/"&gt;this blog
post&lt;/a&gt;,
but in a nutshell: The cold melt water sinks, setting up a column of
spinning water that sheds spinning eddies at regular intervals. Eddies
and ice cube propagate westwards. This is a really easy and fool-proof
experiment, and it looks&amp;nbsp;beautiful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Presenting the DIYnamics tanks at an institute&amp;nbsp;colloquium&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January, Torge and I gave a seminar presentation titled “you should
really play more often! Using tank experiments in teaching” at our
institute’s colloquium. In the abstract, we announced that we would
give a brief overview over our project and then give people the
opportunity to play – which we did. We had been expecting that maybe a
handful of our loyal friends would stick around after the presentation
to look at the tanks, but we were very surprised and excited to see
that pretty much everybody in the audience wanted to stay. We had set
up the four rotating tables with four different experiments and a
student presenting at each in the back of the room, and we ended up
running all the experiments repeatedly, until we were kicked out of
the room because the next lecture was about to start. It was really
motivating to see how everyone – students, PhD students, postdocs,
staff, professors – got really excited and wanted to learn more about
the tank experiments, discuss observations, modify and
experiment. This goes to show that an affordable rotating table is an
amazing tool at every level of education: There is always more to&amp;nbsp;discover!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/mirjam-2020/mirjam-2020_04.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A snapshot of the audience of our seminar presentation interacting
with the tanks and each other. We were running four experiments&amp;nbsp;simultaneously.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Follow our&amp;nbsp;experiences&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow our experiences with the DIYnamics rotating
tables, there are several options for&amp;nbsp;you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Torge and I have recently launched the “Teaching Ocean Science” blog
at
&lt;a href="https://www.oceanblogs.org/teachingoceanscience/"&gt;https://www.oceanblogs.org/teachingoceanscience/&lt;/a&gt;,
which is a joint effort of ourselves and other instructors, describing
fun hands-on stuff they do in their teaching, and students, who write
course assignments on what they are currently learning for the&amp;nbsp;blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, all the outgoing links in my guest post above are to
posts on my own blog, “Adventures in Teaching and Oceanography”, at
&lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/blog"&gt;https://mirjamglessmer.com/blog&lt;/a&gt;. I
use that blog as my own archive and document every new thing I try on
there, so you might want to sign up for email alerts or follow via my
Twitter &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/meermini"&gt;@meermini&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to writing about the DIYnamics rotating tables and what we
are up to with those (and you can be sure that if I played with a
tank, you will read it on that blog right away ;-)), I write a lot
about
&lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/2019/07/09/whats-kitchenoceanography-all-about/"&gt;#KitchenOceanography&lt;/a&gt;
(which are very easy hands-on experiments on ocean and climate topics
that you can do with household items) and
&lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/wave-watching/"&gt;#WaveWatching&lt;/a&gt; (observing
ocean physics everywhere, all the time). I also write about science
communication&amp;nbsp;issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to check out those blogs and as I wrote in the
beginning: Please get in touch if you have any comments or suggestions
for us. I am always happy to&amp;nbsp;chat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;This project has been funded by the PerLe fund for innovative teaching
through resources from the Federal Ministry of Education and Research,
grant number: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;01LP17068&lt;/span&gt;. The responsibility for the content of this
publication lies with the authors.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="guest-author"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="international"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics and Weather in a Tank at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory Open House</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/lamont-open-house-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-02-18:/blog/lamont-open-house-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; table joined forces with the Weather in a Tank in October 2019 to create a powerful one-two punch of demonstrations at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory annual Open House&amp;nbsp;event.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/lamont-open-house-2019/lamont-open-house-2019_1.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Attendees of the Lamont Open House check out the baroclinic instability demonstration up close.  Lamont volunteer Jeff Strong added green dye in addition to the standard red and blue, which adds a nice extra touch of&amp;nbsp;color.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 5, 2019, DIYnamics made its debut at the annual &lt;a href="https://openhouse.ldeo.columbia.edu/"&gt;Open House&lt;/a&gt; event held by the &lt;a href="https://www.ldeo.columbia.edu/"&gt;Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory&lt;/a&gt;, or just &amp;#8220;Lamont&amp;#8221; for short.  Lamont is the home of nearly all of the Earth Sciences conducted at &lt;a href="https://www.columbia.edu/"&gt;Columbia University&lt;/a&gt; in New York and is where Spencer currently works as a postdoctoral research scientist.  Lamont Open House is a giant public science fair event, featuring hundreds of cool demonstrations of Lamont science including a &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/Lamont.Doherty/videos/497661050966596/"&gt;trash can volcano&lt;/a&gt; and, of course, rotating tank&amp;nbsp;demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this event, Spencer introduced to Lamont the DIYnamics &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; table, which we paired with the &lt;a href="http://weathertank.mit.edu/"&gt;Weather in a Tank&lt;/a&gt; platform that Lamont already had on hand to create a very nice one-two punch of demonstrations: attendees could learn the very basics of rotating vs. non-rotating fluids from the ultra simple and approachable &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; tables, and then they could just go a few feet away to the Weather in a Tank setup where Open House volunteer Jeff Strong taught them about the polar vortex and other cool features of Earth&amp;#8217;s oceans and atmosphere via more involved&amp;nbsp;demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/lamont-open-house-2019/lamont-open-house-2019_2.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The DIYnamics table before the event kicked in to high gear.  Just out of the frame to the right was the Weather in a Tank booth led by Jeff Strong.  With only Spencer at the DIYnamics booth, and only Jeff at the Weather in a Tank booth, we didn&amp;#8217;t manage to get a picture of the DIYnamics booth in action!  Which is a good reminder: running a table with one person is possible, but especially for longer events it&amp;#8217;s much better to have multiple&amp;nbsp;volunteers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff made excellent use of technology in his demonstrations.  The Weather in a Tank platform includes a camera mounted in the rotating frame, which he fed to a projector that beamed the footage onto a screen behind him.  Meanwhile, Jeff showed animations on an iPad of real-life weather over the north pole, showing attendees just how similar the real-world patterns look like our simple rotating tank&amp;nbsp;setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/lamont-open-house-2019/lamont-open-house-2019_3.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jeff using technology to help make the connection between the behavior in the tanks and the real world.  The Weather in a Tank setup includes a mounted camera in the rotating frame, which was connected to a project and shown on the screen here, with the effective &amp;#8220;North Pole&amp;#8221; labeled.  Meanwhile, Jeff used an iPad to show animations of real-life weather patterns over the real-life North Pole.  Even from just this stillshot image you can see how similar the two&amp;nbsp;look!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One lesson we learned from this event was that, although having one person per table can work, it&amp;#8217;s much better to have two or more.  With only Spencer at the DIYnamics table, there was a lot of down time in between demos while Spencer emptied out the tanks, refilled them, got them spinning again, etc., not to mention during a break for lunch.  And likewise for Jeff at the Weather in a Tank exhibit.  If we had an extra hand or two at each table, we could have had demos running more or less nonstop throughout the&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great event, and we thank all of the attendees for their enthusiasm as well as everyone at Lamont and Columbia more broadly who helped make it happen.  We&amp;#8217;re already looking forward to Open House&amp;nbsp;2020!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-12"></category><category term="weather in a tank"></category></entry><entry><title>Society of Women Geoscientists and Project Scientist teach K-12 girls planetary fluid dynamics with a record player</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/ucla-swg-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jordyn Moscoso</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-02-07:/blog/ucla-swg-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jordyn introduces us to the Society of Women Geoscientists organization at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; and how they partnered with Project Scientist to teach K-12 girls about planetary fluid motions using a record&amp;nbsp;player.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ucla-swg-2019/ucla-swg-2019_1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ashna (left) demonstrates how rotation affects the shape of the
surface of the water in the tank, and shows how the patterns of dye a
tank develops in contrast to a tank that is not&amp;nbsp;rotating.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics made a debut in a partnership with the Society of Women
Geoscientists (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWG&lt;/span&gt;) and &lt;a href="https://projectscientist.org/"&gt;Project
Scientist&lt;/a&gt; on November 11th, 2019, at
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWG&lt;/span&gt; is a group at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; formed to support women and other
underrepresented genders in the geosciences.  Members and allies in
the group come from the Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt;)
department, the Earth, Planetary, and Space Sciences (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPSS&lt;/span&gt;)
department, the Institute of the Environment and Sustainability
(IoES), and the Geology department.  Project Scientist is a community
of girls and women excited about science.  Their mission is to expose
a diverse population of girls to high quality &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; academy that
inspires confidence in their persuit of learning throughout the&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partnered with the SPINLab, Ashna and Jewel used common household
goods, like a record player to demonstrate how the fluids on the Earth
and other planets behave in the presence of&amp;nbsp;rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ucla-swg-2019/ucla-swg-2019_2.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some volunteers from the Society of Women Geoscientists (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWG&lt;/span&gt;) with
the girls from Project Scientist. The girls joined us for experiences
in SPINLab &amp;#8212;- where DIYnamics was born &amp;#8212;- ranging from understanding
how rotation changes how fluid flows the to seeing how ozone is formed
in the atmosphere, to coding eddies and vortices moving around in a
channel.  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWG&lt;/span&gt; was happy to support and meet our future&amp;nbsp;colleagues!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The future scientists who visited &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; were between the ages of 4 and
12, and we were so impressed by their questions about how the earth
works, and their ideas for more experiments that we can run using
these rotating tanks!  We hope to expand our demonstrations next year
to include building the DIYnamics kits and run more hands on
experiments with Project Scientist next&amp;nbsp;year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-12"></category><category term="record player"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics at UCLA Exploring Your Universe 2019</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/eyu-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jordyn Moscoso</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-01-31:/blog/eyu-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For a 3rd consecutive year, DIYnamics participated in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s massive public science fair called Exploring Your Universe, with core team members and volunteers leading demonstrations for hundreds of&amp;nbsp;attendees.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: we&amp;#8217;re thrilled to have this first post from one
of our newest DIYnamics core team members, Jordyn Moscoso!  Another
post formally introducing her and some other new faces will be coming
soon.  And you can blame me for the lack of posts generally over the
past couple months&amp;#8230;plenty of great posts from Jordyn and others are
in the queue!  -S.&amp;nbsp;Hill]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2019/eyu-2019_1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris, Carlyn, and Oliver hard at work at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;!  Norris demonstrated
how to build the DIYnamics kits, Carlyn demonstrated how baroclinic
instability creates eddies that transfer heat around the tank, and
Oliver used a record player to show how centrifugal instability
pushes chia seeds outward once rotation is turned&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in November, the DIYnamics team returned to Exploring Your
Universe (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;) at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; is the largest outreach event for the
Division of Physical Sciences every year, and it involves nearly every
department.  This year the DIYnamics tent included core team member
Norris and our newest core team member Jordyn, as well as help from
two volunteers, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; graduate student Francisco Spaulding-Astudillo,
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; undergraduate student Carlyn Schmidgell, and Oliver from the
Geffen&amp;nbsp;Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year there were four different sections at the booth all showing
different aspects of Do-It-Yourself&amp;nbsp;dynamics!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Norris demonstrated how to build the DIYnamics motor using legos
   and showed the difference between a rotating and non-rotating tank.
   This experiment shows how the effect of rotation works to organize
   flow into&amp;nbsp;eddies!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carlyn showed how we use the DIYnamics setup to demonstrate how
   eddies exchange heat around the tank.  This demonstration was built
   to show how eddies move warm water and air from low latitudes to
   high latitudes, like for example to the margins of&amp;nbsp;Antarctica.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oliver showed centrifugal instability.  This instability occurs
   when fluid spins very quickly, pushing all of the fluid outward
   toward the edges of the&amp;nbsp;tank.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jordyn (that&amp;#8217;s me) demonstrated 2D turbulence using the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt;
   rotating&amp;nbsp;tank.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not all of the setups you see here are built using Legos, the
purpose of DIYnamics is to show that household objects (like a record
player) can be used to simulate the dynamics and flows on&amp;nbsp;planets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2019/eyu-2019_2.jpg" width="600"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2019/eyu-2019_3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jordyn is showing how the effect of rotation works to create vortices
in the flow when a fluid is rotating.  When a little energy is added,
or the fluid is disturbed by running a pen through the flow, the blobs
of dye stretch and move and organize into coherent&amp;nbsp;vortices!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge thank you to all of our volunteers, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Departments of
Earth, Planetary and Space Sciences and of Atmospheric and Oceanic
Sciences, the Society of Women Geoscientists, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; organizers, and
good old Jon Aurnou and the rest of the SPINLab for help!  And an
equally huge thank you to all of the wonderful kids and parents who
visited our booth.  See you all in the fall for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;2020!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: A lab planet at The Royal Observatory of Belgium</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/belgium-sphere-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Santiago Triana</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-10-31:/blog/belgium-sphere-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Santiago Triana of the Royal Observatory of Belgium shares incredible visualizations of rotating fluids in a sphere performed for research purposes and for public outreach events in Belgium and the Netherlands using the DIYnamics Lego&amp;nbsp;Table.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country &amp;#8212;- and in this case, the world(!) &amp;#8212;- share how they&amp;#8217;ve
used the DIYnamics kit and materials in their local&amp;nbsp;communities.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/mZWnvQ84rHc'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Visualizing wind shear in the lab planet by slightly changing the
rotation rate using the Lego &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IR&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;remote.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our group at the &lt;a href="https://www.astro.oma.be/en/"&gt;Royal Observatory of
Belgium&lt;/a&gt; studies the dynamics of fluid
layers inside rotating planets and moons.  It is very difficult to
imagine the kind of complex flows that we deal with.  To help us with
that, we built a miniature model of a fluid planet in our lab.
Rotation is of major importance in the study of planetary fluid
dynamics.  With our lab planet, we wanted to visualise at least
qualitatively how the fluid flow changes when the rotation speed
varies in time.  We needed our ‘planet’ to be as transparent as
possible and we also needed a way to control its rotation with some
level of&amp;nbsp;precision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_5.jpg" width="600"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_8.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Closeups of the components of the lab planet: (first image) the base
and bearings, (second image) the acrylic&amp;nbsp;globe.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We set to work building our lab planet using a 14&amp;#8221; diameter acrylic
globe, the same kind as used for outdoor lighting.  We used an
aluminium disc as a rotating platform mounted on a spherical ball
bearing, all resting on a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PVC&lt;/span&gt; stand.  We still needed a way to control
the rotation and that was when we heard about DIYnamics and thought it
would be a perfect match for our&amp;nbsp;purpose!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/woneJkvBn-4'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A beautiful wave-2 pattern has emerged in this video.  Wave-2 means
that the wave pattern that circles the globe has (roughly speaking)
two peaks and two&amp;nbsp;valleys.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, in order to visualise the currents in fluids, scientists
used Kalliroscope fluid, a rheoscopic fluid developed by Paul Matisse
in 1966, unfortunately not available anymore.  We considered mica
powder and other alternatives that ended up being not so great
compared to Kalliroscope fluid.  However, Daniel Borrero-Echeverry
from Willamette University devised an &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5045053"&gt;ingenious
way&lt;/a&gt; [1] to get the same rheoscopic
effect as Kalliroscope, simply using shaving cream!  We were able to
obtain large quantities of rheoscopic fluid, about 22 kg (or 48
pounds), which we used to fill the acrylic globe.  The technical
service from the observatory helped us with the machining of the
aluminium disc platform.  The globe is simply glued (with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RTV&lt;/span&gt;) to the
aluminium disc.  We made a threaded hole through the centre of the
disc which we use for filling/draining the&amp;nbsp;globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_1.jpg" width="300"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_2.jpg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_3.jpg" width="300"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_4.jpg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making Barbasoloscope in four easy steps (with pictures ordered left
to right then top to bottom): (1) dispense the Barbasol, (2) add
water, (3) mix, (4) let rest.  (There&amp;#8217;s a little more to it after that.  See &lt;a href=""&gt;this DIYnamics YouTube video&lt;/a&gt; for&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our setup is very close to the traditional DIYnamics except we don’t
use the Lazy Susan platform.  We use the motorised lego wheel to drive
the rotation via the aluminium disc platform.  The lego motor is
powerful enough to spin the whole device!  Mesmerising flow patterns
appear when the spin rate is changed slightly, which we do via the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IR&lt;/span&gt;
remote.  In the videos you can hear the motors whirring and change
pitch as we slow down or spin up the globe, you can see clearly the
shear in the flow caused by the accelerating/decelerating globe
surface in contact with the&amp;nbsp;fluid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/bDjIQadiCws'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Close up video of the DIYnamics Lego motor modified to drive the lab
planet rather than a Lazy&amp;nbsp;Susan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we let the globe spin for a while at a constant rate, the fluid
will eventually spin at the same rate as the globe, in sync, with no
or very little flow in the interior as indicated by the absence of any
patterns in the fluid. This might take 5 to 10 minutes to achieve.
If we reduce the speed of the globe just a notch, turbulence will
develop straddling the equator, induced by Görtler vortices most
likely.  However, if the fluid is still not yet spinning in unison
with the globe surface, turbulence develops within a very well defined
band, which we can see in the videos.  We can’t claim we understand
all features we see in the flow but we do recognise many, some of the
them resembling patterns we see in Jupiter, Saturn (think of the polar
hexagon), or the Earth’s&amp;nbsp;atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_6.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching with the lab planet at Open Door Day at the European Space
Agency centre, Noordwijk, the&amp;nbsp;Netherlands.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lab planet has been a real success during our outreach campaigns,
more than we anticipated!  We have had already a number of open days
here at the Observatory, as well as in the Brussels Planetarium and
last year we took the device to the annual open door day at the
European Space Agency’s centre in Noordwijk, the Netherlands.  During
these sessions we engage a general audience and discuss various topics
related to fluid dynamics at the planetary&amp;nbsp;scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_7.jpg" width="400"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching with the lab planet at an Open Day public outreach event at
the Royal Observatory of&amp;nbsp;Belgium.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lab planet is a reality thanks to Antony Trinh, Jeremy Rekier,
Santiago Andres Triana, the technical service at the Royal Observatory
of Belgium, and of course the DIYnamics team for their brilliant&amp;nbsp;idea!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/bTeULCHjXJg'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Flows generated in the lab planet by slightly slowing down the
rotation&amp;nbsp;rate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Borrero-Echeverry, D., Crowley, C. J., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Riddick,
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;T. P.&lt;/span&gt;(2018). Rheoscopic fluids in a post-Kalliroscope world. Physics
of Fluids, 30(8), 1–6.
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5045053"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5045053&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="guest-author"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="international"></category><category term="barbasoloscope"></category></entry><entry><title>Four new DIYnamics videos in partnership with UCLA Center for the Advancement of Teaching</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/oid-videos-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-10-18:/blog/oid-videos-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamicists and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; SPINLabbers teamed up with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Center for the Advancement of Teaching to create four new, high-quality videos featuring our &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; table, the Whale, and&amp;nbsp;Barbasoloscope.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/oid-videos-2019/oid-videos-2019_1.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Susanne Horn being filmed by (far left) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAT&lt;/span&gt; Producer-Directors Sean
and Kim in their amazing studio, assisted by Jon (and myself) for the
all-important phone&amp;nbsp;footage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this past summer, core DIYnamicist Jon Aurnou and a group of
fellow DIYnamicists and members of Jon&amp;#8217;s SPINLab worked with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s
Office of Instructional Development (since renamed to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Center
for the Advancement of Teaching, or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAT&lt;/span&gt;) to produce four amazing
videos that are now live on our YouTube channel (and embedded in this
post below the text).  The videos show how to build and use our
classic Lego table, how to build a version of our upcoming Whale
table, how to create &amp;#8220;barbasoloscope&amp;#8221; fluid for visualization, and how
to perform various demonstrations on the&amp;nbsp;Whale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAT&lt;/span&gt; has an amazing studio space on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s campus where the videos were
filmed.  I crashed the production for an hour or so to see the pros
(i.e. Kim and Sean from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OID&lt;/span&gt;) and the semi-pros (the rest of us) at
work and capture some behind-the-scenes photos.  Later on, Norris,
Henry, Yufan, and Susanne each recorded their voice overs for their
video.  Then, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OID&lt;/span&gt; took everything and edited down to four excellent&amp;nbsp;videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re extremely grateful to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAT&lt;/span&gt; for this opportunity, in particular to
Sean Cruser and Kim Cohen for their excellent camerawork, direction,
and editing.  We would love to make more high-level videos like this
moving forward&amp;#8230;Hollywood, look out!  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; is just a few miles away
after all&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/iHByXT64Dq4'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OID&lt;/span&gt; Video #1: Norris describes and shows how to build the DIYnamics
Project&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table, for use at all levels in teaching basic ocean
and atmospheric type fluid&amp;nbsp;dynamics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/9wcaDLaVazE'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OID&lt;/span&gt; Video #2: Henry Gonzalez walks you through how to set up a
Sherline &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CNC&lt;/span&gt; Rotary Table Indexer (https://www.sherline.com).  We are
using this Sherline system as a base for the DIYnamics 1 meter
diameter &amp;#8220;Whale&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;table&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/f9K3FEJkBrs'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OID&lt;/span&gt; Video #3: Yufan Xu makes a batch of &amp;#8220;Barbasoloscope&amp;#8221;
visualization fluid, approximately following the recipe given in
Borrero-Echeverry et al. Physics of Fluids,&amp;nbsp;2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/rzRVmxXnJtw'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OID&lt;/span&gt; Video #4: Susanne Horn carries out experiments on the DIYnamics 1
m Whale Table.  Because we did not correctly filter out the oils from
this batch of Barbasoloscope, it is somewhat difficult to see the full
glory of the Barbasoloscope in action.&amp;nbsp;Whoops!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="videos"></category><category term="videos"></category><category term="lego-table"></category><category term="whale2"></category><category term="news"></category><category term="barbasoloscope"></category></entry><entry><title>Vortices on our LEGO table and “The Whale2” table at Roscomare Elementary and David Geffen Academy</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/geffen-roscomare-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jon Aurnou</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-09-16:/blog/geffen-roscomare-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Core DIYnamicist Jon Aurnou shares how he and his group members taught K-8 students about vortices, including the polar vortex, using the standard &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-based DIYnamics table and the large-and-in-charge Whale&amp;nbsp;Table.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/821B56GS7zE'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Swirling polar flows reach down to lower latitudes in our
demonstration made on the 1 meter diameter Whale&amp;nbsp;Table.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Making Crazy Vortices at Roscomare Elementary&amp;nbsp;School&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prof. Aurnou took two DIYnamics Lego Tables to Career Day at Roscomare
Elementary School on April 12, 2019.  After discussing what makes
planets and their atmospheres so interesting in the classroom (How
about jets &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; vortices!), the entire class ventured outside and did
experiments on how food coloring moves around differently in standing
tanks of water compared to rotating ones.  We discussed what aspects
of the different flow patterns looks more or less like what we see in
planetary atmospheres.  Lastly, one student dumped A &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOT&lt;/span&gt; of green food
coloring into one tank and pointed out that there wasn’t anything to
see anymore.  Which is really an important experiment to carry&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/geffen-roscomare-2019/geffen-roscomare-2019-1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students at Roscomare ask Jon questions about fluid flows.  Although
one of them, Ethan (standing), has heard this stuff before&amp;#8230;Jon is
his&amp;nbsp;dad!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Attack of the Polar Vortex!!! at David Geffen&amp;nbsp;Academy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 27, 2019, members of the &lt;a href="http://spinlab.epss.ucla.edu/"&gt;SpinLab
group&lt;/a&gt; —&amp;#8212; Jewel Abbate, Jon Aurnou, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AJ&lt;/span&gt;
Chlarson, Henry Gonzalez, Emily Hawkins, Taylor Lonner and Yufan Xu
&amp;#8212;- figured out how to transport one Lego Table (easy) and our new 40&amp;#8221;
diameter prototype table, code-named Whale2 (not as easy!), over to
the Geffen Academy on the southern tip of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;’s campus.  The next
day, Prof. Aurnou lead three 50-minute classes with essential pit crew
support from Jewel, Emily, Henry and Yufan.  This demo-based
presentation, entitled “Attack of the Polar Vortex!!!”, was given to a
mix of 6th - 8th graders as part of Geffen Academy’s 2019 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Day.
After 5 minutes of slides showing how wintertime polar flows can reach
down and visit the mid-latitudes, the class ran a set of experiments
on the Lego Table to watch how a patch of dense creamer in a rotating
tank of water become unstable, and shreds itself into smaller&amp;nbsp;structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/geffen-roscomare-2019/geffen-roscomare-2019-3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jon with two happy students.  Once again, Ethan Aurnou, this time
with his sister Abby.  Pretty cool to learn science through fun
demonstrations &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AND&lt;/span&gt; have your dad visit you at&amp;nbsp;school!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then a related experiment was carried out on The Whale2, filled
with about 5 cm of water and rotating at about 8 revolutions per
minute.  Here a frozen ice-filled paint can was placed at the center
of the tank to generate cold, dense polar “air masses” which we
demarcated with blue food coloring.  We marked the warmer water near
the outside of the tank with red food coloring, and then sat back and
watched our simulated polar vortex become unstable and “attack”
Chicago and the like.  The students asked many excellent questions and
made a number of observations.  For instance, it was noted that the
processes on the smaller Lego Table appeared to mimic those on the
much larger Whale, and that this suggested that the processes we see
in our demonstrations might then scale up to larger systems like the
atmosphere.  Yes (!), that is exactly the&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="polar-vortex"></category><category term="whale2"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: Teaching with DIYnamics at Iowa State University</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/iowa-state-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Alex Gonzalez</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-08-27:/blog/iowa-state-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Professor Alex Gonzalez at Iowa State University shares how he has used DIYnamics in his&amp;nbsp;classroom.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country (and one day, the world) share how they&amp;#8217;ve used the
DIYnamics kit and materials in their local&amp;nbsp;communities.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZdFOFROqVS0'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Video footage by Prof. Gonzalez of a beautiful demonstration of Ekman
transport.  Near solid boundaries, such as near Earth&amp;#8217;s surface for
the atmosphere, the ocean floor, and the bottom of the tank ifor the
DIYnamics table, friction with the solid surface changes how the fluid
flows compared to far away from the surface, where friction can be
mostly&amp;nbsp;ignored.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I purchased and built a DIYnamics rotating tank and used it in my
undergraduate Dynamics I course at Iowa State University (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt;) during
the 2019 spring semester.  Six experiments were conducted throughout
the semester: 1) Solid body rotation, 2) Dye stirring/Rossby number,
3) Baroclinic eddies, 4) Taylor Proudman effect, 5) Fronts, and 6)
Ekman layers.  I led the first experiment on solid body rotation while
the other five experiments were co-led by one to three students in the
class.  The experiments were quite successful overall and will
continue to be used in dynamics and other courses at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some highlights, including photos and videos, are shown below. Some
issues to address for future improvement are also discussed. Any
feedback would be greatly&amp;nbsp;appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/iowa-state-2019/iowa-state-1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students awaiting (and one performing) the solid-body rotation
demonstration on the DIYnamics&amp;nbsp;table.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baroclinic eddies (no photos): The baroclinic eddies experiment was
not as successful as the others due to the lack of a flat bottom on
the rotating tank and possibly the use of a too small of a cold can at
the center.  Anyone else have similar&amp;nbsp;problems?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/iowa-state-2019/iowa-state-2.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side view of the solid-body rotation demonstration.  Notice the dye
sinking basically straight down to the bottom, with little horizontal
movement.  That means there&amp;#8217;s no relative fluid flow: all of the water
is rotating at the same rate as the tank.  As if it were a &amp;#8220;solid
body&amp;#8221;.  Get&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lack of flat bottom: One student constructed a flat bottom for one of
the two tanks that worked quite well for the experiments but over the
semester the bottom absorbed water so a more solid flat bottom is
planned to be constructed in the future.  Any ideas out there for how
to do this&amp;nbsp;affordably?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/iowa-state-2019/iowa-state-3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An overhead photo of a Taylor column demonstration.  A thin metal
puck is placed at the bottom of the tank, and after solid-body
rotation is reached, dye is injected and the rotation rate is
decreased.  This causes the dye to move toward the puck.  But, rather
than just going over it, the dye gets deflected around &amp;#8212;- as if the
puck extended all the way to the&amp;nbsp;surface.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fronts (aka the &amp;#8220;slumping dye cylinder&amp;#8221;): The fronts experiment was
the most difficult experiment to execute due to the fact that the
salty dyed water in the center kept leaking slightly into the exterior
fresh clear water.  We tried several methods and the one that worked
best was to use A &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOT&lt;/span&gt; of petroleum jelly to seal the bottom and
prevent leaking (following &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MIT&lt;/span&gt;’s weather in a tank) but it still
leaked.  Additionally, the can was removed possibly too abruptly and
induced extra momentum.  Any suggestions for how to get a better&amp;nbsp;seal?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="guest-author"></category><category term="university-teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: Saturdays at Seaport Museum’s “Fisharium” in Philadelphia, PA</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/philly-museum-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Abigale Wyatt</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-08-05:/blog/philly-museum-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Princeton University graduate student Abigale Wyatt shares the awesome outreach she and classmates are doing weekly in Philadelphia using&amp;nbsp;DIYnamics!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note: This post is part of a new series we&amp;#8217;ve started, &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt;, where students, teachers, and other
DIYnamicists tell us (and you) in their own words how they are using
DIYnamics in their schools and communities.&amp;nbsp;-Spencer]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Outside the Independence Seaport Museum, situated right on the
Delaware River in Philadelphia, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturdays are for science at the Independence Seaport Museum in
Philadelphia! A group of Princeton PhD students, Abigale Wyatt,
Allison Hogikyan and Tsung-Lin Hsieh, from the Geosciences department
and Atmosphere and Ocean Sciences program have been visiting the
museum regularly to give demonstrations using the DIYnamics&amp;nbsp;table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-2.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allison using &lt;a href="earth.nullschool.net"&gt;nullschool.net&lt;/a&gt; to talk to
visitors about how our demonstrations correlate to real-time ocean and
atmosphere&amp;nbsp;circulations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the recently opened exhibit “River Alive” that emphasizes how
local Philadelphians are impacted by and affect the Delaware River, is
the “Fisharium,” a perfect lab for demos using the rotating tank set
up. The space comes with a lab bench, faucet, and some friendly fish
to keep us company. Using velcro to stabilize the lego motor allows us
to quickly set up two rotating tanks and a stationary beaker to
demonstrate the impact of rotation on water’s&amp;nbsp;motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Visitors to the museum come in all shapes and sizes. This group of
adults was fascinated by the baroclinic instability experiment that
demonstrates how rotation plus a temperature difference can generate
unique physical&amp;nbsp;structure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The museum’s interest is in all things sea-related, including exhibits
on boat making, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; Naval history and even a new tattoo exhibit. It’s a
great space to engage with local visitors about science in a casual
environment. Our table is also a nice addition to the museum’s already
diverse biology experiments and provides an opportunity for anyone to
ask about our current research. The setting is perfect for both solo
visitors and large groups, giving us space to adjust for everyone to
have a fully hands on&amp;nbsp;experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-4.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A group of visiting Girl Scouts stops by our table to talk about
ocean circulation. After watching the dye spread and diffuse in the
still tank on the right, they’re taking turns adding dye to the
rotating&amp;nbsp;beaker.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been a great opportunity for us to chat with the public about
our science and hone our scicomm skills. We’ll be continuing our
collaboration with the museum into the next school year so if you’re
in the Philadelphia area on a Saturday afternoon, come check us&amp;nbsp;out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-5.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The “Fisharium” fish watching over the rotating fluid&amp;nbsp;experiments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="guest-author"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="public"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: DIYnamics at the Children’s Water Festival at UC Irvine</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/water-fest-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Alex Arnold</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-05-20:/blog/water-fest-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Graduate student Alex Arnold explains how she and fellow students used DIYnamics to teach young students about the Great Pacific Garbage&amp;nbsp;Patch&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Update 2019-08-05: Since this was originally posted, we have
commissioned other DIYnamics users outside of our core team to write
their own posts about how they are using our materials in their
schools and communities.  We&amp;#8217;re calling the series &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt;, and we&amp;#8217;re retroactively naming
Alex&amp;#8217;s great post below the inaugural Field Report.  Thanks again
Alex!&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8212;Spencer]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/water-fest-2019/water-fest-1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt; Graduate students Alexandrea Arnold and Daniel Clements at the
Children’s Water&amp;nbsp;Festival&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;XEP&lt;/span&gt;, the graduate student organization for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;’s Atmospheric and
Oceanic Sciences department (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt;), teamed up with DIYnamics for the
Children’s Water Festival held at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UC&lt;/span&gt; Irvine in late March.  Over 7,500
elementary school students attended this two day event, where students
learned about different elements within the water cycle through
different twenty minute&amp;nbsp;presentations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, the focus of our demonstrations was on the Pacific Garbage
Patch and the underlying mechanisms that help contribute to the growth
of the patch in the ocean.  We started our demonstrations by talking
about the water cycle, reinforcing the point that both water and the
trash that water can bring along with it can eventually run into the&amp;nbsp;ocean!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/water-fest-2019/water-fest-2.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Randy, Daniel, and Ingrid talking about the components of the water&amp;nbsp;cycle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happens to the trash once it gets into the water?&lt;/strong&gt;  Well&amp;#8230;that
depends on the material.  We used a large tank with different objects
to teach about density and buoyancy.  Some of our objects floated above
the water, some of the objects sank, and some things float within the
tank &amp;#8212;- showing that the Pacific Garbage patch is not only a problem at
the very surface of the&amp;nbsp;ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/water-fest-2019/water-fest-3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Getting ready to demonstrate some cool&amp;nbsp;science!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is the Pacific Garbage Patch located where it is?&lt;/strong&gt; Earth’s
rotation!  Here we used the DIYnamics tanks to show that the rotation
of the Earth influences ocean currents, which help to push the garbage
into one centralized patch.  We modeled this using rotating tanks as
our &amp;#8220;ocean&amp;#8221; and dye as our &amp;#8220;garbage&amp;#8221;.  Without the rotation, the
&amp;#8220;garbage&amp;#8221; was able to spread uniformly, all across the &amp;#8220;ocean&amp;#8221;, but
with rotation the dye formed a&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;patch&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/water-fest-2019/water-fest-4.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Randy pouring dye into our non-rotating tank after asking the
students to make their own hypothesis about how the &amp;#8220;garbage&amp;#8221; would
behave with and without&amp;nbsp;rotation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had so much fun spending two days with students and teachers from
classrooms all over Orange County - we can’t wait for next year!
Thanks to DIYnamics for teaming up with us for this amazing&amp;nbsp;event!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="ocean"></category><category term="Pacific Garbage Patch"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics at SoCal Fluids 2019</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/socal-fluids-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-04-20:/blog/socal-fluids-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team shared their outreach resources with other Southern California fluid dynamicists at SoCal Fluids&amp;nbsp;2019&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/socal-fluids-2019/poster.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 20, 2019, Norris and other members of the SPINLab visited sunny Santa Barbara to present
at the thirteenth annual &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/view/socalfluids2019/home"&gt;SoCal Fluids&lt;/a&gt; student
symposium. Graduate students from throughout Southern California met to share their research in
diverse fields of fluid dynamics. For his presentation, Norris took the opportunity to describe the
utility of the DIYnamics table for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; education. We believe that physical models provide a
tangible connection to the large scale processes impacting our atmosphere and oceans, helping
students develop a scientific approach to the&amp;nbsp;world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/socal-fluids-2019/baroclinic-instability.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overhead view of baroclinic instability in action. Look at the eddies towards the top and bottom right of the&amp;nbsp;image!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norris provided an overview of his favorite experiment, baroclinic instability (please watch our
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/2tIVOK9wjI4"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; for a more detailed guide). Begin the experiment by placing
a frozen can in the middle of a rotating tank of warm water. The cold source and warm body,
analogous to the Earth&amp;#8217;s poles and lower latitudes respectively, create a temperature gradient.
The blue water, chilled by the cold source, is dense and pushed out as the tank rotates. Meanwhile,
the red water, heated by the warm body, migrates to the center to fill the void. This process
continues and results in the formation of large circular structures or eddies. Baroclinic
instability defines much of the large scale behavior of Earth&amp;#8217;s atmosphere in the northern&amp;nbsp;hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/socal-fluids-2019/beach.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A visit to the beach after the&amp;nbsp;symposium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to the SoCal Fluids 2019 organizers for providing the opportunity to share our project!
And thank you to other participants for their interesting presentations and valuable insight
regarding improvements for our&amp;nbsp;material!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="symposium"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="presentation"></category></entry><entry><title>BAM(S)! New peer-reviewed paper on DIYnamics</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/bams-paper.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-03-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-03-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-03-12:/blog/bams-paper.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A paper summarizing the DIYnamics project was recently published by the Bulletin of the American Meteorological&amp;nbsp;Society.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/bams-paper/bams-title-snippet.png" width="600" title="Snippet from the title page of our BAMS paper" alt="Snippet from the title page of our BAMS paper"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A snippet from the title page of our &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BAMS&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;paper.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We DIYnamicists are thrilled to share that the
&lt;a href="https://www.ametsoc.org/index.cfm/ams/publications/bulletin-of-the-american-meteorological-society-bams/"&gt;Bulletin&lt;/a&gt;
of the &lt;a href="https://www.ametsoc.org/index.cfm/ams/"&gt;American Meteorological
Society&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8212;- &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BAMS&lt;/span&gt; as its more
commonly known &amp;#8212;- a prestigious journal that publishes peer-reviewed
papers on the latest advances in meteorology, climate science, and
weather/climate science education, recently published an &lt;a href="https://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/10.1175/BAMS-D-17-0215.1"&gt;article all
about
DIYnamics&lt;/a&gt;.
It was written by several of us in the first half of 2018 and accepted
for publication a few months later, and was then published as part of
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BAMS&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217; December 2018 issue.  (Academic publishing does not operate at
lightning&amp;nbsp;speed!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Titled &amp;#8220;Affordable rotating fluid demonstrations for geoscience
education: The &lt;em&gt;DIYnamics&lt;/em&gt; project&amp;#8221;, it provides an overarching
summary of the whole endeavor: why rotating tanks are valuable
teaching tools, why there&amp;#8217;s a need for cheaper devices and easy-to-use
teaching materials, how our platform works, past outreach events that
we&amp;#8217;ve done (see many other blog posts for details on those), and so
on.  As academic journals go, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BAMS&lt;/span&gt; is very not stuffy, and we
deliberately wrote the article so that anybody could read it and
understand it&amp;#8230;since that&amp;#8217;s basically the whole point of DIYnamics&amp;nbsp;anyways!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a major honor for us, and we sincerely hope that more and
more people will learn about DIYnamics and take it seriously thanks to
this.  In fact, already at least one community college professor
emailed me who plans to use it in one of his classrooms.  Huge thanks
go to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BAMS&lt;/span&gt; editors, publishing staff, the two peer reviewers who
provided really valuable suggestions (one was anonymous, the other was
&lt;a href="http://www.met.reading.ac.uk/~williams/"&gt;Prof. Paul Williams&lt;/a&gt; of the
University of Reading), and to everybody else along the way who has
made this&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="announcements"></category><category term="paper"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics at the AGU Fall 2018 meeting</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/agu-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-12-13:/blog/agu-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team shared their efforts to promote geoscience education at the Fall 2018 meeting of the American Geophysical&amp;nbsp;Union.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/agu-2018/agu-2018-tuesday-wide.png" width="600" title="Experiments with the DIYnamics table" alt="Experiments with the DIYnamics table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris describing experiments possible using the DIYnamics table and
their relevance to the behavior of planetary fluid bodies. Over the
course of two poster sessions, we had the opportunity to share our
educational tools with dozens of conference attendees from diverse&amp;nbsp;backgrounds.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 11 and 13, 2018, the DIYnamics team presented at the Fall
2018 meeting of the &lt;a href="https://sites.agu.org/"&gt;American Geophysical Union&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt;). &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt;, currently
celebrating its 100th anniversary, annually holds the largest
geoscience conference in the world. Norris, Spencer and Jon had a great
experience spreading the word about DIYnamics and listening to feedback
from members of the geoscience community - including some who are
already using our&amp;nbsp;materials!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/agu-2018/agu-2018-tuesday-narrow.png" width="600" title="Models can be made using household items" alt="Models can be made using household items"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris sharing the household items necessary to create your own
geophysical fluid dynamics model. The goal of DIYnamics is to promote
geoscience education by making physical models, a useful tool for
studying large scale real world phenomena, as accessible as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt; provided a unique opportunity to share DIYnamics with individuals
from institutions around the world. During our poster sessions, we
prepared demonstrations centered around the DIYnamics table - a fun
logistical challenge 2,500+ miles away from home! We showed how
physical models of planetary fluid bodies can be constructed using 
household items, whether they be LEGOs + a lazy susan for our rotating
table or a frozen can for our cold source. These accessible tools
allow audiences at all levels to observe the fluid dynamics behind
weather, ocean circulation and more providing tremendous educational&amp;nbsp;benefit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/agu-2018/agu-2018-thursday.png" width="600" title="Poster detailing the DIYnamics project" alt="Poster detailing the DIYnamics project"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris with his jerry rigged DIYnamics table setup. Experiments can
be conducted with readily available resources and the number of 
&amp;#8220;recipes&amp;#8221; continues to&amp;nbsp;grow.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the conference, we conducted experiments highlighting solid body
rotation, mechanically generated vortices and baroclinic instability.
For the big picture, we hope that our physical models help individuals
think analytically when approaching real world phenomena. Models are
integral to science because they simplify and facilitate the study of
complex&amp;nbsp;systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/agu-2018/agu-2018-barbasol.png" width="600" title="Close up image of rotating convection in rheoscopic fluid" alt="Close up image of rotating convection in rheoscopic fluid"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After placing rheoscopic fluid in a rotating tank, we observed an
interesting pattern of spirals arranged in concentric circles. This
can be attributed to rotating convection, prompted by differences in
temperature at the top and bottom of the fluid body, resulting in the
formation of columnar structures (spirals are their surface manifestation).
The concentric circle arrangement occurs because the bottom of the
tank features similar&amp;nbsp;ridges.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team was amazed by &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5045053"&gt;Borrero-Echeverry et al. (2018)&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;#8220;do-it-yourself&amp;#8221; rheoscopic fluid made using Barbasol shaving cream.
Rheoscopic fluid contains small particles suspended in water and
allows audiences to track the flow of fluid. At &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt;, we greatly
enjoyed talking with individuals who share our passion for outreach
and hearing stories of the DIYnamics table in use! As more people
adopt our system, we are excited to see what experiments the
community has in&amp;nbsp;store!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt; for providing a platform to share DIYnamics, the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPSS&lt;/span&gt; Strauss Family Fund for Undergraduate Opportunity for supporting
Norris&amp;#8217; first conference visit and last but not least, the conference
attendees who came to our poster and provided their valuable&amp;nbsp;feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="conference"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="education"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics at UCLA Exploring Your Universe 2018</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/eyu-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-11-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-11-04:/blog/eyu-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics returned to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s annual Exploring Your Universe science fair with our Lego-based platforms and larger square&amp;nbsp;tank.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2018/eyu-2018-norris-legos.jpg" width="600" title="Norris helping visitors build their own motors" alt="Norris helping visitors build their own motors"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris helps visitors at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; build their very own DIYnamics motors.
Over the course of the roughly 5 hour event, dozens of kids
successfully built their own, usually with very little help from us&amp;nbsp;required.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 4, 2018, the DIYnamics team made a triumphant return to
the &lt;a href="https://www.exploringyouruniverse.org/"&gt;Exploring Your Universe&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;) science fair held every fall at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;.  Old-timers Spencer and
Norris and newcomers Calvin and Santiago had a blast spending the day
helping kids and their families learn about rotating fluids using the
DIYnamics&amp;nbsp;materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2018/eyu-2018-calvin-top.jpg" width="600" title="Calvin using a spinning top to teach about rotation" alt="Calvin using a spinning top to teach about rotation"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Calvin using a spinning top to help these &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; visitors get a more
intuitive feel for why rotation effects fluids like water and air.
Just like a top stays upright if its spinning but falls over if it&amp;#8217;s
stationary, motions within rotating fluids get aligned with the
rotation axis, while non-rotating fluids move in all&amp;nbsp;directions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like our inaugural appearance at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; in 2017, we had three different
sections of our booth, all of them going&amp;nbsp;simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build your own DIYnamics motor: Using the DIYnamics official
   printed instructions, visitors got to assemble their own DIYnamics
   motors.  Norris kept watch and helped out when necessary, but
   mostly kids were able to build them start-to-finish on their&amp;nbsp;own!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rotating vs. non-rotating tanks: Calvin and Santiago led our
   classic demonstration comparing how dye behaves when dropped into a
   rotating tank vs. a non-rotating one.  They also made great use of
   spinning tops to illustrate how rotation makes things (including
   fluids) stand up&amp;nbsp;straight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Winter storms using the big square tank: Once every hour, Spencer
   performed the demonstration of &amp;#8220;baroclinic instability&amp;#8221; using a
   bigger tank &amp;#8212;- the same one that we used to create our
   &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/5bnmaYOFerk"&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/b4f0plA3_Bg"&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; on the same topic.  With a
   paint can filled with ice in the middle, water gets cooled in the
   middle of the tank compared to the outer edges.  This temperature
   contrast combined with rotation gives rise to beautiful swirling
   eddies that act to transfer heat from the warm section to the cold
   section&amp;#8230;just like the big winter storms in Earth&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;atmosphere!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2018/eyu-2018-booth.jpg" width="600" title="Santiago and Calvin manning our booth" alt="Santiago and Calvin manning our booth"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Calvin and Santiago (both facing toward the camera; Santiago on the
right) manning the DIYnamics booth.  Calvin and Santiago were
first-time DIYnamics volunteers, and they did an amazing job!
Especially given that we didn&amp;#8217;t have as many people this year (only 4
total).  Thanks&amp;nbsp;guys!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; also marked the debut of our amazing new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-based DIYnamics logo
(image below).  How cool is&amp;nbsp;that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2018/lego-diynamics-logo.jpg" width="600" title="Our awesome new LEGO-based logo" alt="Our awesome new LEGO-based logo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our awesome new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-based DIYnamics logo.  We&amp;#8217;re definitely going to
start using this on the website and everywhere else we can!  Thanks to
Jon Aurnou for the idea, and Norris for actually building&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge thanks to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; organizers and volunteers, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;
Department of Earth, Planetary, and Space Sciences staff who helped us
setup, Jon Aurnou and the rest of the SPINLab for help (and including
us in their pizza order!), and of course to the wonderful kids and
parents who came to our booth.  See you in 2019 for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; Round&amp;nbsp;3!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>New instructional videos with rotating frame footage</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/new-how-to-videos.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-05-24:/blog/new-how-to-videos.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have posted new videos to our YouTube channel providing &amp;#8220;how-to&amp;#8221; instructions for our core demonstrations, including recording them from the rotating&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At long last, we have figured out a cheap and easy way (a.k.a. the
DIYnamics way!) of capturing footage of demonstrations on the
DIYnamics table from the rotating frame.  A simple tripod for phone
cameras sits on the DIYnamics table, with its three legs surrounding
the tank in the middle.  The phone can be fastened to the tripod in
two&amp;nbsp;ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the detachable clip that comes with the tripod to fasten the
   phone into place, and then orient it to point down towards the
   tabletop.  The footage won&amp;#8217;t be from directly overhead, but it
   still looks&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use duct tape to fasten the camera into place between the three
   tripod legs.  With enough tape, you can create a surprisingly
   sturdy base that will keep your phone in place even at fast
   rotation&amp;nbsp;rates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In either case, be sure to get the camera into place &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt;
filling the tank!  That way, if you accidentally drop the phone while
setting it up, it won&amp;#8217;t end up taking a bath!  Once the phone is
fastened into place with either method, it should be pretty secure,
even when the table is rotating.  But no matter what, you&amp;#8217;re
ultimately hanging an expensive phone in air directly (or almost
directly) above a tank of water, so be careful throughout!  (Here&amp;#8217;s
where our lawyers would have us put in a disclaimer about not being
liable for damages blah blah&amp;#8230;if we had&amp;nbsp;lawyers.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We created new &amp;#8220;recipe&amp;#8221; videos to show several demonstrations using
this new capabality.  Here&amp;#8217;s the one for baroclinic&amp;nbsp;instability:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/2tIVOK9wjI4'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And one for solid-body&amp;nbsp;rotation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/oCg1tK4arNM'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And one for the behavior of non-rotating&amp;nbsp;fluids:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/5wJvRpiA38Q'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And one for the &amp;#8220;spinning dye&amp;nbsp;curtain&amp;#8221;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/dn_bjnc2a80'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="videos"></category><category term="videos"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category><category term="instructions"></category><category term="solid-body rotation"></category></entry><entry><title>El Marino Language School Science Fair</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/el-marino-science-fair.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-04-27:/blog/el-marino-science-fair.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team taught basics of rotating fluids using our beloved tables, frozen cans of tomato paste, inflatable globes, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Batmen at a really cool science&amp;nbsp;fair.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-sean.jpg" width="600" title="Sean leading a demo" alt="Sean leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean leads a demonstration of &amp;#8220;baroclinic instability&amp;#8221; (a.k.a. the
combination of a strong temperature contrast and rotation that
generates storms on Earth) to El Marino students and parents.  They&amp;#8217;re
so focused!  We&amp;#8217;re now using a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Power Functions remote control to
reduce the rotation rate for this demonstration, which makes these
eddies larger and therefore more engaging.  Even with the bigger
eddies, we were also able to shrink the tank compared to previous
attempts, which allows for a little more breathing&amp;nbsp;room.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 27, 2018, Ashna, Sean, and Spencer of the DIYnamics team
performed hands-on demonstrations for dozens of kids at the 23rd
annual science fair of the &lt;a href="https://elmarino.ccusd.org/"&gt;El Marino Language
School&lt;/a&gt;, a foreign language-focused
elementary school in the Culver City Unified School District, in
Culver City, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;.  In a cool twist on the traditional elementary
school-level science fair, El Marino&amp;#8217;s fair featured science posters
and demonstrations both from their own students and from multiple
science groups at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;.  So the students got to show off their awesome
science and simultaneously learn about the just-as-awesome science
conducted at the university level.  And they even fed us dinner!
Naturally, this was an event that DIYnamics wasn&amp;#8217;t going to&amp;nbsp;miss!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-ashna.jpg" width="600" title="Ashna leading a demo" alt="Ashna leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our newest DIYnamicist, Ashna, with two excited young El Marino
students eager to drop dye into our tanks.  But before they do so,
Ashna makes sure that they make a hypothesis about what they will see
in each tank.  Then, once the dye has been injected, she asks them to
describe what they are seeing, to decide if their hypothesis was
right, and then ultimately link the results back to the underlying
science we&amp;#8217;re trying to teach.  This gets participants engaged in
active learning throughout the&amp;nbsp;demonstration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We came equipped with a handful of our DIYnamics rotating table
platforms, our handy globe, and some &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Batman figurines to teach
the students and parents who came by about how Earth&amp;#8217;s rotation and
temperature contrasts combine to generate the weather patterns that we
know and (sometimes)&amp;nbsp;love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-spencer-sean.jpg" width="600" title="Spencer and Sean leading a demo" alt="Spencer and Sean leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spencer using an inflatable globe with a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; figurine (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Batman,
to be specific) taped onto the north pole to make the connection with
students between the real world and the tanks on the table.  The
DIYnamics table farthest back in this image has another &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Batman
taped at its center, sitting on top of a polar stereographic map
(a.k.a. a map centered on the North Pole).  Spencer spins the globe
showing that Batman spins with it, and at the same time Sean spins the
table showing that Batman spins the exact same way there!  We&amp;#8217;ve found
this really helps students make the otherwise difficult connection
between tanks of water and the real&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parents were a great bunch too!  One father told us that he is a
pilot, and that our explanation of weather systems using the DIYnamics
was the best one he&amp;#8217;s ever heard!  Pilots really need to know the
weather to fy safely, so that&amp;#8217;s no small compliment (if we may say&amp;nbsp;so).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-bci-closeup.jpg" width="600" title="El Marino students getting a closeup look at baroclinic instability" alt="El Marino students getting a closeup look at baroclinic instability"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;El Marino students eagerly awaiting the onset of &amp;#8220;storms&amp;#8221; driven by
the frozen can of tomato paste in the center of the table.  Initially,
all of the blue dye was injected next to the can and all of the red
dye outside of it.  But you can see that the blue dye has moved
outward in places, while the red dye has moved in toward the can.
(Don&amp;#8217;t be alarmed by the red patch on the hand pointing down at the
tank&amp;#8230;one downside of using red dye is that when it gets on hand it
looks like blood!  No DIYnamicists (or students or parents) were
harmed in the making of this&amp;nbsp;demonstration.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Erika M. von Euw of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; and the El Marino Language
School &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PTA&lt;/span&gt; for organizing, the many student and parent volunteers at
the event, and most of all the great kids and parents who came to our
table.  We&amp;#8217;re crossing our fingers that we get a repeat invitation for
next year&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;fair!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics tables used in an undergraduate+graduate level course</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/ucla-epss-class.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-04-26:/blog/ucla-epss-class.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics has now officially been implemented into undergraduate and graduate teaching, as part of a &amp;#8220;lab day&amp;#8221; in a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;course.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/jmitch-course-tables2018.jpg" width="600" title="DIYnamics tables after the demo, with students and Prof. Mitchell at the next station" alt="DIYnamics tables after the demo, with students and Prof. Mitchell at the next station"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students in the background at one of Prof. Mitchell&amp;#8217;s demonstration
stations.  They had just finished at the DIYnamics station, where we
used our simple tables to teach some of the basic properties of
rotating fluids.  Spencer can&amp;#8217;t multi-task well enough to have gotten
a picture of the students while they were at our station, but they
really were just there, we&amp;nbsp;swear!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 26, 2018, DIYnamics marked a major milestone by being
incorporated into undergraduate and graduate-level curricula.
Prof. Jonathan Mitchell of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Department of Earth, Planetary,
and Space Sciences and Department of Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences
(that&amp;#8217;s a mouthful!) invited us to use the DIYnamics materials as part
of a &amp;#8220;lab demos&amp;#8221; day in his course to teach some basic principles of
rotating&amp;nbsp;fluids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With only one of us (Spencer) there, it was difficult to get pictures
of the students at the DIYnamics station in the moment.  So the
picture above showing the aftermath &amp;#8212;- with dye in both the rotating
and non-rotating tables, and the students moved on to the next station
&amp;#8212;- will have to&amp;nbsp;suffice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shows that the DIYnamics materials can be effective teaching
tools from the elementary school to graduate levels!  Of course, the
level of complexity of the accompanying explanations has to be
tailored to the audience: for early elementary school students, we&amp;#8217;re
content with the students recognizing that things are different when
you rotate or not, whereas at the university level we&amp;#8217;re connecting
the demonstations to concepts like the Coriolis parameter, solid body
rotation, spinup times, the Rossby number, and baroclinic instability.
But the physical demonstrations we perform are essentially identical
across these&amp;nbsp;levels!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to Prof. Mitchell for allowing us to take part in his
class, Alex Gonzalez of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; and the Jet Propulsion Laboratory for his
assistance with the DIYnamics station, Henry Gonzalez, Emily Hawkins,
and Helen Parish of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPSS&lt;/span&gt; department for their work on the awesome
stably stratified convection station, and to all of the students for
indulging&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More DIYnamics at the university&amp;nbsp;level&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prof. Mitchell&amp;#8217;s class was a great way to inaugurate DIYnamics&amp;#8217; use at
the college teaching level, and we&amp;#8217;re excited for him to (hopefully!)
have us back later in the quarter to help him teach &amp;#8220;baroclinic
instability&amp;#8221;&amp;#8230;they haven&amp;#8217;t gotten that far in the lectures yet.  But
our expansion into the university level isn&amp;#8217;t stopping&amp;nbsp;there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/angel-video-bci-snapshot.png" width="600" title="Snapshot of a video taken by Angel Adames using his DIYnamics table" alt="Snapshot of a video taken by Angel Adames using his DIYnamics table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snapshot from the video that Prof. Adames posted to his Facebook page
using the DIYnamics table to (kind of) demonstrate baroclinic
instability.  Thanks for trying us out, Prof. Adames!  We&amp;#8217;ll help you
work out the kinks of getting that demonstration working properly.
Looks&amp;nbsp;awesome!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dept.atmos.ucla.edu/stewart"&gt;Prof. Andrew Stewart&lt;/a&gt; of the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt; Department and &lt;a href="http://clasp.engin.umich.edu/people/afadames"&gt;Prof. Ángel
Adames&lt;/a&gt; of the
University of Michigan Department of Climate and Space Science have
both purchased and successfully built their own DIYnamics tables and
intend to use them in courses they teach, also at the university
level.  Thanks both for giving us a try!  We&amp;#8217;re eager to see how their
DIYnamics-based teaching pans&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as we DIYnamics team members love putting on demonstrations
ourselves, there are only so many of us, compared to millions of
students around the world that could learn from these materials.
That&amp;#8217;s why we always try to leave behind a complete DIYnamics rotating
table kit behind at the schools we visit.  And that&amp;#8217;s why efforts like
these by other teachers and professors to use our materials themselves
are the most important thing moving&amp;nbsp;forward!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="courses"></category><category term="colleges"></category><category term="undergraduate"></category><category term="graduate"></category><category term="curriculum"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics featured on UCLA Physical Sciences website</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/ucla-website-story.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-03-25:/blog/ucla-website-story.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Division of Physical Sciences has a new article on DIYnamics on their main website and has added DIYnamics to its Outreach&amp;nbsp;page.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ucla-physci-pic1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ucla-phy-sci-site-snippet.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snippet from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Physical Sciences website with the link to the
story they commissioned about DIYnamics.  How cool is&amp;nbsp;that?!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This isn&amp;#8217;t exactly an event, but it&amp;#8217;s exciting enough that we felt it
deserved a post&amp;nbsp;anyways!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of March 2018, the DIYnamics project is now featured in multiple
places on the official website of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Physical Sciences Division
(link to main site &lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;;
permalink to the DIYnamics story
&lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/spinlab/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  Not only
that, they have also listed us as one of the &amp;#8220;Year-Round Programs&amp;#8221;
available for community and K-12 outreach on their &lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/outreach/"&gt;outreach
page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Physical Sciences Division, one of five divisions of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;
College of Letters and Sciences, oversees the Atmospheric and Oceanic
Sciences Chemistry &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Biochemistry, Earth, Planetary, and Space
Sciences, Mathematics, Physics &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Astronomy, and Statistics
Departments, collectively home to thousands of students and hundreds
of faculty and staff.  With all of the amazing research and outreach
acivities that goes on across the division, it&amp;#8217;s a real honor for us
to be featured on their page so&amp;nbsp;prominently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to Lisa Garibay of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Physical Sciences Divison for
initially taking an interest in us, writing the article, and getting
us featured on both pages.  They say any publicity is good publicity,
in which case this is absolutely fantastic publicity!  We&amp;#8217;re looking
forward to getting our materials into the hands of even more educators
thanks to these&amp;nbsp;links.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="press"></category><category term="colleges"></category></entry><entry><title>UCLA Exploring Your Universe (EYU) 2017</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/eyu-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-11-05:/blog/eyu-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team ran a booth at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s massive public science fair &amp;#8220;Exploring Your Universe,&amp;#8221; featuring demonstrations and kids building their own DIYnamics&amp;nbsp;tables.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_sean.jpg" width="600" title="Sean leading a demo" alt="Sean leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean leading a demonstration using DIYnamics tables.  The farther
table has a special acryllic sidewall that enables us to fill the
whole table with water.  The nearer one uses a plastic planter tray
that costs a few dollars to achieve nearly the same&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 5, 2017, the DIYnamics team performed hands-on
demonstrations for hundreds of kids at the annual &lt;a href="https://www.exploringyouruniverse.org/"&gt;Exploring Your
Universe&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;) event at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; is basically a massive science fair, with groups from nearly every
science department at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;, from astronomers to biochemists,
performing demonstrations to teach kids (and their parents!) about
their science.  Of course, DIYnamics had a booth where we had kids
build our tables, use them to learn about rotating fluids, and also
give more in-depth demonstrations using our larger, custom square
tank.  We had a blast showing off our equipment and teaching science
to hundreds of people in total over the course of the&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_norris.jpg" width="600" title="Norris helping kids build their own tables" alt="Norris helping kids build their own tables"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris helping out as several kids (and an adult!) build their own
motors for the DIYnamics table.  His table was swamped all day; kids
really loved building these!  Who doesn&amp;#8217;t love building with&amp;nbsp;LEGOs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One highlight of the day was our newest activity, wherein kids got to
create the DIYnamics rotating tank kit themselves!  We provided all of
the needed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; parts, along with printouts of our official
instructions of how to assemble the motor.  Dozens of kids went
step-by-step through the instructions, creating the finished product
in just a few minutes every time.  We provided a little guidance here
and there, but mostly they were able to do it all on their&amp;nbsp;own!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever somebody finished building their motor, we would then use it
to drive a table in a science demonstration.  The kids loved to hear
us announce their name and to see their creation used to perform a
real-world science experiment.  Overall, this affirmed our belief that
our kit really is easy to build and use, and that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; aspect of
the apparatus adds to the connection students make with the science &amp;#8212;
if we can learn about something using LEGOs and food coloring, how
hard can it really&amp;nbsp;be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_juan.jpg" width="600" title="Juan leading a demonstration at EYU" alt="Juan leading a demonstration at EYU"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan demonstrating baroclinic instability using our large square
tank, along with a GoPro in the rotating frame that streams footage to
his iPad.  Look at all those excited&amp;nbsp;faces!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight was demonstrating baroclinic instability in our
larger square tank.  By putting a bucket of ice in the center, we
created baroclinic eddies and added some &amp;#8220;Hollywood magic&amp;#8221; via a GoPro
mounted in the rotating frame.  The rotating frame footage was
streamed directly to an iPad, rather than to an iPhone + projector as
we had in the past.  As usual, this was a crowd&amp;nbsp;favorite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_baroclinic.jpg" width="600" title="Baroclinic instability on the DIYnamics table generated at EYU" alt="Baroclinic instability on the DIYnamics table generated at EYU"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Baroclinic instability generated on the DIYnamics table using a
frozen can of tomato paste as the cold source at the center.  We were
happily shocked when this worked first try, all while we were getting
setup for the rest of the event!  Huge thanks to Henry Gonzalez for
making the acryllic sidewall that enabled the fluid to span the
table&amp;#8217;s full&amp;nbsp;width.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in addition to the baroclinic instability demonstration on
the big tank, we managed to get it working for the first time on the
smaller DIYnamics table!  These eddies need a sufficiently large tank
in order to grow (specifically, the tank radius must be appreciably
larger than the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rossby_radius_of_deformation"&gt;&amp;#8220;Rossby radius of
deformation&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;,
which determines the size of the eddies), and that extra space was
enabled by an acryllic sidewall that Jon installed on one of the
tables with the help of Henry Gonzalez of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Dept. of Earth,
Planetary, and Space Sciences.  Instead of a paint bucket filled with
ice, we used a frozen can of tomato paste, which also allowed for more
room for the eddies to grow.  We&amp;#8217;re really excited to try this one
again and ultimately create a lesson plan and videos for&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to returning volunteer Chloe Wicker, first time
volunteer Tersi Arias-Young, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; organizers, and most of all the
great kids and parents who came to our booth.  We&amp;#8217;re already looking
forward to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;2018!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="public"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics + a record player at the Sierra Nevada Aquatic Research Laboratory</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/snarl-event.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-06-13:/blog/snarl-event.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamicist Jon Aurnou led demonstrations using the DIYnamics table and a record player&amp;#8230;and even got written up in the local&amp;nbsp;newspaper!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On June 13, DIYnamics&amp;#8217; own Prof. Jon Aurnou led an outreach event
featuring our Lego-based rotating tanks at the Sierra Nevada Aquatic
Research Laboratory
(&lt;a href="http://www.ucnrs.org/reserves/sierra-nevada-aquatic-research-laboratory.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SNARL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).
Jon gave a public lecture on his research on Jupiter&amp;#8217;s jets and
performed demonstrations for before and after the lecture.  The event
was even written up in a full-page article in the community&amp;#8217;s local
newspaper, &lt;em&gt;The Sheet&lt;/em&gt;.  Checkout a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/pdfs/aurnou_event_article_2017-06.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;; DIYnamics
is featured at the top of page 1 and all of page&amp;nbsp;23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon utilized a feature of the DIYnamics table that we hadn&amp;#8217;t in our
prior events: pouring water directly into the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OXO&lt;/span&gt; lazy susan, rather
than into a container sitting on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OXO&lt;/span&gt;.  This utilizes the full 16&amp;#8221;
diameter surface, although because the rim is only around 1/2&amp;#8221; tall,
only a shallow layer can be attained.  But this is more like Earth&amp;#8217;s
atmosphere or ocean anyways!  In fact, the true aspect ratio (i.e. the
ratio of how wide they are to how tall they are) of either of these is
even larger &amp;#8212; not far from that of a single piece of&amp;nbsp;paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/snarl/jon-oxo.jpg" width="600" title="Jon using the DIYnamics table" alt="Jon using the DIYnamics table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jon using the DIYnamics Table to teach kids and adults about rotating
fluids.  Photo credit: Abagael&amp;nbsp;Giles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon complemented the demonstrations performed on the DIYnamics table
with others using a turntable (i.e. what you use to play vinyl records
or be a legit &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt;).  Turntables are another great tool for these
demonstrations.  Like the DIYnamics table, they are portable and
inexpensive compared to custom built tanks primarily used at
universities.  And unlike the DIYnamics table (at least for now), many
have a lever that enables varying the rotation rate by up to +/-10%,
which is needed for e.g. demonstrating &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor_column"&gt;Taylor
columns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(One snag with using record players is the center nub that keeps vinyl
records centered as they spin.  A notch has to be machined out of the
bottom of your tank, or the tank has to be sitting on something like a
platform with&amp;nbsp;legs.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole event was a major success in Jon&amp;#8217;s eyes, as the crowd seemed
really interested in the hands-on demonstrations.  &amp;#8220;Kids loved getting
to operate the table themselves. They kept playing with it until it
got dark outside,&amp;#8221; Jon said.  &amp;#8220;And they made a complete mess and asked
a lot of questions -– a great sign that they had fun and learned&amp;nbsp;something.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/snarl/jon-record-player.jpg" width="600" title="Jon using a record player" alt="Jon using a record player"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prof. Aurnou using a turntable (a.k.a. a record player) at the same
event.  Turntables are another great way to demonstrate the behavior
of rotating fluids.  Photo credit: Abagael&amp;nbsp;Giles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="public"></category><category term="record player"></category><category term="press"></category></entry><entry><title>Ralph Bunche Middle School Event</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/ralph-bunche-event.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-22T16:16:01-06:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T16:16:01-06:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-05-22:/blog/ralph-bunche-event.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team brought their rotating tables to the 7th grade science class at Ralph J. Bunche Middle School in Compton, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On May 22nd, 2017, we visited Ralph Bunche Middle School in Compton,
California. Similarly to our La Tijera K-8 School events, we first
introduced students to the field of geophysical fluid dynamics
(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;). We sought to teach students about the importance of models in
studying science and, to this end, we showed how our assortment of
rotating tanks can be used to illustrate aspects of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;. Both the
group experiments and individual &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; Rotating Tank experiments went&amp;nbsp;great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lecture" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/sean-slide-show.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean provides a lecture on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt; and the use of models in studying
science. Lecture slides can be found
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ClYEmFAEATzG2iHZ8uqD2pzgEYSqbrYZD0xDRfuADzk/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="LEGO Table" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/katie-students.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Rotating Column" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/small-table-solid-body.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Katie and other members of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; Rotating Tank team demonstrate how
rotating tanks are a simple yet effective tool for studying &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;. Among
other experiments, students created a vertical column and learned how
it mirrors the interior of rotating&amp;nbsp;planets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="White Whale 1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/white_whale_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="White Whale 2" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/white_whale_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan provides a demonstration of the mechanical creation of
vortices, a.k.a. the swirling patterns in the dye. When students dip
their hands into the large rotating tank, the physical disturbance
results in turbluence. Other sources of turbluence like the movement
of heat can also generate&amp;nbsp;vortices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Square Table" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/square-tank.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan shows how an uneven temperature distribution can influence
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;. An ice bucket at the center of the tank and rotation result in
the formation of vortices. This behavior reflects the weather patterns
of the Earth&amp;#8217;s middle latitudes. A video of this demonstration is
available &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G26klqKKCmM"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category></entry><entry><title>La Tijera K-8 School Event</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/la-tijera-events.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-05-19:/blog/la-tijera-events.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team brought rotating tables large and small to La Tijera K-8 Charter School in Inglewood, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;, to teach basics Earth&amp;#8217;s atmospheric and oceanic&amp;nbsp;motions.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On May 12th and May 19th, 2017, we visited La Tijera K-8 School in
Inglewood, California. We introduced seventh and eighth grade students
to the study of geophysical fluid dynamics (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;) and how this pertains
to our everyday lives. Like many other areas of science, studying &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;
involves the extensive use of scientific models and, to this end, we
brought a range of rotating tables to showcase key concepts. Everyone
had a lot of fun during group demonstrations and individual
experiments involving the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; Rotating Tank. At the end, we talked
with students about how they can pursue careers in&amp;nbsp;science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Model" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/globe-table.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Gyroscope" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/gyroscope.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean and Spencer discuss how &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt; can be studied using smaller scale
models. Lecture slides can be found
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ClYEmFAEATzG2iHZ8uqD2pzgEYSqbrYZD0xDRfuADzk/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="White Whale 1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/white_whale_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="White Whale 2" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/white_whale_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan demonstrates the creation of vortices using our large rotating
tank nicknamed the &amp;#8220;White Whale.&amp;#8221; When students placed their hands in
the water, vortices were mechanically generated (seen as swirling
patterns of the colored dyes). Other forms of turbulence can also
create&amp;nbsp;vortices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/square-tank.png" width="450" title="The square tank" alt="The square tank"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/square-projector.png" width="450" title="The projector" alt="The projector"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan provides a demonstration on the effects of temperature
distributions on rotating fluids. At the center of the square tank is
an ice bucket, which cools the nearby water. The resulting temperature
contrasts in the water induce vortices analogous to the weather
patterns of the Earth&amp;#8217;s mid-latitudes. We used a camera and projector
to show the results from the rotating point of view. A video of this
demonstration can be found
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G26klqKKCmM"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego 1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/lego_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Lego 2" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/lego_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alex and other members of the DIYnamics team guided students in using
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; Rotating Tank to model &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt; concepts. The students were able to
compare the movement of dye in rotating versus non-rotating bodies of
fluid. Rotating columns are analogous to the movement of molten iron
in the Earth&amp;#8217;s outer&amp;nbsp;core.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group Photo 1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/group_photo_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Group Photo 2" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/group_photo_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Group photos of DIYnamics team members and our host Mr. Stephenson
taken during the May 12th (left) and May 19th (right) trips. It was a
pleasure to work with Mr. Stephenson, and he played a large part in
making the events run as smoothly as possible. This included visiting
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; beforehand to learn about &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt; and how it relates to his&amp;nbsp;curriculum.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry></feed>