<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>DIYnamics - events</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/feeds/events.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://diynamics.github.io/</id><updated>2020-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated><subtitle>Affordable materials for geoscience teaching demonstrations</subtitle><entry><title>DIYnamics at Exploring Your Universe 2020</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/eyu-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-12-21:/blog/eyu-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team presented a diverse range of fluid dynamics experiments you can perform at home as part of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s Exploring Your Universe public science fair &amp;#8212; held virtually for&amp;nbsp;2020.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/eyu-logo.png" width="400" title="Exploring Your Universe" alt="Exploring Your Universe"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 1st, 2020, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Division of Physical Sciences presented its 12th annual &lt;a href="https://www.exploringyouruniverse.org/"&gt;Exploring Your Universe&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;) public outreach event. Every year, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; features dozens of booths for attendees to learn about a diverse range of topics. Amidst the ongoing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19 pandemic, this year&amp;#8217;s public outreach event was held entirely virtually on &lt;a href="https://hopin.com/events/eyu"&gt;hopin.to&lt;/a&gt;. The DIYnamics Team adapted and utilized the opportunity to share the following experiments for learning at&amp;nbsp;home!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why is Antarctica&amp;nbsp;Melting?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dS1W00XW2LM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jordyn created a video, &lt;strong&gt;How do glaciers melt?&lt;/strong&gt;, providing an overview of the fluid dynamics behind the titular process. She described the experimental setup in detail and analyzed experimental results for background into the range of structures observed. Watch to see the interface between density layers and baroclinic&amp;nbsp;eddies!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordyn Moscoso and Ken Zhao presented a talk on how do glaciers melt. Glaciers are massive bodies of frozen fresh water. In locales such as Antarctica, sheets of ice are surrounded by ocean or warm (in a relative sense &amp;#8212; absolute temperatures can dip to 34&amp;deg;F/1&amp;deg;C!) salty water. The temperature difference causes glaciers to melt from the bottom releasing cold fresh water. This loss of mass renders ice sheets unstable and susceptible to calfing or large chunks falling off. Meanwhile, the cold fresh meltwater is less dense than the warm salty ocean water due to differences in salinity. Convection occurs as the cold fresh water rises above the warm salty water and the ocean equilibriates into layers by&amp;nbsp;density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antarctica is a continent the size of the United States and Mexico combined. The fluid dynamics of this vast system can be modeled with a rotating tank platform capturing its key characteristics. Jordyn and Ken performed an experiment featuring a tank of warm salty water (the &amp;#8220;ocean&amp;#8221;) with a cylindrical block of ice (the &amp;#8220;glacier&amp;#8221;) at its center. The tank is spun to account for the fundamental impacts of Earth&amp;#8217;s rotation. In the experiment, we can observe the model&amp;#8217;s glacier melting from its bottom and ocean stratifying per density differences. Food coloring is added to help visualize fluid motions &amp;#8212; the interface between layers is distinct! Eddies or swirling structures form as the system&amp;#8217;s rotation interacts with the fluid body&amp;#8217;s density&amp;nbsp;differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Home Kitchen&amp;nbsp;Experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-1.png" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 1" alt="Air vortex cannon step 1"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-2.png" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 2" alt="Air vortex cannon step 2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-3.png" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 3" alt="Air vortex cannon step 3"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-4.png" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 4" alt="Air vortex cannon step 4"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-5.gif" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 5" alt="Air vortex cannon step 5"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/vortex-ring-6.gif" width="400" title="Air vortex cannon step 6" alt="Air vortex cannon step 6"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to create your own air vortex cannon&lt;br&gt;
Step 1: Gather required materials &amp;#8212; plastic cup, balloon and source of smoke.&lt;br&gt;
Step 2: Cut a circular hole in the bottom of the cup. &lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: Be careful when using a scissor or knife.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Step 3: Cut the neck of the balloon to leave the head remaining.&lt;br&gt;
Step 4: Wrap the head of the balloon over the top of the cup.&lt;br&gt;
Step 5: Fill the inside of the air vortex cannon with smoke. &lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: Be careful when around open flames.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Step 6: Fire the air vortex cannon by pulling back then releasing the balloon.&lt;br&gt;
The goal is to eject a jet of air that pushes through stationary air &amp;#8212; do not release too much air at once else the jet will immediately break apart. The smoke in the air vortex cannon will allow you to visualize structures (including vortex rings) in the air! For best results, fire the air vortex cannon against a dark background for&amp;nbsp;contrast.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yufan Xu and Akash Gupta guided the virtual audience through easy to perform home experiments providing a glimpse into the fluid dynamics all around us! A vortex ring is a torus or donut shaped structure that forms when a jet of fast moving fluid collides with stationary fluid. As the jet pushes through, its edges are slowed by friction and wrap around themselves leading to the formation of a circular ring of circulating fluid. Yufan and Akash demonstrated how to build your own air vortex cannon before firing vortex rings of&amp;nbsp;smoke!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Convection refers to the transfer of heat by motion within a fluid. The transfer of heat occurs wherever fluid bodies feature a temperature gradient &amp;#8212; from a cooling cup of coffee to a sun generating energy by fusion. Convection can be visualized with particles suspended in fluid &amp;#8212; an ideal solution is Barbasoloscope with a recipe by Yufan &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/f9K3FEJkBrs"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Yufan and Akash highlighted convection by warming up miso soup on a stovetop &amp;#8212; the fermented soybean mixture tracked cells of fluid motion as the solution circulated between the pot&amp;#8217;s fire heated bottom and air cooled&amp;nbsp;top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pendulum O&amp;nbsp;Pendulum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/jon-demonstration.png" width="600" title="Jon's demonstration" alt="Jon's demonstration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jon added creamer (dyed pink) to water to demonstrate how waves in different layers oscillate back and forth through the fluid&amp;nbsp;body!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon Aurnou described how pendulums behave both individually and together. Pendulums refer to masses suspended by an arm from a pivot &amp;#8212; the masses swing back and forth about the pivot. Jon created a homemade pendulum by hanging a length of wood from a nail. He demonstrated that if a pendulum is released from a given height, it will swing across its equilibrium point until eventually coming to rest. Per the conservation of energy, with each cycle, the pendulum reaches a height near to but slightly less than its previous iteration. Meanwhile, the period or time required for a pendulum to complete a cycle depends on the length of the arm separating the mass and pivot. Jon compared short and long homemade pendulums to illustrate how given equivalent starting heights, the short pendulums will oscillate much faster. Having established that the behavior of each pendulum is tied to its properties, he tried swinging two different pendulums back and forth about the same pivot. The two pendulums do not behave independently but rather are impacted by each other &amp;#8212; the signals amplify when the pendulums travel together and are muted when the pendulums&amp;nbsp;collide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon shared how pendulum-like conditions also exist in fluid bodies! He created a &amp;#8220;pendulum&amp;#8221; by filling a tank with water &amp;#8212; after allowing the water to rest, to induce swinging, he added a mass of dense creamer with food coloring to one side. A wave of creamer oscillates back and forth through the tank! Different layers of the ocean (see &lt;strong&gt;Why is Antarctica Melting?&lt;/strong&gt;!) can oscillate at different frequencies leading to combined signals that have been amplified and muted. Finding the original frequency of a &amp;#8220;pendulum&amp;#8221; is an important yet challenging task &amp;#8212; a puzzle to&amp;nbsp;solve!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dancing Milk and the Importance of Surface&amp;nbsp;Tension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/grace-demonstration.png" width="600" title="Grace's demonstration" alt="Grace's demonstration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grace dipped a soap covered Q-tip into milk to spread the liquid apart creating vibrant displays of food&amp;nbsp;coloring!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grace Li performed a series of experiments (helping the virtual audience follow along at home!) demonstrating surface tension in action. Surface tension is a property of liquids referring to its surface&amp;#8217;s integrity against dissipation and attributed to forces of attraction between its molecules. Grace illustrated how different liquids have different degrees of surface tension by using a Q-tip to drag liquid droplets across wax paper. Water molecules are strongly cohesive whilst isopropyl alcohol molecules are weakly cohesive &amp;#8212; thus, only water droplets could be successfully dragged. The strong cohesion of water molecules is essential to the natural world &amp;#8212; from water striders walking on water to redwoods bringing water from their roots to&amp;nbsp;branches!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surface tension is disrupted by surfactants such as soap that reduce the forces of attraction between liquid molecules &amp;#8212; surfactants allow a liquid&amp;#8217;s molecules to spread apart. To demonstrate, Grace filled a tank with milk and rested droplets of food coloring on its surface. She dipped a soap covered Q-tip into the milk &amp;#8212; the surfactant caused the food coloring to dissipate leading to stunning patterns of green and&amp;nbsp;blue!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fluid Dynamics +&amp;nbsp;LEGOs!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/norris-demonstration.png" width="600" title="Norris' demonstration" alt="Norris' demonstration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris compared fluid motions in non-rotating versus rotating systems. In non-rotating systems, as pictured above, the food coloring is free to diffuse with no discernable structure. Rotation will impart constraints on the fluid motions of rotating&amp;nbsp;systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norris Khoo utilized the &lt;a href="/pages/lego.html"&gt;Technics Table&lt;/a&gt; to highlight the impact of rotation on a fluid body&amp;#8217;s behavior. The fluid dynamics of Earth&amp;#8217;s atmosphere (air), oceans (water) and interiors (molten iron) are all fundamentally impacted by the planet&amp;#8217;s rotation. To help the virtual audience reason with its effects, Norris presented a comparison of fluid motions in non-rotating and rotating systems &amp;#8212; food coloring is added to visualize fluid motions. The non-rotating system consists of a tank of water. After allowing the system to rest (no fluid motions within within the tank), we observed that the marked water is free to diffuse with no discernable structure. Meanwhile, the rotating system consists of a rotating tank of water &amp;#8212; the Technics Table. After allowing the system to spin up (no fluid motions within the tank as it rotates), we observed that the marked water organizes itself into vertical columns. This occurs because rotation constrains fluid motions to align them with its axis &amp;#8212; this counteracts diffusion. The impact of rotation, the Coriolis force, is a parameter influencing our (and other) planet&amp;#8217;s weather, ocean currents, magnetic field and&amp;nbsp;more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making Your Own Polar&amp;nbsp;Vortex&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2020/taylor-demonstration.png" width="600" title="Taylor's demonstration" alt="Taylor's demonstration"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taylor established a thermal gradient in the rotating system using a frozen can. Due to rotation, the cold water in the center interacts with the warm water to the periphery to create baroclinic eddies. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; Table&amp;#8217;s diameter enables the formation of large&amp;nbsp;structures!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor Lonner utilized the &lt;a href="/pages/ht3.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; Table&lt;/a&gt; to highlight how rotation and turbulence interact in fluid bodies. Turbulence refers to a disruption to the system &amp;#8212; conditions include a thermal gradient or mechanical movement. Taylor performed a series of experiments feature different types of turbulence in a rotating system &amp;#8212; the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; Table. The rotating tank platform&amp;#8217;s meter diameter provided ample room for large and complex structures to form. Meanwhile, thanks to &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; and steps described &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/pdfs/technics/Zoom_Livestreaming_Guide.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, she provided real-time footage for the virtual audience to digest. This kickstarted a rich Q&amp;amp;A as the virtual audience worked with Taylor, Jon and Norris to analyze the stunning display inside the&amp;nbsp;tank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor established a thermal gradient in the rotating system using methods similar to &lt;strong&gt;Why is Antarctica Melting?&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8212; she fixed a frozen can in the middle of the rotating tank of water. The center is cold whilst the periphery is warm &amp;#8212; as the system rotates, dense cold water is pushed outwards whilst light warm water flows inwards to take its place. This leads to the formation of stunning eddies about the frozen can! On Earth, weather in the mid-lattitudes are defined by similar behavior as cold polar air mixed with warm equatorial air. To induce mechanical movement, Taylor rapidly removed the frozen can from the rotating tank of water. Although this can be interpreted as plucking the &amp;#8220;glacier&amp;#8221; out of the &amp;#8220;ocean&amp;#8221;, in general, the removal of the mass creates a vacuum causing water to flow and fill the gap. Constrained by rotation, the turbulence is reorganized into eddies of different shapes and sizes &amp;#8212; fluid motions remain aligned with the axis of rotation. The interaction between rotation and turbulence is responsible for massive storm systems as seen on&amp;nbsp;Jupiter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; was to demonstrate that you can perform your own experiments at home! Experiments are key to learning because models, whilst abstractions of real world systems, provide intuition into the fundamental forces that govern our universe. The process of setting up, performing and analyzing and experiment is an exciting challenge in problem solving and a first hand account proves invaluable. Most of these demonstrations can be performed using household materials to reduce barriers and expand inclusivity in the sciences. Ultimately, understanding the world around us can help audience members (whether in-person or virtual) make informed decisions in their daily lives &amp;#8212; &lt;strong&gt;Why is Antarctica melting?&lt;/strong&gt; highlights the detrimental impact that ocean warming of mere degrees will have on Antarctica. Learn more on our Teaching &lt;a href="/pages/teaching.html"&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; and YouTube &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnUHxOSVY4G4OFbF8XL1qUg"&gt;channel&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; organizers and volunteers, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Division of Physical Sciences and all of the attendees! It was a blast working together to learn from experiments and ponder interesting questions! Thank you to the following individuals &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/dS1W00XW2LM?t=490"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; who supported the &lt;strong&gt;How do glaciers melt&lt;/strong&gt; video. We look forward to next year&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="DIY"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="virtual"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics and Weather in a Tank at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory Open House</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/lamont-open-house-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-02-18:/blog/lamont-open-house-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; table joined forces with the Weather in a Tank in October 2019 to create a powerful one-two punch of demonstrations at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory annual Open House&amp;nbsp;event.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/lamont-open-house-2019/lamont-open-house-2019_1.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Attendees of the Lamont Open House check out the baroclinic instability demonstration up close.  Lamont volunteer Jeff Strong added green dye in addition to the standard red and blue, which adds a nice extra touch of&amp;nbsp;color.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 5, 2019, DIYnamics made its debut at the annual &lt;a href="https://openhouse.ldeo.columbia.edu/"&gt;Open House&lt;/a&gt; event held by the &lt;a href="https://www.ldeo.columbia.edu/"&gt;Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory&lt;/a&gt;, or just &amp;#8220;Lamont&amp;#8221; for short.  Lamont is the home of nearly all of the Earth Sciences conducted at &lt;a href="https://www.columbia.edu/"&gt;Columbia University&lt;/a&gt; in New York and is where Spencer currently works as a postdoctoral research scientist.  Lamont Open House is a giant public science fair event, featuring hundreds of cool demonstrations of Lamont science including a &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/Lamont.Doherty/videos/497661050966596/"&gt;trash can volcano&lt;/a&gt; and, of course, rotating tank&amp;nbsp;demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this event, Spencer introduced to Lamont the DIYnamics &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; table, which we paired with the &lt;a href="http://weathertank.mit.edu/"&gt;Weather in a Tank&lt;/a&gt; platform that Lamont already had on hand to create a very nice one-two punch of demonstrations: attendees could learn the very basics of rotating vs. non-rotating fluids from the ultra simple and approachable &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; tables, and then they could just go a few feet away to the Weather in a Tank setup where Open House volunteer Jeff Strong taught them about the polar vortex and other cool features of Earth&amp;#8217;s oceans and atmosphere via more involved&amp;nbsp;demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/lamont-open-house-2019/lamont-open-house-2019_2.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The DIYnamics table before the event kicked in to high gear.  Just out of the frame to the right was the Weather in a Tank booth led by Jeff Strong.  With only Spencer at the DIYnamics booth, and only Jeff at the Weather in a Tank booth, we didn&amp;#8217;t manage to get a picture of the DIYnamics booth in action!  Which is a good reminder: running a table with one person is possible, but especially for longer events it&amp;#8217;s much better to have multiple&amp;nbsp;volunteers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff made excellent use of technology in his demonstrations.  The Weather in a Tank platform includes a camera mounted in the rotating frame, which he fed to a projector that beamed the footage onto a screen behind him.  Meanwhile, Jeff showed animations on an iPad of real-life weather over the north pole, showing attendees just how similar the real-world patterns look like our simple rotating tank&amp;nbsp;setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/lamont-open-house-2019/lamont-open-house-2019_3.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jeff using technology to help make the connection between the behavior in the tanks and the real world.  The Weather in a Tank setup includes a mounted camera in the rotating frame, which was connected to a project and shown on the screen here, with the effective &amp;#8220;North Pole&amp;#8221; labeled.  Meanwhile, Jeff used an iPad to show animations of real-life weather patterns over the real-life North Pole.  Even from just this stillshot image you can see how similar the two&amp;nbsp;look!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One lesson we learned from this event was that, although having one person per table can work, it&amp;#8217;s much better to have two or more.  With only Spencer at the DIYnamics table, there was a lot of down time in between demos while Spencer emptied out the tanks, refilled them, got them spinning again, etc., not to mention during a break for lunch.  And likewise for Jeff at the Weather in a Tank exhibit.  If we had an extra hand or two at each table, we could have had demos running more or less nonstop throughout the&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great event, and we thank all of the attendees for their enthusiasm as well as everyone at Lamont and Columbia more broadly who helped make it happen.  We&amp;#8217;re already looking forward to Open House&amp;nbsp;2020!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-12"></category><category term="weather in a tank"></category></entry><entry><title>Society of Women Geoscientists and Project Scientist teach K-12 girls planetary fluid dynamics with a record player</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/ucla-swg-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jordyn Moscoso</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-02-07:/blog/ucla-swg-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jordyn introduces us to the Society of Women Geoscientists organization at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; and how they partnered with Project Scientist to teach K-12 girls about planetary fluid motions using a record&amp;nbsp;player.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ucla-swg-2019/ucla-swg-2019_1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ashna (left) demonstrates how rotation affects the shape of the
surface of the water in the tank, and shows how the patterns of dye a
tank develops in contrast to a tank that is not&amp;nbsp;rotating.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics made a debut in a partnership with the Society of Women
Geoscientists (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWG&lt;/span&gt;) and &lt;a href="https://projectscientist.org/"&gt;Project
Scientist&lt;/a&gt; on November 11th, 2019, at
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWG&lt;/span&gt; is a group at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; formed to support women and other
underrepresented genders in the geosciences.  Members and allies in
the group come from the Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt;)
department, the Earth, Planetary, and Space Sciences (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPSS&lt;/span&gt;)
department, the Institute of the Environment and Sustainability
(IoES), and the Geology department.  Project Scientist is a community
of girls and women excited about science.  Their mission is to expose
a diverse population of girls to high quality &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; academy that
inspires confidence in their persuit of learning throughout the&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partnered with the SPINLab, Ashna and Jewel used common household
goods, like a record player to demonstrate how the fluids on the Earth
and other planets behave in the presence of&amp;nbsp;rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ucla-swg-2019/ucla-swg-2019_2.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some volunteers from the Society of Women Geoscientists (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWG&lt;/span&gt;) with
the girls from Project Scientist. The girls joined us for experiences
in SPINLab &amp;#8212;- where DIYnamics was born &amp;#8212;- ranging from understanding
how rotation changes how fluid flows the to seeing how ozone is formed
in the atmosphere, to coding eddies and vortices moving around in a
channel.  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWG&lt;/span&gt; was happy to support and meet our future&amp;nbsp;colleagues!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The future scientists who visited &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; were between the ages of 4 and
12, and we were so impressed by their questions about how the earth
works, and their ideas for more experiments that we can run using
these rotating tanks!  We hope to expand our demonstrations next year
to include building the DIYnamics kits and run more hands on
experiments with Project Scientist next&amp;nbsp;year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-12"></category><category term="record player"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics at UCLA Exploring Your Universe 2019</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/eyu-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jordyn Moscoso</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-01-31:/blog/eyu-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For a 3rd consecutive year, DIYnamics participated in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s massive public science fair called Exploring Your Universe, with core team members and volunteers leading demonstrations for hundreds of&amp;nbsp;attendees.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: we&amp;#8217;re thrilled to have this first post from one
of our newest DIYnamics core team members, Jordyn Moscoso!  Another
post formally introducing her and some other new faces will be coming
soon.  And you can blame me for the lack of posts generally over the
past couple months&amp;#8230;plenty of great posts from Jordyn and others are
in the queue!  -S.&amp;nbsp;Hill]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2019/eyu-2019_1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris, Carlyn, and Oliver hard at work at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;!  Norris demonstrated
how to build the DIYnamics kits, Carlyn demonstrated how baroclinic
instability creates eddies that transfer heat around the tank, and
Oliver used a record player to show how centrifugal instability
pushes chia seeds outward once rotation is turned&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in November, the DIYnamics team returned to Exploring Your
Universe (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;) at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; is the largest outreach event for the
Division of Physical Sciences every year, and it involves nearly every
department.  This year the DIYnamics tent included core team member
Norris and our newest core team member Jordyn, as well as help from
two volunteers, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; graduate student Francisco Spaulding-Astudillo,
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; undergraduate student Carlyn Schmidgell, and Oliver from the
Geffen&amp;nbsp;Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year there were four different sections at the booth all showing
different aspects of Do-It-Yourself&amp;nbsp;dynamics!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Norris demonstrated how to build the DIYnamics motor using legos
   and showed the difference between a rotating and non-rotating tank.
   This experiment shows how the effect of rotation works to organize
   flow into&amp;nbsp;eddies!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carlyn showed how we use the DIYnamics setup to demonstrate how
   eddies exchange heat around the tank.  This demonstration was built
   to show how eddies move warm water and air from low latitudes to
   high latitudes, like for example to the margins of&amp;nbsp;Antarctica.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oliver showed centrifugal instability.  This instability occurs
   when fluid spins very quickly, pushing all of the fluid outward
   toward the edges of the&amp;nbsp;tank.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jordyn (that&amp;#8217;s me) demonstrated 2D turbulence using the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt;
   rotating&amp;nbsp;tank.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not all of the setups you see here are built using Legos, the
purpose of DIYnamics is to show that household objects (like a record
player) can be used to simulate the dynamics and flows on&amp;nbsp;planets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2019/eyu-2019_2.jpg" width="600"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2019/eyu-2019_3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jordyn is showing how the effect of rotation works to create vortices
in the flow when a fluid is rotating.  When a little energy is added,
or the fluid is disturbed by running a pen through the flow, the blobs
of dye stretch and move and organize into coherent&amp;nbsp;vortices!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge thank you to all of our volunteers, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Departments of
Earth, Planetary and Space Sciences and of Atmospheric and Oceanic
Sciences, the Society of Women Geoscientists, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; organizers, and
good old Jon Aurnou and the rest of the SPINLab for help!  And an
equally huge thank you to all of the wonderful kids and parents who
visited our booth.  See you all in the fall for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;2020!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>Vortices on our LEGO table and “The Whale2” table at Roscomare Elementary and David Geffen Academy</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/geffen-roscomare-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jon Aurnou</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-09-16:/blog/geffen-roscomare-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Core DIYnamicist Jon Aurnou shares how he and his group members taught K-8 students about vortices, including the polar vortex, using the standard &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-based DIYnamics table and the large-and-in-charge Whale&amp;nbsp;Table.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/821B56GS7zE'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Swirling polar flows reach down to lower latitudes in our
demonstration made on the 1 meter diameter Whale&amp;nbsp;Table.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Making Crazy Vortices at Roscomare Elementary&amp;nbsp;School&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prof. Aurnou took two DIYnamics Lego Tables to Career Day at Roscomare
Elementary School on April 12, 2019.  After discussing what makes
planets and their atmospheres so interesting in the classroom (How
about jets &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; vortices!), the entire class ventured outside and did
experiments on how food coloring moves around differently in standing
tanks of water compared to rotating ones.  We discussed what aspects
of the different flow patterns looks more or less like what we see in
planetary atmospheres.  Lastly, one student dumped A &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOT&lt;/span&gt; of green food
coloring into one tank and pointed out that there wasn’t anything to
see anymore.  Which is really an important experiment to carry&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/geffen-roscomare-2019/geffen-roscomare-2019-1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students at Roscomare ask Jon questions about fluid flows.  Although
one of them, Ethan (standing), has heard this stuff before&amp;#8230;Jon is
his&amp;nbsp;dad!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Attack of the Polar Vortex!!! at David Geffen&amp;nbsp;Academy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 27, 2019, members of the &lt;a href="http://spinlab.epss.ucla.edu/"&gt;SpinLab
group&lt;/a&gt; —&amp;#8212; Jewel Abbate, Jon Aurnou, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AJ&lt;/span&gt;
Chlarson, Henry Gonzalez, Emily Hawkins, Taylor Lonner and Yufan Xu
&amp;#8212;- figured out how to transport one Lego Table (easy) and our new 40&amp;#8221;
diameter prototype table, code-named Whale2 (not as easy!), over to
the Geffen Academy on the southern tip of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;’s campus.  The next
day, Prof. Aurnou lead three 50-minute classes with essential pit crew
support from Jewel, Emily, Henry and Yufan.  This demo-based
presentation, entitled “Attack of the Polar Vortex!!!”, was given to a
mix of 6th - 8th graders as part of Geffen Academy’s 2019 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Day.
After 5 minutes of slides showing how wintertime polar flows can reach
down and visit the mid-latitudes, the class ran a set of experiments
on the Lego Table to watch how a patch of dense creamer in a rotating
tank of water become unstable, and shreds itself into smaller&amp;nbsp;structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/geffen-roscomare-2019/geffen-roscomare-2019-3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jon with two happy students.  Once again, Ethan Aurnou, this time
with his sister Abby.  Pretty cool to learn science through fun
demonstrations &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AND&lt;/span&gt; have your dad visit you at&amp;nbsp;school!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then a related experiment was carried out on The Whale2, filled
with about 5 cm of water and rotating at about 8 revolutions per
minute.  Here a frozen ice-filled paint can was placed at the center
of the tank to generate cold, dense polar “air masses” which we
demarcated with blue food coloring.  We marked the warmer water near
the outside of the tank with red food coloring, and then sat back and
watched our simulated polar vortex become unstable and “attack”
Chicago and the like.  The students asked many excellent questions and
made a number of observations.  For instance, it was noted that the
processes on the smaller Lego Table appeared to mimic those on the
much larger Whale, and that this suggested that the processes we see
in our demonstrations might then scale up to larger systems like the
atmosphere.  Yes (!), that is exactly the&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="polar-vortex"></category><category term="whale2"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics at SoCal Fluids 2019</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/socal-fluids-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-04-20:/blog/socal-fluids-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team shared their outreach resources with other Southern California fluid dynamicists at SoCal Fluids&amp;nbsp;2019&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/socal-fluids-2019/poster.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 20, 2019, Norris and other members of the SPINLab visited sunny Santa Barbara to present
at the thirteenth annual &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/view/socalfluids2019/home"&gt;SoCal Fluids&lt;/a&gt; student
symposium. Graduate students from throughout Southern California met to share their research in
diverse fields of fluid dynamics. For his presentation, Norris took the opportunity to describe the
utility of the DIYnamics table for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; education. We believe that physical models provide a
tangible connection to the large scale processes impacting our atmosphere and oceans, helping
students develop a scientific approach to the&amp;nbsp;world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/socal-fluids-2019/baroclinic-instability.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overhead view of baroclinic instability in action. Look at the eddies towards the top and bottom right of the&amp;nbsp;image!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norris provided an overview of his favorite experiment, baroclinic instability (please watch our
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/2tIVOK9wjI4"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; for a more detailed guide). Begin the experiment by placing
a frozen can in the middle of a rotating tank of warm water. The cold source and warm body,
analogous to the Earth&amp;#8217;s poles and lower latitudes respectively, create a temperature gradient.
The blue water, chilled by the cold source, is dense and pushed out as the tank rotates. Meanwhile,
the red water, heated by the warm body, migrates to the center to fill the void. This process
continues and results in the formation of large circular structures or eddies. Baroclinic
instability defines much of the large scale behavior of Earth&amp;#8217;s atmosphere in the northern&amp;nbsp;hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/socal-fluids-2019/beach.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A visit to the beach after the&amp;nbsp;symposium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to the SoCal Fluids 2019 organizers for providing the opportunity to share our project!
And thank you to other participants for their interesting presentations and valuable insight
regarding improvements for our&amp;nbsp;material!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="symposium"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="presentation"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics at the AGU Fall 2018 meeting</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/agu-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-12-13:/blog/agu-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team shared their efforts to promote geoscience education at the Fall 2018 meeting of the American Geophysical&amp;nbsp;Union.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/agu-2018/agu-2018-tuesday-wide.png" width="600" title="Experiments with the DIYnamics table" alt="Experiments with the DIYnamics table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris describing experiments possible using the DIYnamics table and
their relevance to the behavior of planetary fluid bodies. Over the
course of two poster sessions, we had the opportunity to share our
educational tools with dozens of conference attendees from diverse&amp;nbsp;backgrounds.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 11 and 13, 2018, the DIYnamics team presented at the Fall
2018 meeting of the &lt;a href="https://sites.agu.org/"&gt;American Geophysical Union&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt;). &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt;, currently
celebrating its 100th anniversary, annually holds the largest
geoscience conference in the world. Norris, Spencer and Jon had a great
experience spreading the word about DIYnamics and listening to feedback
from members of the geoscience community - including some who are
already using our&amp;nbsp;materials!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/agu-2018/agu-2018-tuesday-narrow.png" width="600" title="Models can be made using household items" alt="Models can be made using household items"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris sharing the household items necessary to create your own
geophysical fluid dynamics model. The goal of DIYnamics is to promote
geoscience education by making physical models, a useful tool for
studying large scale real world phenomena, as accessible as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt; provided a unique opportunity to share DIYnamics with individuals
from institutions around the world. During our poster sessions, we
prepared demonstrations centered around the DIYnamics table - a fun
logistical challenge 2,500+ miles away from home! We showed how
physical models of planetary fluid bodies can be constructed using 
household items, whether they be LEGOs + a lazy susan for our rotating
table or a frozen can for our cold source. These accessible tools
allow audiences at all levels to observe the fluid dynamics behind
weather, ocean circulation and more providing tremendous educational&amp;nbsp;benefit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/agu-2018/agu-2018-thursday.png" width="600" title="Poster detailing the DIYnamics project" alt="Poster detailing the DIYnamics project"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris with his jerry rigged DIYnamics table setup. Experiments can
be conducted with readily available resources and the number of 
&amp;#8220;recipes&amp;#8221; continues to&amp;nbsp;grow.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the conference, we conducted experiments highlighting solid body
rotation, mechanically generated vortices and baroclinic instability.
For the big picture, we hope that our physical models help individuals
think analytically when approaching real world phenomena. Models are
integral to science because they simplify and facilitate the study of
complex&amp;nbsp;systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/agu-2018/agu-2018-barbasol.png" width="600" title="Close up image of rotating convection in rheoscopic fluid" alt="Close up image of rotating convection in rheoscopic fluid"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After placing rheoscopic fluid in a rotating tank, we observed an
interesting pattern of spirals arranged in concentric circles. This
can be attributed to rotating convection, prompted by differences in
temperature at the top and bottom of the fluid body, resulting in the
formation of columnar structures (spirals are their surface manifestation).
The concentric circle arrangement occurs because the bottom of the
tank features similar&amp;nbsp;ridges.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team was amazed by &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5045053"&gt;Borrero-Echeverry et al. (2018)&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;#8220;do-it-yourself&amp;#8221; rheoscopic fluid made using Barbasol shaving cream.
Rheoscopic fluid contains small particles suspended in water and
allows audiences to track the flow of fluid. At &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt;, we greatly
enjoyed talking with individuals who share our passion for outreach
and hearing stories of the DIYnamics table in use! As more people
adopt our system, we are excited to see what experiments the
community has in&amp;nbsp;store!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGU&lt;/span&gt; for providing a platform to share DIYnamics, the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPSS&lt;/span&gt; Strauss Family Fund for Undergraduate Opportunity for supporting
Norris&amp;#8217; first conference visit and last but not least, the conference
attendees who came to our poster and provided their valuable&amp;nbsp;feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="conference"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="education"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics at UCLA Exploring Your Universe 2018</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/eyu-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-11-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-11-04:/blog/eyu-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics returned to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s annual Exploring Your Universe science fair with our Lego-based platforms and larger square&amp;nbsp;tank.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2018/eyu-2018-norris-legos.jpg" width="600" title="Norris helping visitors build their own motors" alt="Norris helping visitors build their own motors"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris helps visitors at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; build their very own DIYnamics motors.
Over the course of the roughly 5 hour event, dozens of kids
successfully built their own, usually with very little help from us&amp;nbsp;required.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 4, 2018, the DIYnamics team made a triumphant return to
the &lt;a href="https://www.exploringyouruniverse.org/"&gt;Exploring Your Universe&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;) science fair held every fall at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;.  Old-timers Spencer and
Norris and newcomers Calvin and Santiago had a blast spending the day
helping kids and their families learn about rotating fluids using the
DIYnamics&amp;nbsp;materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2018/eyu-2018-calvin-top.jpg" width="600" title="Calvin using a spinning top to teach about rotation" alt="Calvin using a spinning top to teach about rotation"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Calvin using a spinning top to help these &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; visitors get a more
intuitive feel for why rotation effects fluids like water and air.
Just like a top stays upright if its spinning but falls over if it&amp;#8217;s
stationary, motions within rotating fluids get aligned with the
rotation axis, while non-rotating fluids move in all&amp;nbsp;directions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like our inaugural appearance at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; in 2017, we had three different
sections of our booth, all of them going&amp;nbsp;simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build your own DIYnamics motor: Using the DIYnamics official
   printed instructions, visitors got to assemble their own DIYnamics
   motors.  Norris kept watch and helped out when necessary, but
   mostly kids were able to build them start-to-finish on their&amp;nbsp;own!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rotating vs. non-rotating tanks: Calvin and Santiago led our
   classic demonstration comparing how dye behaves when dropped into a
   rotating tank vs. a non-rotating one.  They also made great use of
   spinning tops to illustrate how rotation makes things (including
   fluids) stand up&amp;nbsp;straight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Winter storms using the big square tank: Once every hour, Spencer
   performed the demonstration of &amp;#8220;baroclinic instability&amp;#8221; using a
   bigger tank &amp;#8212;- the same one that we used to create our
   &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/5bnmaYOFerk"&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/b4f0plA3_Bg"&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; on the same topic.  With a
   paint can filled with ice in the middle, water gets cooled in the
   middle of the tank compared to the outer edges.  This temperature
   contrast combined with rotation gives rise to beautiful swirling
   eddies that act to transfer heat from the warm section to the cold
   section&amp;#8230;just like the big winter storms in Earth&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;atmosphere!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2018/eyu-2018-booth.jpg" width="600" title="Santiago and Calvin manning our booth" alt="Santiago and Calvin manning our booth"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Calvin and Santiago (both facing toward the camera; Santiago on the
right) manning the DIYnamics booth.  Calvin and Santiago were
first-time DIYnamics volunteers, and they did an amazing job!
Especially given that we didn&amp;#8217;t have as many people this year (only 4
total).  Thanks&amp;nbsp;guys!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; also marked the debut of our amazing new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-based DIYnamics logo
(image below).  How cool is&amp;nbsp;that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2018/lego-diynamics-logo.jpg" width="600" title="Our awesome new LEGO-based logo" alt="Our awesome new LEGO-based logo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our awesome new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-based DIYnamics logo.  We&amp;#8217;re definitely going to
start using this on the website and everywhere else we can!  Thanks to
Jon Aurnou for the idea, and Norris for actually building&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge thanks to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; organizers and volunteers, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;
Department of Earth, Planetary, and Space Sciences staff who helped us
setup, Jon Aurnou and the rest of the SPINLab for help (and including
us in their pizza order!), and of course to the wonderful kids and
parents who came to our booth.  See you in 2019 for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; Round&amp;nbsp;3!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>El Marino Language School Science Fair</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/el-marino-science-fair.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-04-27:/blog/el-marino-science-fair.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team taught basics of rotating fluids using our beloved tables, frozen cans of tomato paste, inflatable globes, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Batmen at a really cool science&amp;nbsp;fair.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-sean.jpg" width="600" title="Sean leading a demo" alt="Sean leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean leads a demonstration of &amp;#8220;baroclinic instability&amp;#8221; (a.k.a. the
combination of a strong temperature contrast and rotation that
generates storms on Earth) to El Marino students and parents.  They&amp;#8217;re
so focused!  We&amp;#8217;re now using a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Power Functions remote control to
reduce the rotation rate for this demonstration, which makes these
eddies larger and therefore more engaging.  Even with the bigger
eddies, we were also able to shrink the tank compared to previous
attempts, which allows for a little more breathing&amp;nbsp;room.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 27, 2018, Ashna, Sean, and Spencer of the DIYnamics team
performed hands-on demonstrations for dozens of kids at the 23rd
annual science fair of the &lt;a href="https://elmarino.ccusd.org/"&gt;El Marino Language
School&lt;/a&gt;, a foreign language-focused
elementary school in the Culver City Unified School District, in
Culver City, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;.  In a cool twist on the traditional elementary
school-level science fair, El Marino&amp;#8217;s fair featured science posters
and demonstrations both from their own students and from multiple
science groups at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;.  So the students got to show off their awesome
science and simultaneously learn about the just-as-awesome science
conducted at the university level.  And they even fed us dinner!
Naturally, this was an event that DIYnamics wasn&amp;#8217;t going to&amp;nbsp;miss!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-ashna.jpg" width="600" title="Ashna leading a demo" alt="Ashna leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our newest DIYnamicist, Ashna, with two excited young El Marino
students eager to drop dye into our tanks.  But before they do so,
Ashna makes sure that they make a hypothesis about what they will see
in each tank.  Then, once the dye has been injected, she asks them to
describe what they are seeing, to decide if their hypothesis was
right, and then ultimately link the results back to the underlying
science we&amp;#8217;re trying to teach.  This gets participants engaged in
active learning throughout the&amp;nbsp;demonstration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We came equipped with a handful of our DIYnamics rotating table
platforms, our handy globe, and some &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Batman figurines to teach
the students and parents who came by about how Earth&amp;#8217;s rotation and
temperature contrasts combine to generate the weather patterns that we
know and (sometimes)&amp;nbsp;love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-spencer-sean.jpg" width="600" title="Spencer and Sean leading a demo" alt="Spencer and Sean leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spencer using an inflatable globe with a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; figurine (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Batman,
to be specific) taped onto the north pole to make the connection with
students between the real world and the tanks on the table.  The
DIYnamics table farthest back in this image has another &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Batman
taped at its center, sitting on top of a polar stereographic map
(a.k.a. a map centered on the North Pole).  Spencer spins the globe
showing that Batman spins with it, and at the same time Sean spins the
table showing that Batman spins the exact same way there!  We&amp;#8217;ve found
this really helps students make the otherwise difficult connection
between tanks of water and the real&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parents were a great bunch too!  One father told us that he is a
pilot, and that our explanation of weather systems using the DIYnamics
was the best one he&amp;#8217;s ever heard!  Pilots really need to know the
weather to fy safely, so that&amp;#8217;s no small compliment (if we may say&amp;nbsp;so).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/el-marino-2018/el-marino-bci-closeup.jpg" width="600" title="El Marino students getting a closeup look at baroclinic instability" alt="El Marino students getting a closeup look at baroclinic instability"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;El Marino students eagerly awaiting the onset of &amp;#8220;storms&amp;#8221; driven by
the frozen can of tomato paste in the center of the table.  Initially,
all of the blue dye was injected next to the can and all of the red
dye outside of it.  But you can see that the blue dye has moved
outward in places, while the red dye has moved in toward the can.
(Don&amp;#8217;t be alarmed by the red patch on the hand pointing down at the
tank&amp;#8230;one downside of using red dye is that when it gets on hand it
looks like blood!  No DIYnamicists (or students or parents) were
harmed in the making of this&amp;nbsp;demonstration.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Erika M. von Euw of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; and the El Marino Language
School &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PTA&lt;/span&gt; for organizing, the many student and parent volunteers at
the event, and most of all the great kids and parents who came to our
table.  We&amp;#8217;re crossing our fingers that we get a repeat invitation for
next year&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;fair!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>UCLA Exploring Your Universe (EYU) 2017</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/eyu-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-11-05:/blog/eyu-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team ran a booth at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s massive public science fair &amp;#8220;Exploring Your Universe,&amp;#8221; featuring demonstrations and kids building their own DIYnamics&amp;nbsp;tables.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_sean.jpg" width="600" title="Sean leading a demo" alt="Sean leading a demo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean leading a demonstration using DIYnamics tables.  The farther
table has a special acryllic sidewall that enables us to fill the
whole table with water.  The nearer one uses a plastic planter tray
that costs a few dollars to achieve nearly the same&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 5, 2017, the DIYnamics team performed hands-on
demonstrations for hundreds of kids at the annual &lt;a href="https://www.exploringyouruniverse.org/"&gt;Exploring Your
Universe&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;) event at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; is basically a massive science fair, with groups from nearly every
science department at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;, from astronomers to biochemists,
performing demonstrations to teach kids (and their parents!) about
their science.  Of course, DIYnamics had a booth where we had kids
build our tables, use them to learn about rotating fluids, and also
give more in-depth demonstrations using our larger, custom square
tank.  We had a blast showing off our equipment and teaching science
to hundreds of people in total over the course of the&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_norris.jpg" width="600" title="Norris helping kids build their own tables" alt="Norris helping kids build their own tables"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norris helping out as several kids (and an adult!) build their own
motors for the DIYnamics table.  His table was swamped all day; kids
really loved building these!  Who doesn&amp;#8217;t love building with&amp;nbsp;LEGOs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One highlight of the day was our newest activity, wherein kids got to
create the DIYnamics rotating tank kit themselves!  We provided all of
the needed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; parts, along with printouts of our official
instructions of how to assemble the motor.  Dozens of kids went
step-by-step through the instructions, creating the finished product
in just a few minutes every time.  We provided a little guidance here
and there, but mostly they were able to do it all on their&amp;nbsp;own!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever somebody finished building their motor, we would then use it
to drive a table in a science demonstration.  The kids loved to hear
us announce their name and to see their creation used to perform a
real-world science experiment.  Overall, this affirmed our belief that
our kit really is easy to build and use, and that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; aspect of
the apparatus adds to the connection students make with the science &amp;#8212;
if we can learn about something using LEGOs and food coloring, how
hard can it really&amp;nbsp;be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_juan.jpg" width="600" title="Juan leading a demonstration at EYU" alt="Juan leading a demonstration at EYU"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan demonstrating baroclinic instability using our large square
tank, along with a GoPro in the rotating frame that streams footage to
his iPad.  Look at all those excited&amp;nbsp;faces!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight was demonstrating baroclinic instability in our
larger square tank.  By putting a bucket of ice in the center, we
created baroclinic eddies and added some &amp;#8220;Hollywood magic&amp;#8221; via a GoPro
mounted in the rotating frame.  The rotating frame footage was
streamed directly to an iPad, rather than to an iPhone + projector as
we had in the past.  As usual, this was a crowd&amp;nbsp;favorite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/eyu-2017/eyu2017_baroclinic.jpg" width="600" title="Baroclinic instability on the DIYnamics table generated at EYU" alt="Baroclinic instability on the DIYnamics table generated at EYU"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Baroclinic instability generated on the DIYnamics table using a
frozen can of tomato paste as the cold source at the center.  We were
happily shocked when this worked first try, all while we were getting
setup for the rest of the event!  Huge thanks to Henry Gonzalez for
making the acryllic sidewall that enabled the fluid to span the
table&amp;#8217;s full&amp;nbsp;width.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in addition to the baroclinic instability demonstration on
the big tank, we managed to get it working for the first time on the
smaller DIYnamics table!  These eddies need a sufficiently large tank
in order to grow (specifically, the tank radius must be appreciably
larger than the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rossby_radius_of_deformation"&gt;&amp;#8220;Rossby radius of
deformation&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;,
which determines the size of the eddies), and that extra space was
enabled by an acryllic sidewall that Jon installed on one of the
tables with the help of Henry Gonzalez of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Dept. of Earth,
Planetary, and Space Sciences.  Instead of a paint bucket filled with
ice, we used a frozen can of tomato paste, which also allowed for more
room for the eddies to grow.  We&amp;#8217;re really excited to try this one
again and ultimately create a lesson plan and videos for&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to returning volunteer Chloe Wicker, first time
volunteer Tersi Arias-Young, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt; organizers, and most of all the
great kids and parents who came to our booth.  We&amp;#8217;re already looking
forward to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EYU&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;2018!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="public"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics + a record player at the Sierra Nevada Aquatic Research Laboratory</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/snarl-event.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-06-13:/blog/snarl-event.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamicist Jon Aurnou led demonstrations using the DIYnamics table and a record player&amp;#8230;and even got written up in the local&amp;nbsp;newspaper!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On June 13, DIYnamics&amp;#8217; own Prof. Jon Aurnou led an outreach event
featuring our Lego-based rotating tanks at the Sierra Nevada Aquatic
Research Laboratory
(&lt;a href="http://www.ucnrs.org/reserves/sierra-nevada-aquatic-research-laboratory.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SNARL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).
Jon gave a public lecture on his research on Jupiter&amp;#8217;s jets and
performed demonstrations for before and after the lecture.  The event
was even written up in a full-page article in the community&amp;#8217;s local
newspaper, &lt;em&gt;The Sheet&lt;/em&gt;.  Checkout a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/pdfs/aurnou_event_article_2017-06.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;; DIYnamics
is featured at the top of page 1 and all of page&amp;nbsp;23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon utilized a feature of the DIYnamics table that we hadn&amp;#8217;t in our
prior events: pouring water directly into the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OXO&lt;/span&gt; lazy susan, rather
than into a container sitting on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OXO&lt;/span&gt;.  This utilizes the full 16&amp;#8221;
diameter surface, although because the rim is only around 1/2&amp;#8221; tall,
only a shallow layer can be attained.  But this is more like Earth&amp;#8217;s
atmosphere or ocean anyways!  In fact, the true aspect ratio (i.e. the
ratio of how wide they are to how tall they are) of either of these is
even larger &amp;#8212; not far from that of a single piece of&amp;nbsp;paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/snarl/jon-oxo.jpg" width="600" title="Jon using the DIYnamics table" alt="Jon using the DIYnamics table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jon using the DIYnamics Table to teach kids and adults about rotating
fluids.  Photo credit: Abagael&amp;nbsp;Giles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon complemented the demonstrations performed on the DIYnamics table
with others using a turntable (i.e. what you use to play vinyl records
or be a legit &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt;).  Turntables are another great tool for these
demonstrations.  Like the DIYnamics table, they are portable and
inexpensive compared to custom built tanks primarily used at
universities.  And unlike the DIYnamics table (at least for now), many
have a lever that enables varying the rotation rate by up to +/-10%,
which is needed for e.g. demonstrating &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor_column"&gt;Taylor
columns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(One snag with using record players is the center nub that keeps vinyl
records centered as they spin.  A notch has to be machined out of the
bottom of your tank, or the tank has to be sitting on something like a
platform with&amp;nbsp;legs.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole event was a major success in Jon&amp;#8217;s eyes, as the crowd seemed
really interested in the hands-on demonstrations.  &amp;#8220;Kids loved getting
to operate the table themselves. They kept playing with it until it
got dark outside,&amp;#8221; Jon said.  &amp;#8220;And they made a complete mess and asked
a lot of questions -– a great sign that they had fun and learned&amp;nbsp;something.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/snarl/jon-record-player.jpg" width="600" title="Jon using a record player" alt="Jon using a record player"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prof. Aurnou using a turntable (a.k.a. a record player) at the same
event.  Turntables are another great way to demonstrate the behavior
of rotating fluids.  Photo credit: Abagael&amp;nbsp;Giles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="public"></category><category term="record player"></category><category term="press"></category></entry><entry><title>Ralph Bunche Middle School Event</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/ralph-bunche-event.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-22T16:16:01-06:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T16:16:01-06:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-05-22:/blog/ralph-bunche-event.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team brought their rotating tables to the 7th grade science class at Ralph J. Bunche Middle School in Compton, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On May 22nd, 2017, we visited Ralph Bunche Middle School in Compton,
California. Similarly to our La Tijera K-8 School events, we first
introduced students to the field of geophysical fluid dynamics
(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;). We sought to teach students about the importance of models in
studying science and, to this end, we showed how our assortment of
rotating tanks can be used to illustrate aspects of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;. Both the
group experiments and individual &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; Rotating Tank experiments went&amp;nbsp;great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lecture" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/sean-slide-show.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean provides a lecture on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt; and the use of models in studying
science. Lecture slides can be found
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ClYEmFAEATzG2iHZ8uqD2pzgEYSqbrYZD0xDRfuADzk/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="LEGO Table" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/katie-students.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Rotating Column" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/small-table-solid-body.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Katie and other members of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; Rotating Tank team demonstrate how
rotating tanks are a simple yet effective tool for studying &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;. Among
other experiments, students created a vertical column and learned how
it mirrors the interior of rotating&amp;nbsp;planets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="White Whale 1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/white_whale_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="White Whale 2" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/white_whale_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan provides a demonstration of the mechanical creation of
vortices, a.k.a. the swirling patterns in the dye. When students dip
their hands into the large rotating tank, the physical disturbance
results in turbluence. Other sources of turbluence like the movement
of heat can also generate&amp;nbsp;vortices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Square Table" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ralph-bunche/square-tank.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan shows how an uneven temperature distribution can influence
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;. An ice bucket at the center of the tank and rotation result in
the formation of vortices. This behavior reflects the weather patterns
of the Earth&amp;#8217;s middle latitudes. A video of this demonstration is
available &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G26klqKKCmM"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category></entry><entry><title>La Tijera K-8 School Event</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/la-tijera-events.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2017-05-19:/blog/la-tijera-events.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics team brought rotating tables large and small to La Tijera K-8 Charter School in Inglewood, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;, to teach basics Earth&amp;#8217;s atmospheric and oceanic&amp;nbsp;motions.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On May 12th and May 19th, 2017, we visited La Tijera K-8 School in
Inglewood, California. We introduced seventh and eighth grade students
to the study of geophysical fluid dynamics (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;) and how this pertains
to our everyday lives. Like many other areas of science, studying &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt;
involves the extensive use of scientific models and, to this end, we
brought a range of rotating tables to showcase key concepts. Everyone
had a lot of fun during group demonstrations and individual
experiments involving the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; Rotating Tank. At the end, we talked
with students about how they can pursue careers in&amp;nbsp;science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Model" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/globe-table.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Gyroscope" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/gyroscope.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sean and Spencer discuss how &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt; can be studied using smaller scale
models. Lecture slides can be found
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ClYEmFAEATzG2iHZ8uqD2pzgEYSqbrYZD0xDRfuADzk/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="White Whale 1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/white_whale_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="White Whale 2" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/white_whale_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan demonstrates the creation of vortices using our large rotating
tank nicknamed the &amp;#8220;White Whale.&amp;#8221; When students placed their hands in
the water, vortices were mechanically generated (seen as swirling
patterns of the colored dyes). Other forms of turbulence can also
create&amp;nbsp;vortices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/square-tank.png" width="450" title="The square tank" alt="The square tank"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/square-projector.png" width="450" title="The projector" alt="The projector"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juan provides a demonstration on the effects of temperature
distributions on rotating fluids. At the center of the square tank is
an ice bucket, which cools the nearby water. The resulting temperature
contrasts in the water induce vortices analogous to the weather
patterns of the Earth&amp;#8217;s mid-latitudes. We used a camera and projector
to show the results from the rotating point of view. A video of this
demonstration can be found
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G26klqKKCmM"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego 1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/lego_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Lego 2" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/lego_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alex and other members of the DIYnamics team guided students in using
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; Rotating Tank to model &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt; concepts. The students were able to
compare the movement of dye in rotating versus non-rotating bodies of
fluid. Rotating columns are analogous to the movement of molten iron
in the Earth&amp;#8217;s outer&amp;nbsp;core.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group Photo 1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/group_photo_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Group Photo 2" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/la-tijera/group_photo_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Group photos of DIYnamics team members and our host Mr. Stephenson
taken during the May 12th (left) and May 19th (right) trips. It was a
pleasure to work with Mr. Stephenson, and he played a large part in
making the events run as smoothly as possible. This included visiting
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; beforehand to learn about &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFD&lt;/span&gt; and how it relates to his&amp;nbsp;curriculum.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="events"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="baroclinic instability"></category></entry></feed>