<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>DIYnamics - Field Reports</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/feeds/field-reports.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://diynamics.github.io/</id><updated>2021-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>Affordable materials for geoscience teaching demonstrations</subtitle><entry><title>Field Report: Teaching with DIYnamics at the Colegio La Esperanza, Tijuana, Mexico</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/tijuana-2021.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Nick Lutsko</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2021-04-12:/blog/tijuana-2021.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nick Lutsko, an assistant professor at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UC&lt;/span&gt; San Diego, describes his collaboration with the Colegio La Esperanza elementary school in Tijuana, Mexico, using DIYnamics to teach (remotely and in Spanish!) their students some fundamentals of rotating&amp;nbsp;fluids.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country &amp;#8212;- and in this case, the world(!) &amp;#8212;- share how they&amp;#8217;ve
used the DIYnamics kit and materials in local communities.&amp;nbsp;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How can I describe hurricane dynamics in rudimentary Spanish?”  This
was one of the questions I asked myself a few weeks ago while giving a
virtual demonstration of some DIYnamics experiments in (limited)
Spanish to the fifth and sixth graders at the Colegio La
Esperanza. The Colegio is a kindergarten and primary school in the La
Esperanza Colonia of Tijuana, Baja California, Mexico. Sited at the
top of a hill about nine miles south of the San Diego border, the
school was founded in 1989 by the non-profit Americas Foundation with
the goal of creating a social institution in an unorganized and
unincorporated yet highly populated area. The school’s curriculum has
a strong focus on the arts, and the Foundation works with volunteers
and other nonprofit organizations and schools in both San Diego and
Tijuana to stage cultural events and educational programs across the
border&amp;nbsp;region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/tijuana-2021/tijuana01.png" width="600" title="Tijuana 1" alt="Tijuana 1"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adding the food dye at the start of the Taylor-Proudman&amp;nbsp;experiment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met the director of the Americas Foundation, Christine Brady, at a
virtual reunion event for Princeton alumni last year &amp;#8212;- Christine
graduated from Princeton with a physics degree, and I did my
Ph.D. there. We stayed in touch over the past year, during which the
Colegio transitioned to remote learning in response to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19
epidemic.  It’s been a very difficult time for the Colegio, as many
students live in households without running water or
electricity.  Christine has led several funding drives to get
wireless-enabled cell phones for all the students who needed one to
follow along in Zoom&amp;nbsp;classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/tijuana-2021/tijuana02.png" width="600" title="Tijuana 2" alt="Tijuana 2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Answering questions after the demonstrations with Profesora&amp;nbsp;Lorena.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics experiments seemed like a fun way to teach the students
a little bit about how the atmosphere and the ocean work, so I reached
out to the DIYnamics team, who very kindly donated two of their
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-based tables to the&amp;nbsp;Colegio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the day of the demonstration, the Colegio moved the filming
equipment they use for virtual demonstrations to the ecology
classroom, where I was frantically building Legos (class with the
fifth graders started an hour earlier than I expected).  With
Profesora Lorena helping to explain the experiments and Profesor
José-Luis manning the cameras, we showed the kids Taylor-Proudman
columns and then how fronts develop. Using two cell phones, we had a
top-down view and a cross-section, so we could see the dye trapped in
columns or watch the swirling eddies from&amp;nbsp;above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/tijuana-2021/tijuana03.png" width="600" title="Tijuana 3" alt="Tijuana 3"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;José-Luis playing with the rotating tank before&amp;nbsp;class&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s always hard to get feedback over Zoom, but the kids seemed to
really enjoy the demonstrations. The sixth-graders in particular asked
lots of questions &amp;#8212; about weather and the oceans, about how
hurricanes and storms work, and about what it’s like to be a
scientist. There were also questions that were harder for me to answer
about the kinds of animals which live at the sea-floor and how long
sharks live. The teachers were also thrilled when they learned that
the kits are staying at the school. My only regret was that I didn’t
spend more time beforehand looking up meteorology terms in&amp;nbsp;Spanish.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="Field report"></category><category term="lego"></category><category term="K-12"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: A high schooler teaching fluid dynamics to middle schoolers using DIYnamics</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/isu-middle-school-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Natalie Kongable</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-05-25:/blog/isu-middle-school-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Natalie Kongable, a high school student working with DIYnamics team member Alex Gonzalez at Iowa State University, describes how she taught middle schoolers about extratropical cyclones using the DIYnamics &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;table.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country &amp;#8212;- share how they&amp;#8217;ve used the DIYnamics kit and materials
in their local communities.  Also, for this post we do not include any
photos of the actual event, because minors appear and we did not
attain release forms from parents permitting their photos to be used
in this way.  Keep that in mind for your own futurue K-12-facing&amp;nbsp;events!]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Natalie Kongable, and I am a senior in high school.  I was
able to purchase and build the DIYnamics rotating table setup.  I used
it with when I was doing research for my Iowa Academy of Science
project.  My project involved collaborating with Professor Alex
Gonzalez from Iowa State University (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt;) along with two graduate
students.  We selected one experiment (The demonstration of
extratropical cyclones) and I presented it to groups of middle school
aged students (6th through 8th&amp;nbsp;grade).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/isu-middle-school-2020/isu-middle-school-2020_01.png" width="600"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/isu-middle-school-2020/isu-middle-school-2020_02.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side views of the extratropical cyclones experiment taken just after
the blue dye and then red dye was injected.  [Note from Spencer: for
those familiar with thermal wind, notice how this baroclinic eddies
simulation actually looks a lot like thermal wind in these shots.
That&amp;#8217;s because these are taken during the initial spin-up phase before
the baroclinic eddies have kicked in.  Timescale&amp;nbsp;matters!]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiments proved to be successful in students understanding of
how cyclones were formed and maintained.  The students I worked with
were from two different schools, including a homeschool, and they
enjoyed the hands-on experiment.  I would love to have more
opportunities to present to students and continue doing outreach to
engage younger students and excite them about the science aspect of
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt;.  Another thing I would like to try would be to do it with more
groups than middle schoolers; I would like to try it with elementary
students, probably about 2nd or 3rd grade, and continue it with a
variety of ages all the way up to high&amp;nbsp;school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although for the most part this was a successful experiment, there was
one improvement I would have made.  I would have tried to find a
better dish that had a flat bottom.  Most of the issues I had were
largely in part due to the slight curve of the bottom. Some of those
problems included the frozen can sliding so it was not in the center
of the dish throughout the entire experiment, and the dye would settle
into the little crevice right around the edge of the dish so no
pattern would be formed.  I believe that these are issues I would be
able to solve if I continued using the apparatus for experiments in
the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was lots of fun to be able to interact with and teach the students,
and I truly look forward to continuing with this&amp;nbsp;project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-report"></category><category term="guest-post"></category><category term="middle-school"></category><category term="high-school"></category><category term="LEGO"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: DIYnamics tables in undergraduate teaching at Kiel University in Germany</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/mirjam-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Mirjam Glessmer</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-03-04:/blog/mirjam-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mirjam Glessmer describes how she and colleagues at Kiel University in Germany are using the DIYnamics tables in innovative ways in their&amp;nbsp;classrooms.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country &amp;#8212;- and in this case, the world(!) &amp;#8212;- share how they&amp;#8217;ve
used the DIYnamics kit and materials in their local&amp;nbsp;communities.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/mirjam-2020/mirjam-2020_01.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our group of students coming together at one tank to discuss
observations. Note that in the background a square tank is sitting on
a different rotating table, being spun up for the Rossby wave
experiment described&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we came across the &lt;a href="https://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/10.1175/BAMS-D-17-0215.1"&gt;DIYnamics
article&lt;/a&gt;
right after its publication,
&lt;a href="https://www.geomar.de/en/staff/fb1/od/tomartin/"&gt;Torge&lt;/a&gt; and I
(&lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/"&gt;Mirjam&lt;/a&gt;) were very excited about the
endless possibilities we saw opening up with an affordable tool like
the DIYnamics rotating table. We applied for, and were granted, money
for an “innovative teaching” project by &lt;a href="https://www.uni-kiel.de/en/"&gt;Kiel
University&lt;/a&gt;’s
&lt;a href="https://www.perle.uni-kiel.de/en"&gt;PerLe&lt;/a&gt; and built four DIYnamics
rotating tables (five if you count the one I built for personal use
;-)), which we’ve been working with for about a year now. Since we are
using them in a slightly different context than we’ve seen described
before, and also have modified and added some of the experiments, I
thought I’d report on it here. If you have any comments or suggestions
for us, please do get in&amp;nbsp;touch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;DIYnamics tables in undergraduate&amp;nbsp;education&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to using the DIYnamics rotating tables mainly for outreach
purposes which is the most common application I am aware of, we are
using them as part of a regular Bachelor-level class on &amp;#8220;ocean and
atmosphere dynamics&amp;#8221; at Geomar, Germany. I have gained a lot of
experience using a rotating table in undergraduate education at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFI&lt;/span&gt;,
Norway, but there we only had one – much bigger – table available. Now
we have four that can be used simultaneously! This is great for so
many&amp;nbsp;reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Time efficiency for the&amp;nbsp;instructor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With only one rotating table available, the typical setup I have used
was to have small groups of students come in at different times over
the course of a week or so, to do that week’s experiment with me. But
that meant that I would spend a lot of time in the lab, and a large
part of that time would be spent on waiting for the water on the
rotating table to have spun up into solid body rotation, as well as
prep time or cleaning, drying, putting away&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, wait times can easily be used for discussions of the
upcoming experiment, of the concept of a “spun up” body of water, of
how to judge whether or not a body of water is spun up or not, and
many other things. But those are things that don’t necessarily have to
be discussed in a setting of one instructor per each small student
group, they could just as well be discussed in student groups and then
in a larger&amp;nbsp;plenum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exchange between student&amp;nbsp;groups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the setup with one table and student groups coming in one after the
other, students would then write lab reports, submit them, and come
back for the next experiment. While I am sure there was some exchange
between student groups happening (which we could sometimes see from
eerily similar ways of expressing things between groups, or errors
propagating through several groups’ reports), that wasn’t an
instructional design&amp;nbsp;choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, however, when we have student groups working on the same
experiment at the same time in the same room, it is very easy to have
discussions both within individual groups and then across
groups. There are many instructional methods to choose from that
facilitate that kind of exchange, for example “think, pair, share”,
where students first think about a question individually, then pair up
with a partner (or the group at their tank) to discuss, and then
results are shared with and discussed in the whole&amp;nbsp;class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Seeing many implementations of the same&amp;nbsp;experiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason why these discussions are especially fruitful if done in
connection with simultaneously run tank experiments is that, even if
all student groups get the exact same instructions, two
implementations of the same experiment do not ever look the
same. There is always something that’s different. Maybe one tank is
spun up less than the others, or a bit wobbly, because someone bumped
into the table mid-spinup. Or the dye that is used as flow tracer has
a different density for one group (less diluted? Different
temperature?) and thus behaves differently. Or dye is put in a
different spot in the tank and thus shows different features of the
flow field. There are so many tiny things that can and will be
different from experiment to experiment, and it’s a great learning
experience to see an ensemble of different implementations and discuss
what change in boundary conditions made results look different rather
than just seeing one implementation and wrongly assuming that this is
the one and only way this experiment always turns&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Seeing many different experiments at the same&amp;nbsp;time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, there is of course the opportunity to have different student
groups work on different experiments simultaneously, which cuts down
on total prep and spin-up time and enables students to see a larger
variety of experiments. It also opens up the possibility that students
pick what experiment they want to work on – either new ones or
repeating older ones that they would like to take better pictures of
or modify something in the boundary conditions. This seems to be very&amp;nbsp;motivating!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Why we are using higher-walled&amp;nbsp;tanks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/mirjam-2020/mirjam-2020_02.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students working with an experiment on the Ekman bottom boundary
layer – one of the experiments that really benefit from a larger water
depth because this allows for observations of the development of the
boundary layer over&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the tanks we’ve seen used on the DIYnamics rotating
tables before, we chose to invest in some high-walled&amp;nbsp;tanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting feature of rotating fluid dynamics is that the flow
becomes 2D, so technically having a shallow layer of water is
completely sufficient to give a good representation of those
flows. And if we look at the aspect ratios of the oceans, they are in
fact extremely shallow compared to their horizontal extent. But it’s
easy to see a 2D flow in a shallow tank and assume that it’s 2D
because of the shape of the tank, not because of the flow itself. So
having an exaggerated third (depth) dimension that can be easily
observed by looking into the tank from the side actually helps drive
home the point that there is “nothing to see” on that dimension
because the flow really is as 2D as theory told us it would&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then there are of course the cases where the flow isn’t 2D, and
then a higher-walled tank is really convenient. For some experiments
where there are exciting things to discover by looking into the tank
from the side, check out &lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/2020/01/31/giving-it-a-side-eye-why-we-use-high-walled-tanks-on-our-rotating-table-flumefriday/"&gt;this blog
post&lt;/a&gt;
over on my&amp;nbsp;blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Experiment on planetary Rossby&amp;nbsp;waves&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first experiments we tried on our DIYnamics rotating table
was a “planetary Rossby wave” experiment. We hadn’t bought our
cylindrical tanks yet (read more about those below), so using a clear
plastic storage box was very convenient. Btw, this is one of the
experiments where looking into the tank from the side gives a lot of
interesting&amp;nbsp;insights!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/mirjam-2020/mirjam-2020_03.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Planetary Rossby waves in a square tank with a sloping&amp;nbsp;bottom.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the planetary Rossby wave experiment, we need a sloping bottom
(easiest done in a rectangular tank, but we’ve also run the same
experiment on a cone-shaped insert in a cylindrical tank) and a dyed
ice cube. When the tank is in solid body rotation, a dyed ice cube is
inserted in the shallow “eastern” corner of the tank (make sure it is
sitting far enough from the edge of the tank so it can turn around its
own axis unobstructed). For more details see &lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/2019/09/13/planetary-rossby-waves-on-beta-plane-a-super-easy-tank-experiment/"&gt;this blog
post&lt;/a&gt;,
but in a nutshell: The cold melt water sinks, setting up a column of
spinning water that sheds spinning eddies at regular intervals. Eddies
and ice cube propagate westwards. This is a really easy and fool-proof
experiment, and it looks&amp;nbsp;beautiful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Presenting the DIYnamics tanks at an institute&amp;nbsp;colloquium&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January, Torge and I gave a seminar presentation titled “you should
really play more often! Using tank experiments in teaching” at our
institute’s colloquium. In the abstract, we announced that we would
give a brief overview over our project and then give people the
opportunity to play – which we did. We had been expecting that maybe a
handful of our loyal friends would stick around after the presentation
to look at the tanks, but we were very surprised and excited to see
that pretty much everybody in the audience wanted to stay. We had set
up the four rotating tables with four different experiments and a
student presenting at each in the back of the room, and we ended up
running all the experiments repeatedly, until we were kicked out of
the room because the next lecture was about to start. It was really
motivating to see how everyone – students, PhD students, postdocs,
staff, professors – got really excited and wanted to learn more about
the tank experiments, discuss observations, modify and
experiment. This goes to show that an affordable rotating table is an
amazing tool at every level of education: There is always more to&amp;nbsp;discover!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/mirjam-2020/mirjam-2020_04.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A snapshot of the audience of our seminar presentation interacting
with the tanks and each other. We were running four experiments&amp;nbsp;simultaneously.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Follow our&amp;nbsp;experiences&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow our experiences with the DIYnamics rotating
tables, there are several options for&amp;nbsp;you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Torge and I have recently launched the “Teaching Ocean Science” blog
at
&lt;a href="https://www.oceanblogs.org/teachingoceanscience/"&gt;https://www.oceanblogs.org/teachingoceanscience/&lt;/a&gt;,
which is a joint effort of ourselves and other instructors, describing
fun hands-on stuff they do in their teaching, and students, who write
course assignments on what they are currently learning for the&amp;nbsp;blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, all the outgoing links in my guest post above are to
posts on my own blog, “Adventures in Teaching and Oceanography”, at
&lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/blog"&gt;https://mirjamglessmer.com/blog&lt;/a&gt;. I
use that blog as my own archive and document every new thing I try on
there, so you might want to sign up for email alerts or follow via my
Twitter &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/meermini"&gt;@meermini&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to writing about the DIYnamics rotating tables and what we
are up to with those (and you can be sure that if I played with a
tank, you will read it on that blog right away ;-)), I write a lot
about
&lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/2019/07/09/whats-kitchenoceanography-all-about/"&gt;#KitchenOceanography&lt;/a&gt;
(which are very easy hands-on experiments on ocean and climate topics
that you can do with household items) and
&lt;a href="https://mirjamglessmer.com/wave-watching/"&gt;#WaveWatching&lt;/a&gt; (observing
ocean physics everywhere, all the time). I also write about science
communication&amp;nbsp;issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to check out those blogs and as I wrote in the
beginning: Please get in touch if you have any comments or suggestions
for us. I am always happy to&amp;nbsp;chat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;This project has been funded by the PerLe fund for innovative teaching
through resources from the Federal Ministry of Education and Research,
grant number: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;01LP17068&lt;/span&gt;. The responsibility for the content of this
publication lies with the authors.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="guest-author"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="international"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: A lab planet at The Royal Observatory of Belgium</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/belgium-sphere-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Santiago Triana</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-10-31:/blog/belgium-sphere-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Santiago Triana of the Royal Observatory of Belgium shares incredible visualizations of rotating fluids in a sphere performed for research purposes and for public outreach events in Belgium and the Netherlands using the DIYnamics Lego&amp;nbsp;Table.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country &amp;#8212;- and in this case, the world(!) &amp;#8212;- share how they&amp;#8217;ve
used the DIYnamics kit and materials in their local&amp;nbsp;communities.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/mZWnvQ84rHc'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Visualizing wind shear in the lab planet by slightly changing the
rotation rate using the Lego &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IR&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;remote.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our group at the &lt;a href="https://www.astro.oma.be/en/"&gt;Royal Observatory of
Belgium&lt;/a&gt; studies the dynamics of fluid
layers inside rotating planets and moons.  It is very difficult to
imagine the kind of complex flows that we deal with.  To help us with
that, we built a miniature model of a fluid planet in our lab.
Rotation is of major importance in the study of planetary fluid
dynamics.  With our lab planet, we wanted to visualise at least
qualitatively how the fluid flow changes when the rotation speed
varies in time.  We needed our ‘planet’ to be as transparent as
possible and we also needed a way to control its rotation with some
level of&amp;nbsp;precision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_5.jpg" width="600"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_8.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Closeups of the components of the lab planet: (first image) the base
and bearings, (second image) the acrylic&amp;nbsp;globe.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We set to work building our lab planet using a 14&amp;#8221; diameter acrylic
globe, the same kind as used for outdoor lighting.  We used an
aluminium disc as a rotating platform mounted on a spherical ball
bearing, all resting on a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PVC&lt;/span&gt; stand.  We still needed a way to control
the rotation and that was when we heard about DIYnamics and thought it
would be a perfect match for our&amp;nbsp;purpose!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/woneJkvBn-4'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A beautiful wave-2 pattern has emerged in this video.  Wave-2 means
that the wave pattern that circles the globe has (roughly speaking)
two peaks and two&amp;nbsp;valleys.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, in order to visualise the currents in fluids, scientists
used Kalliroscope fluid, a rheoscopic fluid developed by Paul Matisse
in 1966, unfortunately not available anymore.  We considered mica
powder and other alternatives that ended up being not so great
compared to Kalliroscope fluid.  However, Daniel Borrero-Echeverry
from Willamette University devised an &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5045053"&gt;ingenious
way&lt;/a&gt; [1] to get the same rheoscopic
effect as Kalliroscope, simply using shaving cream!  We were able to
obtain large quantities of rheoscopic fluid, about 22 kg (or 48
pounds), which we used to fill the acrylic globe.  The technical
service from the observatory helped us with the machining of the
aluminium disc platform.  The globe is simply glued (with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RTV&lt;/span&gt;) to the
aluminium disc.  We made a threaded hole through the centre of the
disc which we use for filling/draining the&amp;nbsp;globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_1.jpg" width="300"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_2.jpg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_3.jpg" width="300"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_4.jpg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making Barbasoloscope in four easy steps (with pictures ordered left
to right then top to bottom): (1) dispense the Barbasol, (2) add
water, (3) mix, (4) let rest.  (There&amp;#8217;s a little more to it after that.  See &lt;a href=""&gt;this DIYnamics YouTube video&lt;/a&gt; for&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our setup is very close to the traditional DIYnamics except we don’t
use the Lazy Susan platform.  We use the motorised lego wheel to drive
the rotation via the aluminium disc platform.  The lego motor is
powerful enough to spin the whole device!  Mesmerising flow patterns
appear when the spin rate is changed slightly, which we do via the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IR&lt;/span&gt;
remote.  In the videos you can hear the motors whirring and change
pitch as we slow down or spin up the globe, you can see clearly the
shear in the flow caused by the accelerating/decelerating globe
surface in contact with the&amp;nbsp;fluid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/bDjIQadiCws'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Close up video of the DIYnamics Lego motor modified to drive the lab
planet rather than a Lazy&amp;nbsp;Susan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we let the globe spin for a while at a constant rate, the fluid
will eventually spin at the same rate as the globe, in sync, with no
or very little flow in the interior as indicated by the absence of any
patterns in the fluid. This might take 5 to 10 minutes to achieve.
If we reduce the speed of the globe just a notch, turbulence will
develop straddling the equator, induced by Görtler vortices most
likely.  However, if the fluid is still not yet spinning in unison
with the globe surface, turbulence develops within a very well defined
band, which we can see in the videos.  We can’t claim we understand
all features we see in the flow but we do recognise many, some of the
them resembling patterns we see in Jupiter, Saturn (think of the polar
hexagon), or the Earth’s&amp;nbsp;atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_6.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching with the lab planet at Open Door Day at the European Space
Agency centre, Noordwijk, the&amp;nbsp;Netherlands.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lab planet has been a real success during our outreach campaigns,
more than we anticipated!  We have had already a number of open days
here at the Observatory, as well as in the Brussels Planetarium and
last year we took the device to the annual open door day at the
European Space Agency’s centre in Noordwijk, the Netherlands.  During
these sessions we engage a general audience and discuss various topics
related to fluid dynamics at the planetary&amp;nbsp;scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/belgium-sphere-2019/belgium-sphere-2019_7.jpg" width="400"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching with the lab planet at an Open Day public outreach event at
the Royal Observatory of&amp;nbsp;Belgium.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lab planet is a reality thanks to Antony Trinh, Jeremy Rekier,
Santiago Andres Triana, the technical service at the Royal Observatory
of Belgium, and of course the DIYnamics team for their brilliant&amp;nbsp;idea!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/bTeULCHjXJg'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Flows generated in the lab planet by slightly slowing down the
rotation&amp;nbsp;rate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Borrero-Echeverry, D., Crowley, C. J., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Riddick,
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;T. P.&lt;/span&gt;(2018). Rheoscopic fluids in a post-Kalliroscope world. Physics
of Fluids, 30(8), 1–6.
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5045053"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5045053&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="guest-author"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="international"></category><category term="barbasoloscope"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: Teaching with DIYnamics at Iowa State University</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/iowa-state-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Alex Gonzalez</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-08-27:/blog/iowa-state-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Professor Alex Gonzalez at Iowa State University shares how he has used DIYnamics in his&amp;nbsp;classroom.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note from Spencer: This post is part of our ongoing &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt; series, where DIYnamics users across
the country (and one day, the world) share how they&amp;#8217;ve used the
DIYnamics kit and materials in their local&amp;nbsp;communities.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZdFOFROqVS0'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Video footage by Prof. Gonzalez of a beautiful demonstration of Ekman
transport.  Near solid boundaries, such as near Earth&amp;#8217;s surface for
the atmosphere, the ocean floor, and the bottom of the tank ifor the
DIYnamics table, friction with the solid surface changes how the fluid
flows compared to far away from the surface, where friction can be
mostly&amp;nbsp;ignored.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I purchased and built a DIYnamics rotating tank and used it in my
undergraduate Dynamics I course at Iowa State University (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt;) during
the 2019 spring semester.  Six experiments were conducted throughout
the semester: 1) Solid body rotation, 2) Dye stirring/Rossby number,
3) Baroclinic eddies, 4) Taylor Proudman effect, 5) Fronts, and 6)
Ekman layers.  I led the first experiment on solid body rotation while
the other five experiments were co-led by one to three students in the
class.  The experiments were quite successful overall and will
continue to be used in dynamics and other courses at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some highlights, including photos and videos, are shown below. Some
issues to address for future improvement are also discussed. Any
feedback would be greatly&amp;nbsp;appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/iowa-state-2019/iowa-state-1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Students awaiting (and one performing) the solid-body rotation
demonstration on the DIYnamics&amp;nbsp;table.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baroclinic eddies (no photos): The baroclinic eddies experiment was
not as successful as the others due to the lack of a flat bottom on
the rotating tank and possibly the use of a too small of a cold can at
the center.  Anyone else have similar&amp;nbsp;problems?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/iowa-state-2019/iowa-state-2.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side view of the solid-body rotation demonstration.  Notice the dye
sinking basically straight down to the bottom, with little horizontal
movement.  That means there&amp;#8217;s no relative fluid flow: all of the water
is rotating at the same rate as the tank.  As if it were a &amp;#8220;solid
body&amp;#8221;.  Get&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lack of flat bottom: One student constructed a flat bottom for one of
the two tanks that worked quite well for the experiments but over the
semester the bottom absorbed water so a more solid flat bottom is
planned to be constructed in the future.  Any ideas out there for how
to do this&amp;nbsp;affordably?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/iowa-state-2019/iowa-state-3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An overhead photo of a Taylor column demonstration.  A thin metal
puck is placed at the bottom of the tank, and after solid-body
rotation is reached, dye is injected and the rotation rate is
decreased.  This causes the dye to move toward the puck.  But, rather
than just going over it, the dye gets deflected around &amp;#8212;- as if the
puck extended all the way to the&amp;nbsp;surface.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fronts (aka the &amp;#8220;slumping dye cylinder&amp;#8221;): The fronts experiment was
the most difficult experiment to execute due to the fact that the
salty dyed water in the center kept leaking slightly into the exterior
fresh clear water.  We tried several methods and the one that worked
best was to use A &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOT&lt;/span&gt; of petroleum jelly to seal the bottom and
prevent leaking (following &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MIT&lt;/span&gt;’s weather in a tank) but it still
leaked.  Additionally, the can was removed possibly too abruptly and
induced extra momentum.  Any suggestions for how to get a better&amp;nbsp;seal?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="guest-author"></category><category term="university-teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: Saturdays at Seaport Museum’s “Fisharium” in Philadelphia, PA</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/philly-museum-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Abigale Wyatt</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-08-05:/blog/philly-museum-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Princeton University graduate student Abigale Wyatt shares the awesome outreach she and classmates are doing weekly in Philadelphia using&amp;nbsp;DIYnamics!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note: This post is part of a new series we&amp;#8217;ve started, &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt;, where students, teachers, and other
DIYnamicists tell us (and you) in their own words how they are using
DIYnamics in their schools and communities.&amp;nbsp;-Spencer]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Outside the Independence Seaport Museum, situated right on the
Delaware River in Philadelphia, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturdays are for science at the Independence Seaport Museum in
Philadelphia! A group of Princeton PhD students, Abigale Wyatt,
Allison Hogikyan and Tsung-Lin Hsieh, from the Geosciences department
and Atmosphere and Ocean Sciences program have been visiting the
museum regularly to give demonstrations using the DIYnamics&amp;nbsp;table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-2.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allison using &lt;a href="earth.nullschool.net"&gt;nullschool.net&lt;/a&gt; to talk to
visitors about how our demonstrations correlate to real-time ocean and
atmosphere&amp;nbsp;circulations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the recently opened exhibit “River Alive” that emphasizes how
local Philadelphians are impacted by and affect the Delaware River, is
the “Fisharium,” a perfect lab for demos using the rotating tank set
up. The space comes with a lab bench, faucet, and some friendly fish
to keep us company. Using velcro to stabilize the lego motor allows us
to quickly set up two rotating tanks and a stationary beaker to
demonstrate the impact of rotation on water’s&amp;nbsp;motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Visitors to the museum come in all shapes and sizes. This group of
adults was fascinated by the baroclinic instability experiment that
demonstrates how rotation plus a temperature difference can generate
unique physical&amp;nbsp;structure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The museum’s interest is in all things sea-related, including exhibits
on boat making, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; Naval history and even a new tattoo exhibit. It’s a
great space to engage with local visitors about science in a casual
environment. Our table is also a nice addition to the museum’s already
diverse biology experiments and provides an opportunity for anyone to
ask about our current research. The setting is perfect for both solo
visitors and large groups, giving us space to adjust for everyone to
have a fully hands on&amp;nbsp;experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-4.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A group of visiting Girl Scouts stops by our table to talk about
ocean circulation. After watching the dye spread and diffuse in the
still tank on the right, they’re taking turns adding dye to the
rotating&amp;nbsp;beaker.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been a great opportunity for us to chat with the public about
our science and hone our scicomm skills. We’ll be continuing our
collaboration with the museum into the next school year so if you’re
in the Philadelphia area on a Saturday afternoon, come check us&amp;nbsp;out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/philly-museum-2019/philly-museum-5.png" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The “Fisharium” fish watching over the rotating fluid&amp;nbsp;experiments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="guest-author"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="public"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Report: DIYnamics at the Children’s Water Festival at UC Irvine</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/water-fest-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Alex Arnold</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2019-05-20:/blog/water-fest-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Graduate student Alex Arnold explains how she and fellow students used DIYnamics to teach young students about the Great Pacific Garbage&amp;nbsp;Patch&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Update 2019-08-05: Since this was originally posted, we have
commissioned other DIYnamics users outside of our core team to write
their own posts about how they are using our materials in their
schools and communities.  We&amp;#8217;re calling the series &lt;a href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/category/field-reports.html"&gt;Field
Reports&lt;/a&gt;, and we&amp;#8217;re retroactively naming
Alex&amp;#8217;s great post below the inaugural Field Report.  Thanks again
Alex!&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8212;Spencer]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/water-fest-2019/water-fest-1.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt; Graduate students Alexandrea Arnold and Daniel Clements at the
Children’s Water&amp;nbsp;Festival&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;XEP&lt;/span&gt;, the graduate student organization for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;’s Atmospheric and
Oceanic Sciences department (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt;), teamed up with DIYnamics for the
Children’s Water Festival held at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UC&lt;/span&gt; Irvine in late March.  Over 7,500
elementary school students attended this two day event, where students
learned about different elements within the water cycle through
different twenty minute&amp;nbsp;presentations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, the focus of our demonstrations was on the Pacific Garbage
Patch and the underlying mechanisms that help contribute to the growth
of the patch in the ocean.  We started our demonstrations by talking
about the water cycle, reinforcing the point that both water and the
trash that water can bring along with it can eventually run into the&amp;nbsp;ocean!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/water-fest-2019/water-fest-2.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Randy, Daniel, and Ingrid talking about the components of the water&amp;nbsp;cycle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happens to the trash once it gets into the water?&lt;/strong&gt;  Well&amp;#8230;that
depends on the material.  We used a large tank with different objects
to teach about density and buoyancy.  Some of our objects floated above
the water, some of the objects sank, and some things float within the
tank &amp;#8212;- showing that the Pacific Garbage patch is not only a problem at
the very surface of the&amp;nbsp;ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/water-fest-2019/water-fest-3.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Getting ready to demonstrate some cool&amp;nbsp;science!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is the Pacific Garbage Patch located where it is?&lt;/strong&gt; Earth’s
rotation!  Here we used the DIYnamics tanks to show that the rotation
of the Earth influences ocean currents, which help to push the garbage
into one centralized patch.  We modeled this using rotating tanks as
our &amp;#8220;ocean&amp;#8221; and dye as our &amp;#8220;garbage&amp;#8221;.  Without the rotation, the
&amp;#8220;garbage&amp;#8221; was able to spread uniformly, all across the &amp;#8220;ocean&amp;#8221;, but
with rotation the dye formed a&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;patch&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/water-fest-2019/water-fest-4.jpg" width="600"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Randy pouring dye into our non-rotating tank after asking the
students to make their own hypothesis about how the &amp;#8220;garbage&amp;#8221; would
behave with and without&amp;nbsp;rotation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had so much fun spending two days with students and teachers from
classrooms all over Orange County - we can’t wait for next year!
Thanks to DIYnamics for teaming up with us for this amazing&amp;nbsp;event!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Field Reports"></category><category term="field-reports"></category><category term="outreach"></category><category term="K-8"></category><category term="ocean"></category><category term="Pacific Garbage Patch"></category></entry></feed>