<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>DIYnamics - news</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/feeds/news.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://diynamics.github.io/</id><updated>2018-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>DIYnamics featured on UCLA Physical Sciences website</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/ucla-website-story.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-03-25:/ucla-website-story.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The UCLA Division of Physical Sciences has a new article on DIYnamics on their main website and has added DIYnamics to its Outreach page.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ucla-physci-pic1" src="{filename}../images/ucla-phy-sci-site-snippet.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snippet from the UCLA Physical Sciences website with the link to the
story they commissioned about DIYnamics.  How cool is that?!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This isn't exactly an event, but it's exciting enough that we felt it
deserved a post anyways!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of March 2018, the DIYnamics project is now featured in multiple
places on the official website of the UCLA Physical Sciences Division
(link to main site &lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;;
permalink to the DIYnamics story
&lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/spinlab/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  Not only
that, they have also listed us as one of the "Year-Round Programs"
available for community and K-12 outreach on their &lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/outreach/"&gt;outreach
page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Physical Sciences Division, one of five divisions of the UCLA
College of Letters and Sciences, oversees the Atmospheric and Oceanic
Sciences Chemistry &amp;amp; Biochemistry, Earth, Planetary, and Space
Sciences, Mathematics, Physics &amp;amp; Astronomy, and Statistics
Departments, collectively home to thousands of students and hundreds
of faculty and staff.  With all of the amazing research and outreach
acivities that goes on across the division, it's a real honor for us
to be featured on their page so prominently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to Lisa Garibay of the UCLA Physical Sciences Divison for
initially taking an interest in us, writing the article, and getting
us featured on both pages.  They say any publicity is good publicity,
in which case this is absolutely fantastic publicity!  We're looking
forward to getting our materials into the hands of even more educators
thanks to these links.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="press"></category><category term="colleges"></category></entry></feed>