<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>DIYnamics - news</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/feeds/news.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://diynamics.github.io/</id><updated>2020-12-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated><subtitle>Affordable materials for geoscience teaching demonstrations</subtitle><entry><title>Portable Platforms - The DJ Table and the HT3</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/dj-ht3-tables-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-22T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Taylor Lonner</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-12-22:/blog/dj-ht3-tables-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In addition to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; revamp in the form of the Technic Table, DIYnamics has recently developed two brand new systems emphasizing portability, ease of assembly, and broad-range rotational capability: the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/dj-ht3-tables-2020/dj_table_annotated.png" width="600" title="DJ Table complete setup" alt="DJ Table complete setup"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introducing the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table! As the first DIYnamics table that
incorporates portability in the design, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table is the perfect
kit for schools and universities who want to showcase advanced fluid
dynamics phenomena in their classrooms and lecture&amp;nbsp;halls.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table is a three part system consisting of modified cart, a
high-torque record player, and a tank.  The modified cart has standard
utility shelf posts such that the height can be adjusted by one inch
increments and the only tool needed for assembly is a mallet.  The
cart is also the only part of the system that requires assembly and is
easily a one-person job.  We offer a variety of options for both new
and used record players, but highly suggest scouring the internet (and
local garage sales) for second-hand record players.  Record players
that lack a tone arm or functioning audio ports may seem like junk to
music enthusiasts, but are perfect for fluid dynamics experiments!
Finally, we provide a few different options for tanks.  While we
recommend our custom-designed tanks with centered holes for mounting
to record players, if you have your own tank, we also provide options
for elevation blocks such that you don&amp;#8217;t have to worry about the
record pin being in the way.  Overall, the pricing for the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table
ranges from $600-$1500 depending on your choice of record player and
tank.  This averages to about 1/5 the price of our more advanced
system, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table is well suited for schools looking to share a kit between
classrooms or lecture halls.  The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table&amp;#8217;s modified cart has locking
wheels and the system maintains a minimal footprint for easy storage.
Situated on the cart, the star of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table is the high-torque
record player which can generate rotation rates from 17 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; to 117 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt;
(depending on the specific model).  This rotation range makes the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt;
Table perfect for rapidly rotating experiments such&amp;nbsp;as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taylor&amp;nbsp;columns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Column collapse and&amp;nbsp;frontogenesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ekman&amp;nbsp;pumping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Centrifugal&amp;nbsp;forcing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corner vortices (in a square&amp;nbsp;tank)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spin up&amp;nbsp;demonstrations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Columnar (vertical)&amp;nbsp;convection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of columnar convection can be seen below.  The
visualization is accomplished with green food dye distributed using a
spray&amp;nbsp;bottle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/dj-ht3-tables-2020/vertical_convection.gif" width="600" title="Columnar Convection" alt="Columnar Convection"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/dj-ht3-tables-2020/ht3_annotated.jpg" width="600" title="HT3 complete setup" alt="HT3 complete setup"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introducing the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;!  The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; is our most ambitious kit to date.
Boasting a powerful turntable, meter-scale tank, and built in
visualization deck, this system can be used for demonstrating
geophysical fluid dynamics everywhere from a classroom or lecture hall
to a museum or a outreach science&amp;nbsp;festival.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; is a multi-part system optimized for portability,
accessibility, and ease of assembly.  The custom acrylic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; tank has
a maximized diameter while still fitting through a standard doorframe
and comes pre-drilled with mounting holes on a 2.5-inch lip for the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; visualization deck.  The visualization deck consists of a
polycarbonate plate held above the tank with three legs and it allows
users to place sensors in the rotating frame of the tank, including
phones and cameras to record and stream video.  The tank sits on a
powerful turntable, capable of maintaining a consistent low rotation
rate with over 25 gallons of water in the tank.  Finally, we encourage
those who want to invest in an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; to purchase the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt; (Taylor-Henry
Cart) - a multi-purpose cart designed by our team to make the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; a
broadly useful and accessible teaching device.  Low to the ground to
enable children to look over the tank, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt; sits on 5-inch locking
casters which turns the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; into an all-terrain vehicle.  With the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt;, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; system can easily be carted from classroom to classroom,
or across campus from lecture hall to lecture hall.  The lower deck on
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt; is ideal for storing your power, as well as dyes and other
visualization tools.  Additionally, the cart&amp;#8217;s handlebar can be bent
to provide a platform for controls, or completely stowed under the
lower deck to make 360 degrees of viewing available.  Most
importantly, the entire system (both the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt;) can be
assembled without any power tools!  The cost of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; kit with the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THC&lt;/span&gt; is&amp;nbsp;$4,800.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; system is a flexible device that was designed with large-scale
outreach in mind, but with careful set-up and leveling, it has the
potential for being a research device.  The visualization deck can
also be used to house measurement instrumentation including motion
tracking and thermometry systems.  The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; turntable is capable of
rotating from 0.16 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; to 13.3 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; which makes this system ideal for
experiments such&amp;nbsp;as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thermal wind&amp;nbsp;flows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ocean Garbage Patches and Ekman&amp;nbsp;Pumping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baroclinic&amp;nbsp;instability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Columnar&amp;nbsp;convection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanical turbulence (i.e., Great Red Spot&amp;nbsp;experiments)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-rotating evaporative convection (solar-style&amp;nbsp;convection)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rossby&amp;nbsp;waves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video shows a baroclinic instability demonstration on
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="480"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/HTm3U8mfE1Y'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit the DIYnamics Kits page &lt;a href="/pages/kits.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn more
about the original Do-It-Yourself rotating tank platform &amp;#8212; the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;
Table &amp;#8212; and its newly-released successor: the Technics Table. If you
are interested in sharing your experiences with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table or the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;, feel free to contact us on Twitter at
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/diynamicsteam"&gt;@DIYnamicsTeam&lt;/a&gt; or email at
&lt;a href="mailto:diynamicsteam@gmail.com"&gt;diynamicsteam@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="dj"></category><category term="ht3"></category><category term="thc"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>The Technics Table - A Robust and Consistent $80 DIY Rotating Tank Platform</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/technics-table-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Norris Khoo</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-11-19:/blog/technics-table-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Technics Table is the upgraded successor to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table. Available for $80, the Technics Table features a more robust design to provide a more consistent user&amp;nbsp;experience.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/technics-table-complete-setup.png" width="600" title="Technics Table complete setup" alt="Technics Table complete setup"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introducing the Technics Table! As with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table, the rotating tank platform consists of a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly, lazy susan and tank. Hands-on demonstrations provide insight into the forces responsible for our (or other) planet&amp;#8217;s weather, ocean currents, magnetic field and&amp;nbsp;more!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is an affordable yet effective way to build your own rotating tank platform? One of our answers is combining LEGOs and a lazy susan! From outreach events to classrooms, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table provides opportunities for audiences of all ages to perform experiments start to finish themselves. The Do-It-Yourself approach encourages analytical thinking as teachers and students reason together in establishing a model and relating observations with the world around us. After its use in facilitating a diverse range of experiments, we have received feedback that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table is an effective rotating tank platform but features several opportunities for improvement. Meanwhile, the DIYnamics community has been pushing the envelope on the capabilities of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table necessitating a robust design to&amp;nbsp;match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/lego-table-lego-assembly.png" width="400" title="LEGO Table LEGO assembly" alt="LEGO Table LEGO assembly"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/technics-table-lego-assembly.png" width="400" title="Technics Table LEGO assembly" alt="Technics Table LEGO assembly"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table (L) versus the Technics Table (R) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assemblies. The modules serve as a mount for the motor, battery and drive wheel rotating the lazy susan. Between (L) and (R), the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly has been upgraded to a beefier design for much improved&amp;nbsp;consistency.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we introduce the Technics Table! The Technics Table draws its name from Technics pieces &amp;#8212; a variant of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; pieces featuring interlocking beams and pins. Rather than reinventing the wheel, the Technics Table retains the core layout of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table consisting of a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly, lazy susan and tank. The second generation builds upon its predecessor by improving the sturdiness and stability of the system with changes to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly. The revamped &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly is constructed with Technics pieces and is built atop a broad baseplate. The Technics Table can be purchased in its entirety for $80 &amp;#8212; only $25 more than the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;Table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/design.png" width="400" title="Technics Table Technics pieces" alt="Technics Table Technics pieces"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/cad.png" width="400" title="Technics Table CAD design" alt="Technics Table CAD design"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(L) The Technics Table &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly with arm detached. The new design utilizes Technics pieces and features a broad baseplate. Compared to traditional &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; bricks, Technics beams and pins provide stronger connections difficult to pull apart. Instead of holding the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly in place with a rubber slip pad, there is now ample room to place down weights (e.g. water bottles) to keep the module stationary and in contact with the lazy&amp;nbsp;susan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(R) The Technics Table was created and documented with the help of the &lt;a href="https://www.ldraw.org/"&gt;LDraw&lt;/a&gt; family of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; software. Bricksmith (pictured above) enables developing designs in a digital domain and LPub facilitates publishing designs to&amp;nbsp;instructions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Technics Table has demonstrated itself to be a consistent rotating tank platform for driving experiments! Prior inconveniences with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table, such as the arm falling off or the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; assembly shifting, have abated to non-issues. Although the Technics Table features a higher upfront cost  compared to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt; Table, the new design enables users to depend on a consistent experience for each&amp;nbsp;experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="600" height="340" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/b4ARJls03YA" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, home to Earth Sciences research at Columbia University, held an open house &lt;a href="https://openhouse.ldeo.columbia.edu/"&gt;event&lt;/a&gt; in October 2020. We utilized the Technics Table to perform a variety of experiments illustrating the impact of planetary rotation on the fluid motions of our atmosphere, oceans and planetary&amp;nbsp;interior.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/mechanically-generated-vortices.jpg" width="600" title="Mechanically generated vortices" alt="Mechanically generated vortices"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(U) Technics Table experimental results and (D) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt; Juno &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/image-feature/jpl/churning-texture-in-jupiter-s-atmosphere"&gt;satellite image&lt;/a&gt; of Jupiter&amp;#8217;s atmosphere. Turbulence and rotation interact to form circular structures known as eddies &amp;#8212; fluid motions in the tank are analogous to storm systems such as Jupiter&amp;#8217;s Great Red&amp;nbsp;Spot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/juno-jupiter.jpg" width="600" title="Storms systems on Jupiter. Image credit: NASA Juno" alt="Storms systems on Jupiter. Image credit: NASA Juno"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the Technics Table, new developments include DIYnamics community driven add-ons that expand the utility of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based Tables! Visit the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based Tables page &lt;a href="/pages/lego.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and our YouTube channel &lt;a href="https://tinyurl.com/diynamicsvideos"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; and video guides on how to purchase, build and operate the Technics Table and&amp;nbsp;add-ons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/rotating-frame-camera-mount.png" width="400" title="Rotating frame camera mount" alt="Rotating frame camera mount"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/external-power-supply.png" width="400" title="External power supply" alt="External power supply"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(L) The rotating frame camera mount provides the ability to mount a camera in the rotating frame &amp;#8212; the perspective of an observer rotating in sync with the system. Capturing rotating frame footage is beneficial because it enables viewing fluid motions sans the visual effects of rotation. The rotating frame camera mount can be coupled with solutions like Zoom to livestream footage for real-time analysis. The design was developed by Marianna&amp;nbsp;Linz.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(R) The external power supply provides the ability to power the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based Tables with wall power instead of battery power. The adjustable voltage power adapter enables fine control over rotating rate &amp;#8212; perfect for experiments like Taylor columns! The design was developed by Alex&amp;nbsp;Gonzalez.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/technics-table-2020/sidewall-tank.png" width="400" title="Sidewall tank" alt="Sidewall tank"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sidewall tank provides an option for a tank of increased diameter and height. Using a larger tank expands the breadth and quality of experiments possible with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based&amp;nbsp;Tables.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit the DIYnamics Kits page &lt;a href="/pages/kits.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about our other larger Do-It-Yourself rotating tank platforms &amp;#8212; the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; Table. If you are interested in sharing your experiences with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEGO&lt;/span&gt;-Based Tables, feel free to contact us on Twitter at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/diynamicsteam"&gt;@DIYnamicsTeam&lt;/a&gt; or email at &lt;a href="mailto:diynamicsteam@gmail.com"&gt;diynamicsteam@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="lego"></category><category term="technics"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>Exciting new chapter for DIYnamics with three new Kits and new guides</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/kits-launch-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-10-28:/blog/kits-launch-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics has launched a major overhaul with three new kits and accompanying guides that range from a beefed-up Lego table to a nearly research-grade 3-foot diameter&amp;nbsp;device.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/kits-launch-2020/technics_table.gif" width="600" title="New Technics table" alt="New Technics table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The new Technics Table in&amp;nbsp;action!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DIYnamics &lt;a href="/pages/lego.html"&gt;Lego Table&lt;/a&gt; has proven to be a really valuable tool in
teaching fundamentals of atmospheric circulations, ocean currents,
planetary interior flows, and other core geoscience concepts.  Its low
cost, ease of ordering, assembly, and operation, and the simple fact
that it is mostly made out of toy Lego pieces help make the underlying
science seem approachable and fun to learn all the way down to the
elementary school level.  And at the other end of the educational
spectrum, its use in undergraduate and graduate courses continues to
expand across the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; and beyond: this semester with many
institutions teaching remotely due to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19, at least two courses
(at Harvard and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;) have provided Lego Tables for each of their
students to use remotely from their own homes &amp;#8212;- including multiple
students in China.  (More to come about these endeavors in future&amp;nbsp;posts.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, through our own uses and events and from reports
back from users in the wild, we&amp;#8217;ve come to find some limitations of
the original design.  For one, on repeated or extended use, sometimes
the motor arm will detach from the main assembly entirely&amp;#8230;not great
in the middle of a demonstration!  Another is that some &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OXO&lt;/span&gt; tables can
develop a tilt or slow spot, leading to tank-wide sloshing and/or the
rotation rate not staying constant.  Finally, for rotating tanks at
least there&amp;#8217;s no denying that bigger is better, and so the 6&amp;#8221; diameter
tanks that are most commonly used with the Lego Table can only
generate so much of a &amp;#8220;wow&amp;#8221; factor compared to much bigger&amp;nbsp;tanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/kits-launch-2020/dj_table.gif" width="600" title="New DJ Table" alt="New DJ Table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt; Table in&amp;nbsp;action!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spurred by these limitations, over the past couple years the DIYnamics
team &amp;#8212;- most of all Norris, Taylor, Henry, and Jon &amp;#8212;- have been
developing upgraded rotating tank platforms.  The result of their hard
work is three new &amp;#8220;kits&amp;#8221;, as we&amp;#8217;re now calling them, ranging from a
beefed-up Lego table to a nearly research-grade, 3-foot diameter tank
(but that&amp;#8217;s 100% portable).  We&amp;#8217;re happy to introduce these new kits
&amp;#8212;- the &lt;a href="/pages/lego.html"&gt;Technics Table&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="/pages/dj.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DJ&lt;/span&gt;
Table&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href="/pages/ht3.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  A series of
posts will follow this introductory one, each describing one of the
new kits in more&amp;nbsp;detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/kits-launch-2020/ht3_table.gif" width="600" title="New HT3 table" alt="New HT3 table"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HT3&lt;/span&gt; table in&amp;nbsp;action!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devices are only so helpful without instructions on how to build
and operate them, and so the team has also created &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; and video
guides for each device.  Along the way, we (mostly Norris) also
created guides for commonly needed &amp;#8220;peripherals&amp;#8221; like how to
livestream rotating frame footage &amp;#8212;- these were inspired by ingenious
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; solutions created by team members Alex and Marianna.  These too
are now all available via our &lt;a href="/pages/kits.html"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnUHxOSVY4G4OFbF8XL1qUg"&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;channel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We encourage you to check out the new materials now, and to look out
for our followup posts describing each kit in more detail, all coming&amp;nbsp;soon!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="organization"></category></entry><entry><title>New DIYnamics core team members</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/people-updates-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2020-04-21:/blog/people-updates-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics happily welcomes new members to our core team and updates the whereabouts of existing members and&amp;nbsp;alumni.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;DIYnamics has taken off far beyond what any of us expected when Jon,
Juan, Norris, and I got it off the ground in early 2017.  Now, over
three years later, we&amp;#8217;re happy to introduce some new members to the
core DIYnamics team and provide updates on those of us still around
and some alumni who have moved on to other exciting pursuits.  All of
this can be found on our freshly updated
&lt;a href="/pages/people.html"&gt;People&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These additions are long overdue &amp;#8212;- Alex, Jordyn, and Henry each have
been doing fantastic work for the DIYnamics efforts for a long time
already.  But better late than&amp;nbsp;never!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Alex&amp;nbsp;Gonzalez&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/people/alex-gonzalez.jpg" width="300" title="Alex Gonzalez" alt="Alex Gonzalez"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex joined the DIYnamics project in September 2019. He loves using
rotating tanks in the fluid dynamics classes he teaches at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt;. His
goal is to transition to placing more focus on applications rather
than theory in his classes. He is excited about using the DIYnamics’
rotating tanks in outreach activities to inspire a new generation of
scientists, especially those from underrepresented &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; groups. &lt;a href="https://tad.ge-at.iastate.edu/"&gt;Link
to Alex’s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISU&lt;/span&gt; Research Group&amp;nbsp;webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Jordyn&amp;nbsp;Moscoso&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/people/jordyn-moscoso.jpg" width="600" title="Jordyn Moscoso" alt="Jordyn Moscoso"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordyn is a graduate student in the Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences
department studying oceanography and ocean dynamics. She is excited to
be a part of the DIYnamics team and is working to bring DIYnamics into
the curriculum in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOS&lt;/span&gt; department. She is also a member of the
Society of Women Geoscientsts and uses DIYnamics to give hands on
experiences to women, girls, and people of other classically
underrepresented genders in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Henry&amp;nbsp;Gonzalez&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/people/henry-gonzalez.jpg" width="500" title="Henry Gonzalez" alt="Henry Gonzalez"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry Gonzalez is currently serving as the SPINLab Project Manager and
Space Magnetism Lab Manager, developing/coordinating everything from
spacecraft instruments to geophysical fluid dynamics experiments.  His
extensive knowledge in prototyping has paved the way to new modeling
systems for understanding the interiors and atmospheres of
planets.  Furthermore, he is working on the Henry &lt;span class="caps"&gt;III&lt;/span&gt; (H3) Model which
will be a portable geoshysical system that will be used for classroom
teaching of advanced concepts as well as outreach at public events and
interactive K-12 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="organization"></category></entry><entry><title>DIYnamics featured on UCLA Physical Sciences website</title><link href="https://diynamics.github.io/blog/ucla-website-story.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Spencer Hill</name></author><id>tag:diynamics.github.io,2018-03-25:/blog/ucla-website-story.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Division of Physical Sciences has a new article on DIYnamics on their main website and has added DIYnamics to its Outreach&amp;nbsp;page.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ucla-physci-pic1" src="https://diynamics.github.io/images/ucla-phy-sci-site-snippet.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snippet from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Physical Sciences website with the link to the
story they commissioned about DIYnamics.  How cool is&amp;nbsp;that?!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This isn&amp;#8217;t exactly an event, but it&amp;#8217;s exciting enough that we felt it
deserved a post&amp;nbsp;anyways!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of March 2018, the DIYnamics project is now featured in multiple
places on the official website of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Physical Sciences Division
(link to main site &lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;;
permalink to the DIYnamics story
&lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/spinlab/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  Not only
that, they have also listed us as one of the &amp;#8220;Year-Round Programs&amp;#8221;
available for community and K-12 outreach on their &lt;a href="https://www.physicalsciences.ucla.edu/outreach/"&gt;outreach
page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Physical Sciences Division, one of five divisions of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt;
College of Letters and Sciences, oversees the Atmospheric and Oceanic
Sciences Chemistry &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Biochemistry, Earth, Planetary, and Space
Sciences, Mathematics, Physics &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Astronomy, and Statistics
Departments, collectively home to thousands of students and hundreds
of faculty and staff.  With all of the amazing research and outreach
acivities that goes on across the division, it&amp;#8217;s a real honor for us
to be featured on their page so&amp;nbsp;prominently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to Lisa Garibay of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCLA&lt;/span&gt; Physical Sciences Divison for
initially taking an interest in us, writing the article, and getting
us featured on both pages.  They say any publicity is good publicity,
in which case this is absolutely fantastic publicity!  We&amp;#8217;re looking
forward to getting our materials into the hands of even more educators
thanks to these&amp;nbsp;links.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="news"></category><category term="press"></category><category term="colleges"></category></entry></feed>